<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
	<esp:name>Anzu</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Anzu the monstrous lion-eagle</esp:title>

	<html><head>
</head><body>

<p class="firstpara">The Anzu bird, half-lion, half-eagle, had been a mainstay of <esp:techterms term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> culture from at least the third millennium BC. He appears in <esp:link page="sumerian">Sumerian</esp:link> literary works <esp:link url="http://etcsl.orinst.ox.ac.uk/cgi-bin/etcsl.cgi?text=t.1.8.2.2&amp;display=Crit&amp;charenc=gcirc#" rel="external" hide-print="yes">as a wild creature of the mountains</esp:link>. He can also be tamed by the gods, as depicted in monumental sculpture. In 9th-century Kalhu, he was portrayed doing battle with the warrior god <esp:link page="ninurta">Ninurta</esp:link>, at an entrance to <esp:link page="ziggurat" bookmark="h_thezigguratandthetempleofninurta">the most important shrine</esp:link> of the royal <esp:techterms term="citadel">citadel</esp:techterms>.  <esp:glossary term="Layard, Austen Henry (person)">Layard</esp:glossary> discovered this sculpture in the mid-19th century, and shipped it to the <esp:techterms term="British Museum">British Museum</esp:techterms>. For generations this unnamed "dragon" or <esp:techterms term="demon">"demon"</esp:techterms> captivated the public imagination in many different ways. However, it took over half a century to rediscover Anzu's true identity.</p>

<esp:image file="anzu/layard_monuments2_pl5-REV.jpg" description="Layard, Monuments II pl. 5" position="inline"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/anzu/layard_monuments2_pl5-large.jpg" title="Large version of Layard, Monuments II pl. 5" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img188"><b>Image 1</b>: In <esp:glossary term="Layard, Austen Henry (person)"> Layard's</esp:glossary> glossy publication of sculptures from Nimrud and <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary> he simply labelled the <esp:techterms term="bas-relief">relief</esp:techterms> later known as Anzu and Ninurta as "Bas-reliefs from the entrance to a small temple (Nimroud)" <esp:ref referent="layard1849-53" page="vol II, plate 5"/>.</esp:bookmark> The engraving was made by the eminent <esp:glossary term="Gruner, Ludwig (person)">Ludwig Gruner</esp:glossary>. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/anzu/layard_monuments2_pl5-REV-large.jpg" title="Large version of Layard, Monuments II pl. 5" hide-print="yes">View large version (277 KB).</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>

<esp:h>Fight or flight: Anzu in Ninurta's temple</esp:h>
<esp:image file="anzu/malan_at_nimrud.jpg" description="Solomon Malan's sketch of the northern Anzu and Ninurta, while under excavation" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/anzu/malan_at_nimrud_large.jpg" title="Solomon Malan's sketch of the northern Anzu and Ninurta, while under excavation" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img43"><b>Image 2</b>: <esp:glossary term="Malan, Rev Solomon (person)">Solomon Malan</esp:glossary>'s sketch, made on the spot at Nimrud in 1950, shows the northern member of the pair of <esp:techterms term="bas-relief">bas-reliefs</esp:techterms> coming out of the ground   <esp:ref referent="gadd1938" page="plate XV"/>. The southern one, which originally stood opposite, has already been removed.</esp:bookmark> The tunnel to the left shows how Layard's men dug by following the temple walls. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/anzu/malan_at_nimrud_large.jpg" title="Solomon Malan's sketch of the northern Anzu and Ninurta, while under excavation" hide-print="yes">View large version (236 KB).</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>

<esp:image file="anzu/layard_ruins_small.jpg" description="The entrance to the small temple while under excavation, from Layard, Discoveries in the Ruins, p. 302" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/anzu/layard_ruins.jpg" title="Large image of entrance to the temple" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img189"><b>Image 3</b>: Contrast Layard's tidy image of the so-called "small temple" under excavation in 1850, showing a neatly paved floor and all the monumental sculpture standing in place, with Malan's sketch of the same scene <esp:ref referent="layard1853" page="302"/>. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/anzu/layard_ruins.jpg" title="Large image of entrance to the temple" hide-print="yes">View large version (171 KB).</esp:link></esp:bookmark></esp:caption> </esp:image>

<p>There were two ways into the shrine of the mighty god Ninurta, nestled into the southeast corner of the ziggurat at Kalhu. The most direct entrance was flanked by enormous stone human-headed lions. When the doors between them were opened, priests and the privileged few could gaze directly through an ante-chamber to the statue of the deity himself (<esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/ziggurat_2_large.jpg" title="Julian Reade's plan of Nimrud ziggurat and associated temples" hide-print="yes">Room A on the plan</esp:link>). Alternatively, they could enter and exit through a doorway just to the north of the lion gateway, and then turn back south into the antechamber or the shrine (<esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/ziggurat_2_large.jpg" title="Julian Reade's plan of Nimrud ziggurat and associated temples" hide-print="yes">Room B</esp:link>). Protective male figures holding branches were positioned on the courtyard side of the doorway, fish-cloaked figures on the interior side. A <esp:link page="nd1900" bookmark="img272">huge sculpture</esp:link> of king <esp:glossary term="Assurnasirpal II (person)">Assurnasirpal</esp:glossary> stood just to the right.</p>


<p>The doorway to Room B was lined on both sides with mirror-image depictions of the same extraordinary scene (<b>Image 1</b>). A towering male figure in a long robe bears down on a monstrous creature, half lion and half eagle, who turns back to him open mouthed, claws out. The bearded man's horned helmet and double wings mark him out as a god. His muscles bulge and he is laden with weapons. A <esp:techterms term="sickle">sickle</esp:techterms> and a sheathed sword hang from his body, while he clutches forked bolts of lightning in each hand. This can only be the culminating episode in <esp:link page="ninurta" bookmark="h_anzu"><i>The Epic of Anzu</i></esp:link>, where Ninurta cunningly defeats this <esp:techterms term="demon">demonic</esp:techterms> force of chaos, and reclaims the <esp:techterms term="Tablet of Destinies">Tablet of Destinies</esp:techterms> for the gods. </p>

<p>The image of Ninurta chasing Anzu out of his temple powerfully marries the militaristic ideals of Assyrian kingship with the importance of scholarly learning.  One the one hand, Ninurta must use intelligence as well as brute force to defeat the wicked Anzu. On the other, his quest is to recover the Tablet of Destinies, which records the gods' decisions about Assyria's future. <esp:link page="professions">Court scholars</esp:link> advised the Assyrian king on his military decision-making by interrogating the gods about their intentions, through various forms of <esp:techterms term="diviner">divination</esp:techterms>. Assyria went to war only with the gods' blessing, and with victory assured in the Tablet of Destinies. Assyrian <esp:link page="inscriptions">royal inscriptions</esp:link> increasingly acknowledged the role of scholarly divination in predicting divine support and garnering military success.</p>

<p>Assurnasirpal II commissioned the building of Ninurta's shrine early in the ninth century BC. When the royal court moved to <esp:glossary term="Dur-Šarruken (place)">Dur-Šarruken</esp:glossary>, and then to <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary>, in the late eighth and early seventh centuries BC, Ninurta was already losing royal patronage in favour of <esp:glossary term="Nabu (deity)">Nabu</esp:glossary>. Now that the empire had stabilised, learnedness was more fashionable than militarism. Nevertheless, Ninurta's temple survived nearly 200 years of royal neglect, and the twin monuments to his victory over Anzu remained standing, right until Kalhu's temples were pillaged by invaders at the end of empire in 612 BC <esp:ref referent="reade2002" page="201"/>.</p>

<esp:h>A monster unearthed: but which one?</esp:h>
<esp:image file="anzu/wellcome_m0007475.jpg" description="The Nimroud Gallery at the British Museum in the early 20th century" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/anzu/wellcome_m0007475_large.jpg" title="View large version of Nimroud Gallery image on Wellcome Images website" rel="external" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img190"><b>Image 4</b>: Well into the 20th century, the British Museum's Nimroud Gallery displayed Ninurta and Anzu as <esp:glossary term="Marduk (deity)">Marduk</esp:glossary> and Tiamat, adjacent to a restoration of the fish-cloaked figure that had stood with it in the temple. Look closely and you will spot that it doubles as a cupboard door!</esp:bookmark> Source: <esp:link url="http://wellcomeimages.org/" rel="external" hide-print="yes">M0007475</esp:link>, Wellcome Library, London. CC BY 4.0. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/anzu/wellcome_m0007475_large.jpg" title="View large version of Nimroud Gallery image on Wellcome Images website" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<esp:image file="anzu/anzu_ninurta.jpg" description="Anzu and Ninurta in situ in the British Museum" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=367087&amp;partId=1" title="British Museum catalogue entry on Anzu and Ninurta relief" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img191"><b>Image 5</b>: These days Anzu and Ninurta may be visited in Room 6 on the ground floor of the British Museum.</esp:bookmark> They are still accompanied by their protective <esp:techterms term="genie">genie</esp:techterms> and <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=365970&amp;partId=1">the fish-cloaked figure</esp:link> from the northern half of the doorway.  British Museum ME 124571. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=367087&amp;partId=1" title="British Museum catalogue entry on Anzu and Ninurta relief" hide-print="yes">View the British Museum's catalogue entry for this object.</esp:link> </esp:caption> </esp:image>

<p>Anzu came to light again only in June 1850. A visitor to Layard's excavations at Nimrud, the <esp:glossary term="Malan, Rev Solomon (person)">Reverend Solomon Malan</esp:glossary>, <esp:link page="ziggurat" bookmark="malan">vividly sketched the northern half of the pair of bas-reliefs</esp:link>, still in its earthen matrix and surrounded by discarded rubble (<b>Image 2</b>). A weary local workman sits propped up in its shade <esp:ref referent="gadd1938" page="pl. XV"/>. Malan's watercolour is the only surviving record of this object, as Layard decided to keep only the southern member of the pair (<b>Image 3</b>).</p>

<p>The sculpture arrived at the British Museum, as part of much larger shipment of Nimrud artefacts, in 1851. It was set up in the so-called Nimroud Gallery on the ground floor, in between the bas-reliefs of protective genies that had flanked it in antiquity (<b>Image 4</b>, <b>Image 5</b>).  But who these two powerful, well-matched figures were, no-one yet knew. The inscription running across the front was very badly worn, and the one on the back could not yet be deciphered. In his account of the excavations, Layard rightly inferred that the image "appears to represent the bad spirit driven out by a good deity; a fit subject for the entrance of a temple dedicated to the god of war" <esp:ref referent="layard1853" page="301"/>. That was as much as anyone could say for now.</p>

<p>Gradually over the next few decades, cuneiform script <esp:link url="/saao/knpp/essentials/discoverydecipherment/index.html" hide-print="yes" rel="external">began to make more sense</esp:link>. In 1876, a full quarter of a century after the arrival of the sculpture at the British Museum, the first clues as to Anzu's identity began to appear. Museum assistant <esp:glossary term="Smith, George (person)">George Smith</esp:glossary> published a book of translated Assyrian and <esp:glossary term="Babylonia (place)">Babylonian</esp:glossary> myths that aimed to relate this still difficult material to the much more familiar world of the Old Testament <esp:ref referent="smith1876"/>. The climax of the so-called "Chaldean account of Genesis" (now better known as the <esp:techterms term="Standard Babylonian">Standard Babylonian</esp:techterms> <esp:techterms term="Epic of Creation">Epic of Creation</esp:techterms>, or <i>Enūma Eliš</i>) featured a cosmic battle very like that shown in the bas-relief from Nimrud. The warrior god <esp:glossary term="Bel (deity)">Bel</esp:glossary> or Merodach — now known as <esp:glossary term="Marduk (deity)">Marduk</esp:glossary> — defeats the dragon <esp:glossary term="Tiamat (deity)">Tiamat</esp:glossary> with a sword and bow.</p>

<p>Smith confidently identified the hitherto mysterious monument from Nimrud as the "fight between Merodach (Bel) and the Dragon" <esp:ref referent="smith1876" page="62"/> and even used it on the front cover of the book. He undoubtedly knew that Tiamat was female: "Tiamat opened her mouth to swallow him", he translated  <esp:ref referent="smith1876" page="98"/>. Yet Anzu's snake-headed penis was clearly visible in the line drawing he used in the book, though was removed for the sake of Victorian modesty on the cover itself. At almost exactly the same time, <esp:techterms term="Assyriology">Assyriological</esp:techterms> dilettante <esp:glossary term="Talbot, William Henry Fox (person)">Henry Fox Talbot</esp:glossary> made almost exactly the same argument, explicitly bringing the apocryphal Old Testament book "<esp:link url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bel_and_the_Dragon" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Bel and the Dragon</esp:link>" into the argument <esp:ref referent="talbot1876"/> <esp:ref referent="robson2013"/>.</p>

<p>It was to be several more decades before the three monsters — Anzu, Tiamat, and Marduk's <esp:link url="http://www.dia.org/object-info/b50e37fa-0803-425c-92c9-d009262b1b7e.aspx" hide-print="yes" rel="external"><i>mušhuššu</i>-dragon</esp:link> — were disentangled. Meanwhile, the British Museum's curators started to label the Nimrud scuplture as "the conflict between the god Marduk or Bêl and the monster Tiâmat", and continued to do so until at least 1908 <esp:ref referent="britishmuseum1908" page="24"/>.</p>

<esp:h>From Zu to Anzu</esp:h>
<esp:image file="anzu/smith_cover.jpg" description="Anzu on the cover of George Smith's book" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/anzu/smith_cover_large.jpg" title="Large image of Anzu on the cover of George Smith's book" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img192"><b>Image 6</b>: For propriety's sake, Anzu lost his snake-headed penis on the cover of <esp:glossary term="Smith, George (person)">George Smith's</esp:glossary> 1876 book of translations <esp:ref referent="smith1876"/>.</esp:bookmark> Much confusion resulted, for many years. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/anzu/smith_cover_large.jpg" title="Large image of Anzu on the cover of George Smith's book" hide-print="yes">View large version of image (276 KB).</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>


<p>It did not take long to decipher the inscriptions on the slabs from the temple, establishing it as property of the god "Ninib". British Museum <esp:techterms term="Assyriology">Assyriologist</esp:techterms> <esp:glossary term="King, Leonard (person)">Leonard King</esp:glossary> published the first systematic translation of the temple texts in 1902 <esp:ref referent="king1902" page=""/> <esp:ref referent="grayson1996" page="nos.A.0.101.3, 5-7, 31"/>. W F Albright correctly read the name "Ninib" as Ninurta in 1915 <esp:ref referent="albright1915"/>. However, there was nothing in these inscriptions to identify the protagonists of the battle scene as Ninurta and Anzu. That was a long time coming.</p>

<p>Another of the narratives in Smith's anthology was the very fragmentary work that he named "The Sin of the God Zu" <esp:ref referent="smith1876" page="113-122"/>. At that point, in 1876, it was very hard to interpret its contents, except that "Zu" ran away after committing some crime against the gods, who then discussed how to react. As Smith noted, other inscriptions suggested that Zu "was  in the likeness of a bird of prey" <esp:ref referent="smith1876" page="119"/>. Gradually, as more pieces of <esp:techterms term="tablet">clay tablets</esp:techterms> were discovered, the composition we now call <i>The Epic of Anzu</i> began to take shape. But the process was very gradual indeed. In the late 1940s the Manchester Assyriologist Thomas Fish was still struggling with what the "Zu bird" must have looked like, and which god had defeated him, Marduk or Ninurta <esp:ref referent="fish1948"/>.</p>

<p>The monster's identity as "Anzu" rather than "the god Zu" gradually gained acceptance over the 1960s and 70s, as it became clear that the first cuneiform sign of the name must be the syllable <i>an</i> and not the (visually identical) divine marker DINGIR <esp:ref referent="landsberger1961"/> <esp:ref referent="civil1972"/>. Ilse Fuhr-Jaeppelt's <esp:techterms term="diachronic">diachronic</esp:techterms> analysis of Anzu's <esp:techterms term="iconography">iconography</esp:techterms> over the third to first millennium BC, together with Blahoslav Hruška's study and full critical edition of <i>The Epic of Anzu</i> finally put Anzu's identity beyond doubt, a full 125 years after he emerged from the earth of Nimrud <esp:ref referent="fuhr-jaeppelt1972"/> <esp:ref referent="hruška1975"/>. In the meantime, however, Anzu's image had taken on a life of its own, far beyond the confines of Assyriology.</p> 

<esp:h>Anzu in advertising</esp:h>

<esp:image file="anzu/Wellcome-Diary-1915-Anzu-advert.jpg" description="Diary page with printed advert showing eagle-lion monster Anzu at the top, with the words 'Dangerous Abbreviation' underneath" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/anzu/Wellcome-Diary-1915-Anzu-advert-large.jpg" title="Large version of Anzu advert in medical diary"  hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img193"><b>Image 7</b>: Anzu starring in a pharmaceuticals advert in <i>Wellcome's Medical Diary and Visting List</i> (1915). In the early twentieth century, pharmaceuticals firm Burroughs Wellcome and Company distributed around 35,000 of these pocket-sized diaries annually to doctors as a marketing tool.</esp:bookmark> Source: private collection. The Nimrud Project CC-BY-SA 3.0 <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/anzu/Wellcome-Diary-1915-Anzu-advert-large.jpg" title="Large image of Anzu advert in medical diary" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link> (763 KB).</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>In the early twentieth century, Anzu featured in an advert by pharmaceuticals firm Burroughs Wellcome &amp; Company (BW&amp;C) designed to defend its brands of medicines against commercial rivals (<b>Image 7</b>). Headed by businessman <esp:link url="http://www.wellcome.ac.uk/about-us/history/index.htm" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Henry Wellcome</esp:link>, BW&amp;C secured financial success in the early twentieth century by selling compressed forms of foodstuffs and medicines, trade-marked under the brand-name 'Tabloid' (but which are now better known as tablets). The company fiercely pursued any copyright infringement, through advertising campaigns and by threatening perpetrators with legal action <esp:ref referent="larson2009" page="12-13"/> <esp:ref referent="churchtansey2007" page="131–139, 284–285"/>.</p>


<p>As part of their brand protection campaign, BW&amp;C targeted chemists and druggists who passed off cheap home-made medicines as BW&amp;C branded versions, pocketing the profits. The company fought a decade of trade warfare with retail chemists over issues of drug substitution around 1900. <esp:ref referent="churchtansey2007" page="130-145"/>. They pitched adverts to doctors warning them of the dangers of imitation medicines, and the Anzu advert is once such example. Its sharp wording pushed doctors to write out BW&amp;C trade-marked names in their prescriptions, which forced chemists to dispense branded medicines and not cheaper substitutes. According to BW&amp;C's advert, abbreviating the 'Tabloid' brand-name was actively "dangerous" (<b>Image 7</b>), as it let unscrupulous chemists use dubious ingredients and endanger patients.</p>

<p>The Anzu advert appears in the 1915 edition of <i>Wellcome's Medical Diary and Visiting List</i>, a promotional tool distributed free to doctors <esp:ref referent="wf-m-pb-003-28"/>. These appointments diaries came complete with reference information, a handy pencil, and copious BW&amp;C advertisements. Each diary between 1906 and 1940 featured a different ancient civilisation, catering to a rising interest in history of medicine among the medical profession, and the 1915 diary was entirely Assyrian themed. A complete set of the diaries is now held in the <esp:link url="http://wellcomelibrary.org/" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Wellcome Library</esp:link> in London.</p>

<esp:h>Tablet stealers</esp:h>

<p>But why use an image of Anzu to represent cut-throat commercial practices? BW&amp;C likely understood that its well-educated audience of doctors would be familiar with the ancient mythologies depicted in their diaries. Each year they chose an appropriate mythological character to accompany their 'Dangerous Abbreviation' advert, assembling a motley crew of 'baddies' to symbolize commercial evil. Anzu's appearance in 1915 was preceded by the fearsome <esp:link url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medusa" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Gorgon Medusa</esp:link> from ancient Greek legend (1911), whose stare turned men to stone, and the <esp:link url="http://www.teara.govt.nz/en/1966/maori-art/page-4" hide-print="yes" rel="external">Maori <i>marakihau</i></esp:link> (1910), a deep-water monster that devoured passing sailors <esp:ref referent="wf-m-pb-003-24"/> <esp:ref referent="wf-m-pb-003-23"/> <esp:ref referent="horry2013" page="96-100, 110-113"/>.</p>

<p>Some of these characters were famously recognisable, others playfully obscure. And if the company was inviting medical doctors to play 'guess the monster', Anzu was likely one of the more familiar creatures, even if his name was not yet known. His image was famous from Layard's and Smith's books where he was known to represent dark malevolence, even though his exact identity as a bird-monster or dragon was uncertain. The pharmaceuticals company played on this familiarity, visualizing brand infringement practices as an evil creature that needed vanquishing.</p>

<p>Doctors who were familiar with the Assyrian battle scene image may also have noticed what was missing in in the BW&amp;C version: the force of good - the vanquishing hero. In the absence of the champion, was the audience invited to infer that the hero was company proprietor, Henry Wellcome, himself? Certainly, the implication was that in the fight between good and evil, BW&amp;C was the force of good. And Anzu, originally stealer of the Tablet of Destinies, now represented 'tablet stealers' of a pharmaceutical kind.</p>


<esp:author first-names="Ruth A." last-name="Horry"/>
<esp:author first-names="Eleanor" last-name="Robson"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/>
	</body></html>

</esp:page>
