<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
	<esp:name>Cat or dog?</esp:name>
	<esp:title>The model dog that became a cat</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>

<p class="firstpara">Small models of dogs are one of many types of protective <esp:techterms term="figurine">figurines</esp:techterms> found at Nimrud, which were used in Assyria to prevent evil and sickness from entering a building and plaguing its occupants. The bronze dog figurine shown in Image 1 was excavated in 1951-2 by the British School of Archaeology in Iraq and is now held in the <esp:link page="museumsuk" bookmark="maacambridge">Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology</esp:link>, Cambridge. It is one of six dog models found down a well in the <esp:link page="northwestpalace">North West Palace</esp:link> of king <esp:link page="assurnasirpal2">Assurnasirpal II</esp:link>. In the 60 years after its discovery and separation from the other models, this dog has acquired a new identity as a cat, due to its distinctly feline appearance.</p>

<esp:image file="maa/BSAI-ND2183-MAA-1956_5.jpg" description="Bronze figurine of four-legged animal, which appears very cat-like but probably represents a dog" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img103"><b>Image 1</b></esp:bookmark>: A cat or a dog? This Assyrian bronze figurine of a four-legged animal was discovered with five dog figurines down a well in the Northwest palace of king <esp:glossary term="Assurnasirpal II (person)">Assurnasirpal II</esp:glossary> in 1952 and is now in Cambridge's <esp:link url="http://maa.cam.ac.uk/maa/" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology</esp:link>. MAA 1956.5 (ND 2183). Photo: <esp:link page="copyright" bookmark="BISIimages">BSAI/BISI</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<esp:h>Found down a palace well</esp:h>

<esp:image file="maa/OatesOates2001-p64-Fig-36-courtyard80-room-NN-well-BSAI.jpg" description="Bronze figurine of four-legged animal, which appears very cat-like but probably represents a dog" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/maa/OatesOates2001-p64-Fig-36-courtyard80-room-NN-well-BSAI-large.jpg" rel="external" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img164"><b>Image 2</b></esp:bookmark>: Photograph taken during 1950s excavations of Courtyard 80 of the <esp:link page="northwestpalace">Northwest Palace</esp:link>, Nimrud. The well in Room NN is the rearmost of the two wells, visible behind the group of men. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/maa/OatesOates2001-p64-Fig-36-courtyard80-room-NN-well-BSAI-large.jpg" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image.</esp:link> Photo: <esp:link page="copyright" bookmark="BISIimages">BSAI/BISI</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Six <esp:techterms term="bronze">bronze</esp:techterms> figurines of dogs were discovered by excavators from the the <esp:techterms term="British School of Archaeology in Iraq">British School of Archaeology in Iraq</esp:techterms> (BSAI), led by <esp:glossary term="Mallowan, Max (person)">Sir Max Mallowan</esp:glossary>, during excavations of the <esp:link page="northwestpalace">Northwest Palace</esp:link> in 1951-2. Mallowan's team came across a deep well in the corner of Room NN (<b>Image 2</b>), which was filled with sludge that Mallowan described as being “the consistency of plaster of Paris" <esp:ref referent="mallowan1952" page="14"/>.  No electric pumps were available to dig out the well so the workmen had to scoop out the water and sludge by hand, aided only by heavy-duty winching equipment borrowed from the Iraq Petroleum Company. It was difficult and dangerous work as the well bottom repeatedly filled up with water, as Mallowan himself later recounted:</p>

<blockquote><p>"[T]he deeper we went and the more we cleared the well, the faster the water came in as the man at the bottom scooped the sludge into the bucket. Indeed, during the last stages of this operation the rapid inflow compelled us to start at midnight, and by the light of hurricane lamps to draw water continuously for six hours until dawn. From then until sunset the men were drawing up one oil-drum full of sludge followed by 40 gallons of water in alternative succession. By this method we managed to extract all of the sludge from the well." <esp:ref referent="mallowan1977" page="123"/></p></blockquote>

<p>Mallowan’s team cleared the well to a depth of around 25 metres and remarkable number of objects were found. The sludge had provided ideal conditions for preserving materials that would otherwise have decayed, such as fragments of Assyrian rope and wooden well equipment that had accidentally fallen in. Other objects appeared to have been deliberately thrown down the well in antiquity, by <esp:link page="northwestpalace" bookmark="afterassurnasirpal">invaders ransacking the building</esp:link>. Among them were fragments of <esp:techterms term="Nimrud ivories">carved ivory furniture</esp:techterms>, <esp:link page="maa-intro" bookmark="founddownawell">shell ornaments</esp:link>, pieces of horse harnesses, and six bronze figurines of dogs, each about the size of a human thumb. The dogs were given the excavation numbers ND 2182-ND 2186, ND 2214. Another bronze dog (ND 3209) was discovered in an <esp:techterms term="stratified">unstratified</esp:techterms> context, in a rubbish dump "along the <esp:techterms term="acropolis">acropolis</esp:techterms> wall", and a fragmentary clay dog (ND 5304) in a dump at <esp:link page="ninurta">Ninurta's</esp:link> temple.</p>

<esp:h>“Don’t think, bite!" – Assyrian protective figurines of dogs</esp:h>

<p>The <esp:techterms term="findspot">findspots</esp:techterms> of the dog figurines alone do not give many clues as to their purpose. Wider evidence from Assyria though suggests that the dogs had a <esp:techterms term="rite, ritual">ritual</esp:techterms> function. They were one of several types of figurines that guarded against evil entering buildings and plaguing the inhabitants within <esp:ref referent="green1983"/>. Protective figurines were placed under doorways, in building thresholds, or in corners – all places where evil spirits and disease lurked. A ritual against evil that involves protective figurines of dogs is known from a <esp:techterms term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablet</esp:techterms> from the city of <esp:glossary term="Assur (place)">Assur</esp:glossary>, written in the reign of king <esp:glossary term="Assurbanipal (person)">Assurbanipal</esp:glossary>. To prevent evil from crossing the threshold of a building, the instructions prescribe burying two sets of five model dogs underneath a doorway <esp:ref referent="wiggermann1992" page="15-16, KAR 298"/>.</p>


<p>In fact, some sets of dog figurines have been discovered buried under doorways in Assyrian buildings. One example is a group of five clay dogs found buried under a doorway in the North Palace at <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary> during mid-19th century excavations, and now in the British Museum (<b>Images 3 and 4</b>) <esp:ref referent="curtisreade1995" page="116-117"/>. <!-- by Loftus. Ref given is Gadd, RA 19 (1922), 158f.--> These dog models closely match those described in the ritual text and thus strongly suggest that a version of the ritual was carried out in Assyria in the seventh century BCE. Each clay dog has traces of coloured pigment and is inscribed with a suitably powerful name:</p>
<ul><li>“Expeller of evil" (<i>mušēṣu lemnūti</i>) with white pigment and red spots (<esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=388877&amp;partId=1" title="View object BM 30001 on the British Museum website" rel="external" hide-print="yes">BM 30001</esp:link>)</li>
<li>“Catcher of the enemy" (<i>kāšid ayyāb</i>) with red pigment (<esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=388876&amp;partId=1" title="View object BM 30002 on the British Museum website" rel="external" hide-print="yes">BM 30002</esp:link>)</li>
<li>“Don’t think, bite!" (<i>ē tamtallik epuš pāka</i>) with white pigment (<esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=388875&amp;partId=1" title="View object BM 30003 on the British Museum website" rel="external" hide-print="yes">BM 30003</esp:link>)</li>
<li>“Biter of his foe!" (<i>munaššiku gārîšu</i>) with turquoise pigment (<esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=388874&amp;partId=1" title="View object BM 30004 on the British Museum website" rel="external" hide-print="yes">BM 30004</esp:link>)</li>
<li>“Loud is his bark!" (<i>dan rigiššu</i>) with black pigment (<esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=388873&amp;partId=1" title="View object BM 30005 on the British Museum website" rel="external" hide-print="yes">BM 30005</esp:link>)</li></ul>

<p>Cats, on the other hand, never occur in Assyrian protective rituals, and have never been found as figurines. Omens portray them as wild animals, at best untameable ones, that wandered in and out of houses at will. Humans and cats lived in and around each other but did not engage directly. The modern technical term for this is commensalism.  In other words, the inhabitants of Kalhu, even the king in his palace, could not rely on cats to guard a building, whether from mice or more supernatural forces.</p>


<esp:image file="maa/BM30001-to-BM30005.jpg" description="Five clay models of standing dogs, some coloured with brown or red pigment, and each with a name inscribed in cuneiform along the body" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=109112&amp;objectId=388876&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img104"><b>Image 3</b></esp:bookmark>: Five protective models of dogs found buried under a doorway in the North Palace, Nineveh; dating from c.645 BC. Each clay dog has traces of coloured pigment and is inscribed in cuneiform script with a suitably powerful name. From left to right: “Don’t think, bite!" (<esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=388875&amp;partId=1" title="View object BM 30003 on the British Museum website" rel="external" hide-print="yes">BM 30003</esp:link>); “Catcher of the enemy" (<esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=388876&amp;partId=1" title="View object BM 30002 on the British Museum website" rel="external" hide-print="yes">BM 30002</esp:link>); “Biter of his foe!" (<esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=388874&amp;partId=1" title="View object BM 30004 on the British Museum website" rel="external" hide-print="yes">BM 30004</esp:link>); “Expeller of evil" (<esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=388877&amp;partId=1" title="View object BM 30001 on the British Museum website" rel="external" hide-print="yes">BM 30001</esp:link>); “Loud is his bark!" (<esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=388873&amp;partId=1" title="View object BM 30005 on the British Museum website" rel="external" hide-print="yes">BM 30005</esp:link>). <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=109112&amp;objectId=388876&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<esp:image file="maa/BM-30005.jpg" description="Clay models of standing dog, coloured with brown or red pigment inscribed in cuneiform script along the body" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?partid=1&amp;assetid=316506&amp;objectid=388873" rel="external" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img104"><b>Image 4</b></esp:bookmark>: Clay model of a dog inscribed with the name “Loud is his bark!" (<i>dan rigiššu</i>) in cuneiform script. One of a set of five protective dog models found buried under a doorway in the North Palace, Nineveh, to protect against evil, c.645 BC. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=388873&amp;partId=1" title="View object BM 30005 on the British Museum website" rel="external" hide-print="yes">BM 30005</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?partid=1&amp;assetid=316506&amp;objectid=388873" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website.</esp:link> © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<esp:h>Dog ND 2183, from Nimrud to Cambridge</esp:h>

<p>The six bronze dogs found at Nimrud were stored in the <esp:techterms term="dig house">dig house</esp:techterms> until the end of the 1952 <esp:techterms term="excavation season">excavation season</esp:techterms>, when the excavated objects were reviewed by officials from the Iraqi <esp:techterms term="State Board of Antiquities and Heritage">State Board of Antiquities and Heritage</esp:techterms> in a process called the <esp:techterms term="division of finds">'division of finds'</esp:techterms>. During each season's division, the excavated artefacts were apportioned between the Iraqi authorities and the BSAI excavation. The model dogs were divided up, as was common for groups of similar objects at this time. Two dogs (ND 2184 and ND 2186) remained in Iraq and are now in the <esp:link page="museumsworldwide" bookmark="iraqmuseum">Iraq Museum</esp:link>, <esp:glossary term="Baghdad (place)">Baghdad</esp:glossary> and the other four were gifted to the BSAI excavation.</p>

<esp:image file="maa/BSAI-ND2185-ND2183-ND2182.jpg" description="Three bronze figurines of standing dogs, though the central example looks very cat-like" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img106"><b>Image 5</b></esp:bookmark>: Three of the bronze figurines found down a well in Room NN of the Northwest Palace, photographed in 1953 before dispersal to museums. <b>Left</b>: ND 2185, now in the <esp:link url="http://www.metmuseum.org/Collections/search-the-collections/323812" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Metropolitan Museum</esp:link>, New York, USA; <b>middle</b>: ND 2183,  <esp:link url="http://maa.cam.ac.uk/maa/" rel="external" hide-print="yes">MAA</esp:link>, Cambridge, England; <b>right</b>: ND 2182, now in the <esp:link url="http://www.aiarch.org.au/index.htm" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Australian Institute of Archaeology, La Trobe University</esp:link>, Bundoora, Australia. Photo: <esp:link page="copyright" bookmark="BISIimages">BSAI/BISI</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>The four dogs allocated to the BSAI excavation were sent temporarily to London University’s <esp:techterms term="Institute of Archaeology">Institute of Archaeology</esp:techterms>, along with the rest of that season’s finds. From London, Mallowan’s team portioned out artefacts as gifts to the various institutions that had provided financial support for that year’s dig. The dog models were all allocated to different museums that had made major monetary contributions. Dog ND 2183 (<b>Image 5, middle</b>) was <esp:link page="maa-intro">gifted to the University of Cambridge's Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology</esp:link>, as a result of the University's donation to the dig <esp:ref referent="maaannualreport1955-56"/>. One of its friends, dog ND 2214, stayed in the Institute of Archaeology's collection until 1984 when it was transferred to the <esp:link page="museumsuk" bookmark="britishmuseum">British Museum</esp:link>. The other two dogs made further journeys across the world: dog ND 2185 (<b>Image 5, left</b>) was gifted to the <esp:link page="museumsworldwide" bookmark="metmuseum">Metropolitan Museum</esp:link> in New York and the final dog, ND 2182 (<b>Image 5, right</b>), was given to the Australian Institute of Archaeology, Melbourne (now the <esp:link page="museumsworldwide" bookmark="australianinst">Australian Institute of Archaeology</esp:link> at La Trobe University). ND 3209, the dog that was found in the dump, was gifted to <esp:link page="museumsuk" bookmark="birmingham">Birmingham Museum and Art Gallery</esp:link>.</p>

<esp:h>Map showing present-day locations of the model dogs from Nimrud</esp:h>

<p><object type="text/html" width="425" height="350" data="https://maps.google.co.uk/maps/ms?msid=204599863567827172960.0004eccbd4da5cadb822e&amp;msa=0&amp;z=1&amp;output=embed">
</object></p>

<p><esp:link url="https://maps.google.co.uk/maps/ms?msid=204599863567827172960.0004eccbd4da5cadb822e&amp;msa=0" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View larger version of map using Google Maps</esp:link><br/>
<esp:link url="/nimrud/downloads/ModeldogsfromNimrud.kml" title="Map showing museums worldwide holding bronze dog figurines from Nimrud, excavated by BSAI 1949-1963" hide-print="yes">Download map content to view using Google Earth or re-use within your own custom maps (KML file, 4 KB)</esp:link></p>

<p>&#187; <esp:link bookmark="dogtable">See table showing current museum locations of model dogs from Nimrud</esp:link></p>

<esp:h>The dog that became a cat</esp:h>

<p>The figurine ND 2183 that was gifted to the University of Cambridge's Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology does not look much like a dog compared with the other models, and instead is very cat-like in appearance. In Max Mallowan’s 1952 season report of notable discoveries, he suggested that this model may indeed represent a cat rather than a dog: “Some of these beasts obviously represent the Assyrian breeds of dogs of the time, but at least one of them was feline in character" <esp:ref referent="mallowan1952" page="24"/>.</p>

<p>Yet Mallowan changed his mind about the animal’s identity in later writings, or at least, appeared hesitant to decide one way or another. He discussed the "delightful group of small metal dogs" found at Nimrud in an article for the <i>Illustrated London News</i> (16 August 1952) about the excavation and included a photograph of three of the models, taken before their dispersal to museums. This photo features MAA's model in the middle of the group (<b>Image 4</b>), and the caption notes: "The centre figure is distinctly cat-like in pose, but the Assyrian custom was to bury dog effigies under the doorstep to scare away spirits or <esp:techterms term="demon">demons</esp:techterms>" <esp:ref referent="mallowan1952b"/>. In this article, MAA's model was most likely a dog. Yet describing these "bronze statuettes of dogs" in his 1966 publication <i>Nimrud and Its Remains</i>, Mallowan hedged his bets, saying "ND 218[3], however, has a feline appearance" <esp:ref referent="mallowan1966" page="146"/>.</p>

<p>On arrival in Cambridge in 1956, separated from its five doggy friends, figurine ND 2183 was even less easily identifiable as a dog. The artefact was described in MAA's accession register as a “bronze figurine of cat" <esp:ref referent="maaaccessionreg1956-67" page="1"/>. It was understood to be a cat for the next sixty or so years.</p>

<p>In 2013 MAA generously permitted the Nimrud Project to study <esp:link page="maa-intro">their Nimrud artefacts</esp:link>, including the 'cat' figurine. Tracking down the other models and studying them as a group has shed new light on the MAA model. Considering this object alongside the other models found in the well, and in the wider context of Assyrian protective figurines, it is very unlikely to be a cat after all. After spending 60 years being a feline, this figurine has become understood as a dog once again.</p>

<esp:h><esp:bookmark id="dogtable">Current museum locations of model dogs from Nimrud</esp:bookmark></esp:h>

<esp:sh>Bronze dog figurines from the well in Room NN of Assurnasirpal II's Northwest Palace</esp:sh>

<table class="pretty">
<tr><th>Nimrud number</th><th>Museum</th><th>Museum accession number</th></tr>
<tr><td>ND 2182</td><td>Australian Institute of Archaeology, La Trobe University, Bundoora, Australia (formerly at the Australian Institute of Archaeology, Melbourne, Australia)</td><td></td></tr>
<tr><td>ND 2183</td><td>Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology, University of Cambridge, Cambridge</td><td>1956.5</td></tr>
<tr><td>ND 2184</td><td>Iraq Museum, Baghdad, Iraq</td><td></td></tr>
<tr><td>ND 2185</td><td>Metropolitan Museum, New York, USA</td><td>54.117.23</td></tr>
<tr><td>ND 2186</td><td>Iraq Museum, Baghdad, Iraq</td><td></td></tr>
<tr><td>ND 2214</td><td>British Museum, London, England (formerly at the Institute of Archaeology, University of London)</td><td>BM 140474</td></tr>
</table>

<esp:sh>Dog figurines from other findspots</esp:sh>

<table class="pretty">
<tr><th>Nimrud number and material</th><th><esp:techterms term="findspot">Findspot</esp:techterms></th><th>Museum</th><th>Museum accession number</th></tr>
<tr><td>ND 3209, bronze model</td><td><esp:techterms term="stratified">unstratified</esp:techterms> context (rubbish dump along <esp:techterms term="acropolis">acropolis</esp:techterms> wall)</td><td>Birmingham Museum and Art Gallery, Birmingham, England</td><td>1954A794</td></tr>
<tr><td>ND 5304, fragmentary clay model</td><td><esp:techterms term="stratified">unstratified</esp:techterms> context (Ninurta temple, dump)</td><td>Iraq Museum, Baghdad</td><td></td></tr>
</table>

<p>Table of information on model dogs from <esp:techterms term="British School of Archaeology in Iraq">BSAI</esp:techterms> excavations at Nimrud, 1949-1963, compiled using data courtesy of Christopher Walker and a group of volunteers at the British Museum.</p>

<p>Many thanks to <esp:link url="http://maa.cam.ac.uk/maa/imogen-gunn-curatorial-assistant-archaeology/" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Imogen Gunn</esp:link>, Collections Manager for Archaeology at MAA, for generous assistance with this research.</p>

<esp:reading referent="curtis2013" page="52-53, plate XXIII"/>
<esp:reading referent="green1983"/>
<esp:reading referent="mallowan1952" page="24"/>
<esp:reading referent="mallowan1952b"/>
<esp:reading referent="mallowan1966" page="122-148"/>
<esp:reading referent="mallowan1977" page="259-262"/>
<esp:reading referent="wiggermann1992"/>

<p>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/>.<br/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/></p>

<esp:author
    first-names="Ruth A."
	last-name="Horry"
/>
	</body></html>

</esp:page>
