<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
	<esp:name>Standard Inscription</esp:name>
	<esp:title>The Standard Inscription of Assurnasirpal II</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>

<p class="firstpara">As part of his transformation of Kalhu into a magnificent royal capital, Assurnasirpal II commissioned a vast new palace to serve as his residence in the city. The palace walls were lined with brightly painted <esp:techterms term="relief">relief</esp:techterms> sculptures illustrating war, hunting and religious scenes. Across the reliefs ran a cuneiform inscription telling of Assurnasirpal’s victories and the founding of his new capital, and this its new palace. This inscription is now known as the “Standard Inscription” of Assurnasirpal.</p>

<esp:h><esp:bookmark id="housewarming" title="A royal housewarming, and the Banquet Stela">A royal housewarming party</esp:bookmark></esp:h>

<esp:image file="sia/ND1104.jpg" description="Stone stela celebrating Assurnasirpal's grand new palace in Kalhu" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img62"><b>Image 1</b></esp:bookmark>: This stela commemorates the inauguration of Assurnasirpal’s <esp:link page="northwestpalace">Northwest Palace</esp:link>. Its description of a lavish feast has given it its modern name, the "Banquet Stela". The  <esp:techterms term="stela, stele">stela</esp:techterms> lay just a few metres from where Layard’s excavations had ended a century before. It had been installed in a recess just outside the entrance to the throne room. The stela was excavated by the <esp:techterms term="British School of Archaeology in Iraq">British School of Archaeology in Iraq</esp:techterms> in 1951 and is now in the collection of the museum in <esp:glossary term="Mosul (place)">Mosul</esp:glossary> ( ND1104). Photo: <esp:link page="copyright" bookmark="BISIimages">BSAI/BISI</esp:link> <esp:ref referent="wiseman1952" page="plate 2, between pp.24-25"/>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>In 879 BC king <esp:link page="assurnasirpal2">Assurnasirpal II</esp:link> of Assyria celebrated the completion of his new palace (now known as the <esp:link page="northwestpalace">Northwest Palace</esp:link>) by hosting a party that lasted for ten days. 69,574 guests were invited - men and women from across the Assyrian realm, including 16,000 citizens of Kalhu and 5,000 visiting dignitaries. In the company of <esp:link page="ashur">Aššur</esp:link> and all the other gods they feasted on thousands of sheep, oxen and deer, tens of thousands of birds and fish, eggs, hundreds of containers of grains, vegetables, bread, cheese, nuts and fruit, garnished with hundreds of jars of honey and spices. To wash it down, the guests were given 10,000 jugs of beer and 10,000 skins of wine. They were bathed, anointed with oil, and sent home “in peace and joy”<!-- [fn 2]-->. Assurnasirpal commemorated this lavish feast in an inscribed stela (the so-called Banquet Stela) set up near the throne room of his new palace (<b>Image 1</b>) <esp:ref referent="grayson1991" page="288-293, A.0.101.30 contains the full English translation of the Banquet Stela"/>.</p>

<p>Among those invited to the celebrations were representatives from <esp:glossary term="Gilzanu (place)">Gilzanu</esp:glossary>, <esp:glossary term="Suhu (place)">Suhu</esp:glossary> and <esp:glossary term="Patina (place)">Patina</esp:glossary>. Representatives from these regions are also depicted upon the <esp:link page="obelisk">Black Obelisk</esp:link> bringing tribute to Assurnasirpal’s son and successor <esp:link page="shalmaneser3"> Shalmaneser III</esp:link>. Inside the royal palace, these lucky guests would have seen walls decorated with carved <esp:techterms term="bas-relief">bas-reliefs</esp:techterms> and inscribed with <esp:techterms term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> text (<b>Image 2</b>). But what did the inscriptions say?</p> 

<esp:image file="sia/BM124560.jpg" description="A relief from Assurnasirpal’s palace, inscribed with the text of the Standard Inscription" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=588694&amp;objectId=367048&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img63"><b>Image 2</b></esp:bookmark>: A relief from <esp:link page="assurnasirpal2">Assurnasirpal II's</esp:link> <esp:link page="northwestpalace">Northwest Palace</esp:link>, inscribed with the text of the Standard Inscription. The protective spirit once guarded the entrance to the royal throne room. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=367048&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 124560</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=588694&amp;objectId=367048&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<esp:h>What is the Standard Inscription?</esp:h>

<p>The Standard Inscription is not an object in its own right, but rather a single, standardised cuneiform text written in Akkadian, which was carved out many times in celebration of Assurnasirpal's accomplishments. It ran to 22 lines of script altogether. The first five lines assert the king’s credentials:</p>

<blockquote><p>Palace of Assurnasirpal, vice-regent of Aššur, chosen one of the gods <esp:glossary term="Ellil (deity)">Enlil</esp:glossary> and <esp:link page="ninurta">Ninurta</esp:link>, beloved of the gods <esp:glossary term="Anu (deity)">Anu</esp:glossary> and <esp:glossary term="Dagan (deity)">Dagan</esp:glossary>, destructive weapon of the great gods, strong king, king of the universe, king of Assyria, son of <esp:glossary term="Tukulti-Ninurta II (person)">Tukulti-Ninurta</esp:glossary>, great king, strong king, king of the universe, king of Assyria, son of <esp:glossary term="Adad-nerari II (person)">Adad-nerari</esp:glossary>, great king, strong king, king of the universe, king of Assyria; valiant man who acts with the support of Aššur, his lord, and has no rival among the princes of the four quarters, marvellous shepherd, fearless in battle, unopposable mighty floodtide, king who subdues those insubordinate to him, he who rules all peoples, strong male who treads upon the necks of his foes, trampler of all enemies, he who smashes the forces of the rebellious, king who acts with the support of the great gods, his lords, and has conquered all lands, gained dominion over all the highlands and received their <esp:techterms term="tribute">tribute</esp:techterms>, capturer of hostages, he who is victorious over all countries... <esp:ref referent="grayson1991" page="275, A.0.101.23:1-5"/>.</p></blockquote>

<p>The next nine lines report the extent of his victories, stretching from <esp:glossary term="Lebanon (place)">Mount Lebanon</esp:glossary> in the west to <esp:glossary term="Armenia (place)">Armenia</esp:glossary> in the east, and encroaching south into <esp:glossary term="Babylonia (place)">Babylonian</esp:glossary> territory. The last eight lines tell how he rebuilt the city of Kalhu (and made it his capital), and settled there people from his newly conquered territories. He built a great palace, decorated with the finest woods and metals, and stone statues of the beasts of the mountains and the seas; then he filled it with booty.</p>

<p>Passages of text with very similar wording are found on other monumental inscriptions of Assurnasirpal. Together they reveal in splendid detail the accomplishments of one of the most important rulers in Assyrian history.</p>

<esp:h>Text and image</esp:h>

<esp:image file="sia/BM124562.jpg" description="Stone panel carved in low relief showing two Syrian men carrying monkeys. Assurbanipal's inscription text is carved across the middle of the figures" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=325683&amp;objectId=367049&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img64"><b>Image 3</b></esp:bookmark>: The text of the Standard Inscription can be seen running across the fine detail of this relief (<esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=367049&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 124562</esp:link>) from the Northwest Palace's throne room. Here Syrians bring monkeys as <esp:techterms term="tribute">tribute</esp:techterms> to the king. Compare the depiction of monkeys on <esp:link page="obelisk">Shalmaneser’s Black Obelisk.</esp:link> <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=325683&amp;objectId=367049&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Assurnasirpal had no qualms about having his Standard Inscription carved across the figures on the reliefs decorating his palace walls (<b>Image 3</b>). The gods and the king himself would have text written across their visual representation. In the cuneiform world, this meant the words being <esp:link page="materials-others" bookmark="h_monumentalinscriptions">carved into</esp:link> the bodies of the figures. It was a deliberately chosen technique intended to wed text and image. The figures were all designed to perform a function, and to communicate a message. Likewise, the king’s carefully composed text does the same. And the two are physically united.</p>

<esp:image file="sia/BM124530-detail.jpg" description="The inscription on this slab stops in mid-sentence with the words 'Encircler of the obstinate, crowned'." position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/sia/BM124530-large.jpg" hide-print="yes" rel="external" title="View large image"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img65"><b>Image 4</b></esp:bookmark>: The inscription on this slab stops abruptly, part-way through line 13 with the words “Encircler of the obstinate, crowned”. It was due to continue “with splendour, fearless in battle ...” but the carver had run out of space. The inscription looks convincingly complete at first glance, but the <esp:techterms term="scribe">scribes</esp:techterms> would have noticed the trick. A detail from relief <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=367022&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 124530</esp:link>. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/sia/BM124530-large.jpg" hide-print="yes" rel="external" title="View large image">View large image.</esp:link> Image: Jon Taylor for the Nimrud Project <esp:link page="copyright">CC-BY-SA 3.0</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Study of the many duplicates of the inscription has revealed that a set amount of space was assigned for the inscription on each relief slab. The result was a harmonious visual appearance throughout the rooms. Sometimes the stone carver was unable to fit the full 22 line text in the allotted space. Examples are known where as few as the first 8 lines were carved. And occasionally the carver stopped in mid-sentence (<b>Image 4</b>).</p>

<esp:h>Fragments of history</esp:h>

<esp:image file="sia/BM-2010_6022_19.jpg" description="A small fragment of the Standard Inscription collected during the 19th century" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=992411&amp;objectId=3355092&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img66"><b>Image 5</b></esp:bookmark>: A fragment of the Standard Inscription from <esp:glossary term="Wiseman, Donald (person)">Donald Wiseman’s</esp:glossary> collection, given to the British Museum in 2010. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=3355092&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 2010,6022.19</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=992411&amp;objectId=3355092&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Layard, the first excavator of Nimrud, realised that the text of Assurnasirpal's Standard Inscription was repeated frequently across many of the reliefs from his palace. However, excavations at this time were not concerned with the systematic collecting of archaeological material, and when the slabs were cut in preparation for transport, many of the copies of this standardised text were left behind. More than 400 copies of the text are known, and examples can be found in <esp:link page="museumsworldwide" bookmark="nwp-nd-map">museums around the world</esp:link>. 
<esp:bookmark id="smallfragments">Other fragments were collected privately and some have subsequently come to light over the years.</esp:bookmark> One example (<esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=3355092&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 2010,6022.19</esp:link>) was given as a gift by Layard to one of his wife’s relatives (<b>Image 5</b>). She gave it to her daughter, who in turn gave it to <esp:glossary term="Wiseman, Donald (person)">Donald Wiseman</esp:glossary>. Wiseman himself was part of the <esp:techterms term="British School of Archaeology in Iraq">British School of Archaeology in Iraq</esp:techterms> excavation team working at Nimrud in the 1950s. A second fragment (<esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=271416&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 136715</esp:link>) was collected by the Rev. S. C. Malan, a Biblical scholar and artist who visited Layard’s excavations in June 1850. Malan’s drawings illustrate Layard’s <i>Discoveries in Nineveh and Babylon</i> (1853) <esp:ref referent="layard1853"/>. Both of these fragments are now in the British Museum collection.</p>

<p>However, more than half of the known examples of the Inscription are still in situ at Nimrud. Other monumental inscriptions were also left behind. Layard produced <esp:techterms term="squeeze">paper squeezes</esp:techterms> of some, and their text was later published on the basis of these squeezes. The squeezes have since perished, however, meaning that anyone who wishes to check what a particular inscription says must now visit the original object in situ. Many of these are underground, having been reburied by the excavators to protect them.</p>

<esp:reading referent="collins2008" page="29-61"/>
<esp:reading referent="wiseman1952"/>
<esp:reading referent="reade1983" page="34-41"/>
<esp:reading referent="mallowan1966" page="57-73"/>
<esp:reading referent="russell1999" page="9-63"/>

<p>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/>.<br/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/></p>

<esp:author
	first-names="Jonathan"
	last-name="Taylor"
/>
	</body></html>

</esp:page>
