<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
	<esp:name>Succession Treaties</esp:name>
	<esp:title>The Succession Treaties of Esarhaddon</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>

<p class="firstpara">"Swear by <esp:link page="ashur">Aššur</esp:link>, father of the gods, lord of all the lands!" So commanded king <esp:link page="esarhaddon">Esarhaddon</esp:link> in the spring of 672 BC, as he bound the inhabitants of the Assyrian empire to ensure the <esp:techterms term="succession">succession</esp:techterms> of his son, <esp:link page="assurbanipal">Assurbanipal</esp:link>. Experience had shown him that the change of rule from one king to the next was a dangerous time. <esp:techterms term="vassal">Vassals</esp:techterms> would seek to regain their independence, and rival claimants to the throne could plunge the country into civil war. Treaties were a long-established method of controlling the behaviour of key figures at moments like this. Copies of Esarhaddon's Succession Treaty (previously referred to as the 'Vassal Treaty') found at Nimrud reveal the king's plans for securing the empire after his death.</p>

<esp:h><esp:bookmark id="transfer" title="The transfer of power in Assyria">The Succession Treaties in historical context: transfer of power</esp:bookmark></esp:h>

<esp:image file="vte/BM-132548.jpg" description="A Succession Treaty of king Esarhaddon" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?partid=1&amp;assetid=433287&amp;objectid=795262" rel="external" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img87"><b>Image 1</b></esp:bookmark>: A copy of the great Succession Treaty drawn up by king <esp:glossary term="Esarhaddon (person)">Esarhaddon</esp:glossary> of Assyria in 672 BC. This tablet has been extensively restored from fragments found in the throne room of <esp:link page="nabu">Nabu's</esp:link> temple at Kalhu, and much of the text is missing. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=795262&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 132548</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?partid=1&amp;assetid=433287&amp;objectid=795262" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>In 672 BC the ageing king Esarhaddon put into effect a strategy for his succession. One son – <esp:glossary term="Assurbanipal (person)">Assurbanipal</esp:glossary> – would become the next king of Assyria; under him, his older brother – <esp:glossary term="Šamaš-šumu-ukin (person)">Šamaš-šumu-ukin</esp:glossary> – would become king of Babylon.</p> 

<p>Esarhaddon’s own ascent to the throne was not straightforward, even though he had been made <esp:techterms term="crown prince">crown prince</esp:techterms> by his father, king <esp:glossary term="Sennacherib (person)">Sennacherib</esp:glossary>. Intrigues made him flee the royal court. In 681 BC Sennacherib was murdered by other sons who tried to seize the throne for themselves. Esarhaddon took back his rightful place through force of arms.</p>

<p>Esarhaddon was desperate to avoid a repeat of this turmoil. He gathered key figures from across his empire to support his succession plan. Many of the partners listed on the preserved treaties (<b>Image 1</b>) were rulers of eastern lands that had only recently been brought back into the Assyrian empire.</p>

<p>According to Assurbanipal, the treaty was sworn on the 12th of Ayyar (March/April) 672 BC. The surviving copies are dated to the 16th or 18th, however. We might perhaps imagine that it took several days for so many people to swear such a long oath according to proper procedures.</p>

<esp:h><esp:bookmark id="treaties" title="Treaties in Assyria">Treaties in Assyria</esp:bookmark></esp:h>

<esp:image file="vte/BM-91027.jpg" description="Detail from Esarhaddon's monument recording the restoration of Babylon" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?partid=1&amp;assetid=604420&amp;objectid=369187" rel="external" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img88"><b>Image 2</b></esp:bookmark>: Detail from Esarhaddon's monument recording the restoration of Babylon. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=369187&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 91027</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?partid=1&amp;assetid=604420&amp;objectid=369187" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>International treaties were nothing new. Many are known from ancient Mesopotamia, stretching back for almost 2,000 years before Esarhaddon’s Succession Treaty. This is all the more remarkable given that very few treaties have survived from elsewhere in the ancient world. The Mesopotamian habit of writing on clay has preserved once again for us original documents that yield first hand testimony as to how the ancient world actually worked.</p>

<p>The king of Assyria made treaties both with equals and with those in much weaker positions. What seem to us to be one-sided treaties were often made at the request of the weaker party. In return for tribute to Assyria and obedience to its rulers, vassals gained the protection of one of the most powerful empires in the world. Assyrian weapons and fear of the royal wrath strengthened vassal rulers against hostile neighbours and rival claimants to the throne.</p>

<p>Esarhaddon’s Succession Treaty is the longest Assyrian treaty known. It sets out in detail the many actions required of his subjects, secured by a <esp:link page="vte-detail" bookmark="curses">long list of fearful curses</esp:link> for anyone who might dare to break their oath. The full text and translation is available online (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa02/P336598" hide-print="yes">SAA 2: 006</esp:link>).</p>

<p>&#187; <esp:link page="vte-detail">See the Succession Treaty of Esarhaddon in more detail</esp:link></p>

<esp:h>Did the treaty work?</esp:h>

<esp:image file="vte/90866.jpg" description="Šamaš-šumu-ukin, king of Babylon, striking a pose as a builder" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=1426343&amp;objectId=369184&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img89"><b>Image 3</b></esp:bookmark>: <esp:techterms term="stela, stele">Stela</esp:techterms> from <esp:link page="nabu">Nabu's</esp:link> temple in <esp:glossary term="Borsippa (place)">Borsippa</esp:glossary> showing <esp:glossary term="Šamaš-šumu-ukin (person)">Šamaš-šumu-ukin</esp:glossary>, king of Babylon, striking a pose as a builder. The king's image was defaced when Assyrian troops stormed Babylon in 648 BC. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=369184&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 90866</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=1426343&amp;objectId=369184&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Three years after the treaty was made, Esarhaddon died. As he had hoped, Assurbanipal took the Assyrian throne, and his brother Šamaš-šumu-ukin the Babylonian throne (<b>Image 3</b>). All was well. The treaty had done its job. Assurbanipal remarked in his annals:</p>

<blockquote><p>Esarhaddon, king of Assyria, my father and begetter, heeded the command of <esp:link page="ashur">Aššur</esp:link> and <esp:glossary term="Mullissu (deity)">Mullissu</esp:glossary>, the gods in whom he trusted, who told him that I was to exercise the kingship. On 12th of Ayyar, at the noble command of Aššur, Mullissu, <esp:glossary term="Sin (deity)">Sin</esp:glossary>, <esp:glossary term="Šamaš (deity)">Šamaš</esp:glossary>, <esp:glossary term="Adad (deity)">Adad</esp:glossary>, <esp:glossary term="Bel (deity)">Bel</esp:glossary>, <esp:link page="nabu">Nabu</esp:link>, <esp:glossary term="Ištar (deity)">Ištar of Nineveh</esp:glossary>, <esp:glossary term="Ištar (deity)">Ištar of Arbela</esp:glossary>, <esp:link page="ninurta">Ninurta</esp:link>, <esp:glossary term="Nergal (deity)">Nergal</esp:glossary> and <esp:glossary term="Nusku (deity)">Nusku</esp:glossary>, he convened the people of Assyria, great and small, from coast to coast, made them swear a treaty oath by the gods, and made a binding agreement to protect my <esp:techterms term="crown prince">crown-princeship</esp:techterms> and future kingship over Assyria.</p></blockquote> 

<p>But the situation could not last. Control of Babylon had always been a problem for the Assyrians. Over the years they had tried many approaches, but none had worked for long. In 652 BC, brother turned on brother. Šamaš-šumu-ukin made a bid for independence, and the empire was plunged once more into a long and bloody civil war. Later legend told of the death of the decadent king <esp:glossary term="Sardanapalus (person)">Sardanapalus</esp:glossary> in the flames of his burning palace. The name Sardanapalus seems to derive from that of Assurbanipal. But the fiery death matches the fate suffered by his brother Šamaš-šumu-ukin when Assyrian troops finally defeated his rebellion.</p>

<esp:h>Where were the treaty tablets found?</esp:h>

<esp:image file="vte/ND-4336c.jpg" description="The reverse of a Succession Treaty tablet with the scribal colophon at the end" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img90" title="The colophon from Esarhaddon's Succession Treaty"><b>Image 4</b></esp:bookmark>: The <esp:techterms term="obverse, reverse">reverse</esp:techterms> of a fragmentary Succession Treaty <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablet</esp:techterms> from <esp:link page="ezida">Nabu's temple</esp:link> in Kalhu. The scribal <esp:techterms term="colophon">colophon</esp:techterms>, in the lower right corner of the tablet, records the nature and date of the text: “The treaty which Esarhaddon, king of Assyria, concluded on behalf of Assurbanipal, the great <esp:techterms term="crown prince">crown prince</esp:techterms> designate of Assyria, and Šamaš-šumu-ukin, crown prince designate of Babylon”. ND 4336c; Iraq Museum, Baghdad. British Museum photograph © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p><esp:link page="vte-detail">The exceptionally long and detailed treaty</esp:link> imposed by Esarhaddon is known from at least 10 copies, each of which was sworn by a different vassal or <esp:techterms term="province">province</esp:techterms>. <esp:link page="vte-detail" bookmark="showpiece">Such a long and important text required equally grand clay <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablets</esp:techterms>.</esp:link> Each was certified by the <esp:techterms term="impression">impression</esp:techterms> of no fewer than <esp:link page="vte-detail" bookmark="seal impressions">three seals</esp:link> of Aššur, head of the Assyrian pantheon, and had been stored under divine protection.</p>

<p>In the 1950s, excavators from the <esp:techterms term="British School of Archaeology in Iraq">British School of Archaeology in Iraq</esp:techterms> found 8 copies of the treaty in the throne room of the <esp:link page="ezida">temple of Nabu</esp:link> at Kalhu. This was a meaningful home. <esp:link page="nabu">Nabu</esp:link>, god of writing, had a significant library in his temple; he was also thought to be the divine <esp:techterms term="scribe">scribe</esp:techterms> of the <esp:techterms term="Tablet of Destinies">Tablet of Destinies</esp:techterms>. It is not certain that the treaties had originally been stored there, however. The treaty was sworn across the empire, yet the only copies found are those imposed on the tribes to the east of Assyria, from <esp:glossary term="Media (place)">Media</esp:glossary>, <esp:glossary term="Ellipi (place)">Ellipi</esp:glossary> and <esp:glossary term="Zamua (place)">Zamua</esp:glossary>. Did the Medes who sacked Kalhu in 612 BC bring them to the throne room to be <esp:link page="vte-detail" bookmark="jigsaw">ceremonially smashed</esp:link>?</p>

<p>Three fragments (perhaps from a single copy) of the treaty were excavated at the important Assyrian city of<esp:glossary term="Assur (place)">Assur</esp:glossary> (modern Qala'at Sherqat) between 1903 and 1914, although frustratingly it is not known where on the site they were found. More recently, a badly broken copy of the treaty was excavated at <esp:link url="http://www.utoronto.ca/tap/" hide-print="yes" rel="external">Tell Tayinat</esp:link> (in modern Turkey) in 2009 <esp:ref referent="harrisonosborne2012"/>. The tablet was found in the ruins of the temple, where it had shattered on the floor during the final destruction. Tayinat was once the capital of the Assyrian <esp:techterms term="province">province</esp:techterms> of Kullania. The find shows that the Succession Treaty was not imposed only on Assyria's vassals, as was previously thought. Rather, it was administered to Assyrians and subjugated peoples alike, in a large-scale public ceremony which took place over several days.</p>

<esp:reading referent="fales2012b"/>
<esp:reading referent="george1986"/>
<esp:reading referent="lauinger2012a"/>
<esp:reading referent="mallowan1956"/>
<esp:reading referent="parpolawatanabe1988"/>
<esp:reading referent="watanabe1987"/>
<esp:reading referent="wiseman1958"/>

<p>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/>.<br/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/></p>

<esp:author
	first-names="Jonathan"
	last-name="Taylor"
/>
	</body></html>

</esp:page>
