<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
	<esp:name>Early Kalhu</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Kalhu: from prehistoric settlement to royal capital</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>

<p class="firstpara">The city of Kalhu reached the peak of its glory in the 9th and 8th centuries BC, when it served as Assyria's administrative capital and the residence of the Assyrian king. However, archaeological and textual evidence shows that the settlement's occupation stretches back to much earlier times.</p>

<esp:h>The early settlement at Kawalhum</esp:h>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/BM-130870.jpg" description="A glazed faience rosette excavated by Max Mallowan to the south of the temple of Kidmuru on Kalhu's citadel mound" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img29"><b>Image 1</b></esp:bookmark>: An example of the glazed <esp:techterms term="faience">faience</esp:techterms> rosettes excavated by <esp:glossary term="Mallowan, Max (person)">Max Mallowan</esp:glossary>'s team to the south of the <esp:link page="ziggurat">temple of Kidmuru</esp:link> on Kalhu's <esp:techterms term="citadel">citadel</esp:techterms> mound. The rosettes were perhaps originally used to decorate a temple. The black <esp:techterms term="boss">boss</esp:techterms> in the centre of the rosette is the only surviving colour element of this once vibrant object. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=369409&amp;partId=1" rel="external">BM 130870</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=1145645&amp;objectId=369409&amp;partId=1">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>The city of Kalhu (modern Nimrud) is located along the northeast bank of the <esp:glossary term="Tigris (place)">Tigris</esp:glossary> river, near its confluence with the <esp:glossary term="Greater Zab (place)">Greater Zab</esp:glossary>, some 35 kilometres downstream of <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary> (modern <esp:glossary term="Mosul (place)">Mosul</esp:glossary>) in the <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/aebp/essentials/countries/centralassyria" rel="external">heartland of ancient Assyria</esp:link>. The settlement's location had many important benefits. An irrigation canal brought water from the Greater Zab to the city, and enabled the locals to make the most of the region's fertile soil to grow various crops. The two rivers provided transport for people, troops and goods. Kalhu's central location meant that the other major Assyrian centres - Nineveh, <esp:glossary term="Assur (place)">Assur</esp:glossary> and <esp:glossary term="Arbela (place)">Arbela</esp:glossary> - were within relatively easy reach. A natural source of <esp:techterms term="bitumen">bitumen</esp:techterms>, a substance used for waterproofing pavements and other structures, was also located conveniently close to the city. Overall, Kalhu's position enabled it to play an important role in overland and riverine trade networks both within Assyria and further afield.</p>

<p>Very little is known about the earliest settlement at Kalhu because the deepest layers of the site have never been formally excavated. However, work at Nimrud during the 19th and 20th centuries has uncovered evidence of occupation which long predates the city's heyday in the 9th century BC, when king <esp:link page="assurnasirpal2">Assurnasirpal II</esp:link> (r. 883-859 BC) transformed the city into his magnificent royal capital. During excavations in the southeast corner of the <esp:techterms term="citadel">citadel</esp:techterms> mound, <esp:glossary term="Mallowan, Max (person)">Max Mallowan</esp:glossary> found <esp:techterms term="potsherd">potsherds</esp:techterms> and flints dating back to an <esp:techterms term="stratigraphy">archaeological layer</esp:techterms> known as Nineveh V - evidence that the site was occupied already by the 3rd millennium BC. A grave uncovered underneath the <esp:link page="ezida">temple of Nabu</esp:link> was dated by Mallowan to around 1750 BC. Unfortunately these isolated finds don't allow any meaningful reconstruction of the settlement, and since no contemporary textual sources have been found, Kalhu's role in this early period remains something of a mystery.</p>

<esp:h>Kalhu in the Middle-Assyrian period</esp:h>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/BM-1856_0903_144.jpg" description="A spacer bead made of translucent blue glass found underneath the Burnt Palace in Kalhu" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img30"><b>Image 2</b></esp:bookmark>: This inauspicious-looking object is a spacer bead made of translucent blue glass using an open mould. It was found underneath the Burnt Palace in Kalhu, in a tomb which probably dates from the <esp:techterms term="Middle Assyrian">Middle Assyrian</esp:techterms> period (c.1400-c.1050 BC). <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=1638945&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">BM 1856,0903.144</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?partid=1&amp;assetid=992031&amp;objectid=1638945" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>We are on slightly firmer ground with the Middle Assyrian period (c.1400-1050 BC). A <esp:techterms term="seal, sealing">seal</esp:techterms> <esp:techterms term="impression">impression</esp:techterms> and a number of <esp:techterms term="glaze">glazed</esp:techterms> <esp:techterms term="faience">faience</esp:techterms> ornaments (<b>Image 1</b>) from this period were uncovered near the <esp:link page="ziggurat">temple of Kidmuru</esp:link>. This temple is thought to have a long history and is certainly the only temple known to predate Assurnasirpal II's rebuilding of the city. Tentative evidence that the settlement enjoyed some importance at this time comes from a letter found at <esp:glossary term="Assur (place)">Assur</esp:glossary> and dated to c.1200 BC, according to which Kassite prisoners of war were housed in the city. Later on, written sources from the reign of <esp:glossary term="Tiglath-pileser I (person)">Tiglath-pileser I</esp:glossary> (r. 1114-1076 BC) mention Kalhu as a provincial capital, a status which the city may have enjoyed already under earlier kings and would continue to enjoy until the final days of the Assyrian empire. This suggests that we should probably not take at face value Assurnasirpal's claim that "the ancient city of Kalhu, which Shalmaneser (I)... had built - this city had become dilapidated; it lay dormant" <esp:ref referent="grayson1991" page="285, A.0.101.28:v 1-2"/>.</p>

<p>It was the reign of Assurnasirpal II that brought about a turning point in Kalhu's fortunes. The king's successful military expeditions provided him with great wealth and resources which he used to completely rebuild Kalhu. The city underwent a dramatic transformation from an unremarkable provincial town to an opulent <esp:link page="kalhu-aeb">capital city</esp:link> which served as the seat of royal power for the next 170 years and was a fitting symbol of Assyria's imperial power.</p>

<esp:reading referent="oatesoates2001"/>
<esp:reading referent="postgatereade1976-1980"/>
<esp:reading referent="reade1982"/>

<p>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/><br/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/></p>
<esp:author first-names="Silvie" last-name="Zamazalová"/>
</body></html>
</esp:page>
