<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

	<esp:name>Nabu's temple</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Ezida, the god Nabu's temple of scholarship</esp:title>

	<html><head>
</head><body>
	
<p class="firstpara">The god of wisdom's temple, Ezida, was at the opposite end of the royal <esp:techterms term="citadel">citadel</esp:techterms> to the palace, next to the city governor's residence. It gained in importance over the 8th century BC and king Sargon II (r. 721-705 BC) remodelled it to reflect a close, triangular relationship between deity, royalty and scholarship. Royal <esp:link page="professions"><i>āšipu</i>-healers</esp:link> led scholarly activities in the temple, including the development of a large library of learned works.</p>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/plan-ezida-kalhu.png" description="Plan of Nabu's temple at Kalhu" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/plan-ezida-kalhu-large.png" title="View large image of Plan of Nabu's temple at Kalhu" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img225">Plan of Ezida, Nabu's temple at Kalhu</esp:bookmark> <esp:ref referent="oatesoates2001" page="112, figure 67"/>. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/plan-ezida-kalhu-large.png" title="View large image of Plan of Ezida, Nabu's temple at Kalhu" hide-print="yes">View large image (334 KB)</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>


<esp:h>The temple's early years</esp:h>

<p>When <esp:link page="assurnasirpal2">Assurnasirpal II</esp:link> started on the renovation of Kalhu's citadel, <esp:link page="nabu">Nabu’s</esp:link> temple was one of the last buildings to be constructed—and not in the palace quarter b ut several hundred metres to the southeast. Assurnasirpal's numerous and extensive building accounts rarely mention Nabu’s temple, and do so only in passing. Nabu, then, was only a peripheral member of Assurnasirpal’s personal pantheon. It is now impossible to determine what his temple might have looked like at this time, as only traces of it survived later building work.</p> 

<p>However, from its first days, Nabu's temple was a centre of scholarly activity. <esp:glossary term="Ištaran-mudammiq (person)">Ištaran-mudammiq</esp:glossary>, Assurnasirpal's senior <i>āšipu</i>, wrote an ominous calendar for the library (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/P363473" hide-print="yes" rel="external">CTN 4: 58</esp:link>). His descendants continued to be associated with the temple for at least four generations, as royal <i>āšipus</i> and royal <esp:techterms term="scribe">scribes</esp:techterms>, writing <esp:techterms term="incantation">incantations</esp:techterms> and <esp:techterms term="omen">omens</esp:techterms> (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/P363423" hide-print="yes" rel="external">CTN 4: 8</esp:link>; <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/P363517" hide-print="yes" rel="external">CTN 4: 103</esp:link>).</p>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/BM-118889.jpg" description="Limestone statue of bearded god wearing a horned headdress, standing with hands clasped in front of him" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=574167&amp;objectId=367084&amp;partId=1"
title="View large image on British Museum website" hide-print="yes"
rel="external"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img10">One of a pair of divine attendant statues that stood at the entrance to Nabu's sanctuary (see isometric plan above).</esp:bookmark> This statue arrived in London in 1856 <esp:ref referent="gadd1936" page="150-151"/> and is now displayed in Room 6 at the British Museum; <esp:link page="nabu" bookmark="img222">its counterpart is in the Iraq Museum</esp:link>, Baghdad. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=367084&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 118889</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=574167&amp;objectId=367084&amp;partId=1" title="View large image" hide-print="yes" rel="external">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link> © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>During the reign of Assurnasirpal II's grandson <esp:glossary term="Adad-nerari III (person)">Adad-nerari III</esp:glossary> (r. 810-783 BC) the old temple on the <esp:techterms term="acropolis">acropolis</esp:techterms> was demolished and a massive 3 metre-high mud-brick platform constructed for the new building to rest on <esp:ref referent="mallowan1966" page="261 (vol. I)"/>. The solid walls, monumental statuary, and extensive use of large stone blocks in the <esp:techterms term="foundation course">foundation-courses</esp:techterms> and pavements all speak of considerable expense.</p> 

<p>Curiously, however, Nabu’s name hardly ever occurs in Adad-nerari’s royal inscriptions, while conversely Adad-nerari’s name is almost nowhere to be found in the temple. The only place it occurs is on two statues outside Nabu's shrine, which his city governor <esp:glossary term="Bel-tarṣi-ilumma (person)">Bel-tarṣi-ilumma</esp:glossary> dedicated to Nabu for the life of the king and the <esp:techterms term="queen mother">queen mother</esp:techterms>.</p> 

<p>Even when the temple was renovated again in the late 8th century BC, no king claimed credit for the work. However, there is no reason to doubt <esp:glossary term="Mallowan, Max (person)">Max Mallowan</esp:glossary>’s carefully drawn conclusion that this work was carried out in the reign of <esp:glossary term="Sargon II (person)">Sargon II</esp:glossary> <esp:ref referent="mallowan1966" page="283-284 (vol. I)"/>.</p>

<esp:h><esp:bookmark id="heyday" title="Ezida in its heyday">The temple in its heyday</esp:bookmark></esp:h>

<p>The twin shrines of Nabu and his consort <esp:glossary term="Tašmetu (deity)">Tašmetu</esp:glossary>, the rooms around the adjacent inner courtyard, as well as the famous "Fish Gate" entrance to the north, were laid out in about 800 BC and then remained essentially unchanged. Just before 700 BC much of the northern part of the temple was built anew, and perhaps completely remodelled. It is essentially this version of Ezida that was used right until the end of empire and which excavators discovered in the 19th and 20th centuries.</p>

<p>The close relationship between <esp:techterms term="Neo-Assyrian">Neo-Assyrian</esp:techterms> kingship, deity and scholarship is elegantly realised in the architecture of the Kalhu Ezida. The temple is entered via a monumental gateway that features colossal <esp:techterms term="beneficent">beneficent</esp:techterms> spirits in typical Assyrian style. But whereas most temples and palaces famously feature monumental <esp:techterms term="colossal bull">winged bulls</esp:techterms>, Ezida’s main entrance - the so-called "Fish Gate" - is flanked by giant mermen, originally covered in <esp:techterms term="gold">gold</esp:techterms> leaf <esp:ref referent="oatesoates2001" page="111"/>, who represented the <esp:techterms term="sage">primordial sages</esp:techterms> who brought wisdom and civilisation to humankind in deep antiquity.</p> 

<p>Off the temple’s first courtyard, which was surrounded by primarily utilitarian offices, are two further courts. A large courtyard to the south gave access to the twin shrines of Nabu and Tašmetu, whose larger-than-life statues, and Bel-tarṣi-ilumma’s protective figures at their gateways, could gaze directly on the <esp:techterms term="scholar">scholars</esp:techterms> at work in and around the tablet store immediately opposite. A corridor around the back of the shrines perhaps enabled the priests to voice communications from the gods without being seen as the intermediaries.</p>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/ND4304.jpg" description="Stone pebble with dedicatory inscription to Nabu" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/ND4304-large.jpg" title="View large image of pebble with dedicatory inscription" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img226">This brown pebble was found among burnt debris in corridor NT3 opposite the entrance to Nabu's sanctuary.</esp:bookmark> It has been inscribed with a dedication to Nabu and a priest figure standing in front of symbols of Nabu (a wedge-shaped stylus) and <esp:glossary term="Marduk (deity)">Marduk</esp:glossary> (a triangular-headed spade) <esp:ref referent="mallowan1966" page="270, figure 252"/>. ND 4304, Iraq Museum. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/ND4304-large.jpg" title="View large image of pebble with dedicatory inscription" hide-print="yes">View large image (145 KB).</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>To the west, a smaller courtyard led on to a small-scale throne room, complete with tracks for a <esp:techterms term="brazier">brazier</esp:techterms> in cold weather, so that the king could visit with appropriate <esp:techterms term="rite, ritual">ritual</esp:techterms> and protocol. Nabu and Tašmetu could occupy miniature versions of the twin shrines right next to the throne room while the king was in residence.</p>

<p>Early 7th century records and letters show that this area of the temple was known as the <i>bēt akiāte</i>, the <esp:techterms term="akītu"><i>akītu</i></esp:techterms>-suite, which was set aside for an annual "<esp:techterms term="sacred marriage">sacred marriage</esp:techterms>" ritual between Nabu and Tašmetu. The ritual lasted several days and took place in the second month of the year (in late spring). A further room in the <i>akītu</i>-suite, which might have been called the <i>bēt ūmē sebetti</i> ("seven-day room"), may have served as their bedroom for the duration. Offerings made to the divine couple during this time were designed to prolong the life of the king and all of his descendants <!-- (Postgate 1974; Matsushima 1987) --> <esp:ref referent="colemachinist1998" page="xv-xvi"/>. Even if the king were unable to attend, the <esp:link page="templestaff"><i>hazannu</i> ("mayor")</esp:link> of Ezida was present throughout, to make offerings on the king’s behalf <!-- (Postgate 1974)--> <esp:ref referent="oatesoates2001" page="119-123"/>.</p>

<esp:h>Scholarly activity in the 7th century BC</esp:h>

<p>Fully half of the 250-odd <esp:link page="scholarlyworks">scholarly tablets</esp:link> found in a room immediately opposite his shrine bear omens, incantations and rituals—for advising the Assyrian king on political decision-making and for helping him to maintain his relationship with the gods. A further quarter comprise hymns and lexical works (standardised lists of words and <esp:techterms term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> signs), while the majority of the remainder comprise medical, literary and calendrical writings.</p>

<p>Some 30 scholarly tablets of the Kalhu Ezida corpus have extant or partially surviving <esp:techterms term="colophon">colophons</esp:techterms>, from which at least 15 names of scholars can be identified. Many of them belong to just <esp:link page="families">two dynasties</esp:link> of Assyrian royal scholars. As we have seen, the earliest comprises several generations of the descendants of <esp:glossary term="Ištaran-šumu-ukin (person)">Ištaran-šumu-ukin</esp:glossary>, a 10th(?)-century <i>āšip šarri</i> (“royal <esp:techterms term="exorcist">exorcist</esp:techterms>”). But by the late 8th century, it appears that they had been ousted or superseded by the <esp:link page="families" bookmark="gabbu-ilani-eres">descendants of Gabbu-ilani-ereš</esp:link>, <i>ummânu</i> ("chief scholar") of Assurnasirpal II (and thus Ištaran-mudammiq’s contemporary).</p>

<p>When Sargon II inauspiciously died in battle in the summer of 705, and when - even more inauspiciously - his body was never found, his son and heir <esp:glossary term="Sennacherib (person)">Sennacherib</esp:glossary> ordered the court to move to <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary> for a fresh beginning. Sennacherib ignored Kalhu, commissioned no building work on any of Nabu’s temples and never mentioned him in any of <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/rinap/rinap3/corpus" hide-print="yes" rel="external">his copious royal inscriptions</esp:link>, except in occasional collective invocations to all the great gods for their blessings or curses<!-- (Pomponio 1978: 78–9)-->. Yet even then,  royal scholarship was not confined to Nineveh. Even the most trusted scholars came and went from court.</p>

<p><esp:glossary term="Nabu-zuqup-kenu (person)">Nabu-zuqup-kenu</esp:glossary>, scribe to both Sargon II and Sennacherib, wrote over 60 surviving scholarly tablets, nearly two-thirds of which explicitly state that they were written in Kalhu <esp:ref referent="hunger1968" page="90-95, nos. 293–311, of which nos. 293–294 and 305 name Kalhu"/>. However, the tablets themselves belong to the <esp:techterms term="Kuyunjik collection">Kuyunjik collection</esp:techterms> of the British Museum, most likely meaning that they were excavated by <esp:glossary term="Layard, Austen Henry (person)">Layard</esp:glossary> and his associates from the royal citadel of Nineveh.</p> 

<esp:image file="ancientcity/ashmolean-1957-1-2.jpg" description="Ivory throne arm" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.ashmolean.org/ash/amps/iraq-navel/palacelife/1957-1+2.htm" title="View large image on Ashmolean Museum's website" hide-print="yes" rel="external"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img227">Arm of a throne once belonging to king Esarhaddon, found in Nabu's temple.</esp:bookmark> The ivory was burned in antiquity, turning it a black colour. 1957.1+2, Ashmolean Museum, Oxford <esp:link url="http://www.ashmolean.org/ash/amps/iraq-navel/palacelife/1957-1+2.htm" title="View large image" hide-print="yes" rel="external">View large image on Ashmolean Museum website</esp:link>. © Ashmolean Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Nabu-zuqup-kenu’s sons, Esarhaddon's <i>rab āšipi</i> ("chief <i>āšipu</i>-healer") <esp:glossary term="Adad-šumu-uṣur (person)">Adad-šumu-uṣur</esp:glossary> and chief scribe <esp:glossary term="Nabu-zeru-lešir (person)">Nabu-zeru-lešir</esp:glossary>, are well attested in Assyrian court correspondence from Nineveh, sometimes in collaboration with the king's chief <esp:techterms term="lamenter">lamenter</esp:techterms> <esp:glossary term="Urad-Ea (person)">Urad-Ea</esp:glossary> and other colleagues. But Adad-šumu-uṣur spent at least some of his time in Ezida at Kalhu, where he is documented performing a ritual against two types of fungi that had infested Ezida (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa13/P334243" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAA 13: 71</esp:link>). His nephew, the <esp:techterms term="crown prince">crown prince</esp:techterms>’s <i>āšipu</i> <esp:glossary term="Šumaya (person)">Šumaya</esp:glossary>, petitioned for a move to Kalhu after the death of his father Nabu-zeru-lešir. That suggests that Nabu-zeru-lešir too was based in Ezida there.</p>

<p>And many of these men's tablets have been found in Nabu's temple. Adad-šumu-uṣur owned a tablet from the terrestrial <esp:techterms term="omen">omen</esp:techterms> series <i>Šumma ālu</i>  ("If a city (is set on a height)") (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/P363460" rel="external" hide-print="yes">CTN 4: 45</esp:link>). One of Nabu-zeru-lešir's son (possibly Šumaya) copied an ominous calendar “for the prolongation of his life” (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/P363474" rel="external" hide-print="yes">CTN 4: 59</esp:link>). Further sons or descendants of Nabu-zuqup-kenu are mentioned in colophons of two tablets of physiognomic omens <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/theworldoftheipu/divinatoryseries/signsofappearance/" hide-print="yes" rel="external"><i>Alandimmû</i></esp:link> and another of unidentified omens (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/P363489,P363493,P363503" rel="external" hide-print="yes">CTN 4: 74; 78; 89</esp:link>). <esp:glossary term="Nabu-leʾi (person)">Nabu-le’i</esp:glossary>, son of Adad-šumu-uṣur’s close associate Urad-Ea, was the scribe of a hitherto unidentified ritual (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/P363601" rel="external" hide-print="yes">CTN 4: 187</esp:link>), which he “copied like its original for him to see”.</p>

<esp:h>The end</esp:h>

<p>Ezida continued to function perhaps right until the end of empire. <esp:glossary term="Assurbanipal (person)">Assurbanipal</esp:glossary> refurbished and re-roofed it "in glad singing and celebration", while <esp:glossary term="Aššur-etel-ilani (person)">Aššur-etel-ilani</esp:glossary> (r. 630?-623? BC) carried out repairs to its east wall and <i>akītu</i> suite. At least for the first two decades of Assurbanipal’s reign the temple gave out short-term loans of grain to local inhabitants in Nabu’s name <esp:ref referent="parker1957"/>, and until 621<esp:techterms term="eponym">*</esp:techterms> BC or later it received private <esp:techterms term="votive">votive</esp:techterms> gifts of slaves and land for Nabu as "scribe of the universe" or "scribe of <esp:glossary term="Esaggila (place)">Esaggila</esp:glossary>" (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa12/P336733,P336734,P336278,P336797" rel="external" hide-print="yes">SAA 12: 95–98</esp:link>). Such <esp:link page="legaldocuments">legal documents</esp:link> were witnessed by the temple’s cultic and domestic - but not scholarly - personnel, as well as the royal representative (<i>qēpu</i>, lit. "trusted one").</p> 

<p>A lack of dateable <esp:techterms term="colophon">colophons</esp:techterms> prevents us from determining whether scholarly tablets continued to be written or deposited in the room opposite Nabu’s shrine, but clearly several hundred were still in situ when the building ceased to function as a temple, presumably when the city fell in 614 BC. Likewise, copies of Esarhaddon’s <esp:link page="vte-intro">Succession Treaty</esp:link> of 672 BC, that had bound citizens, scholars and <esp:techterms term="vassal">vassals</esp:techterms> to supporting the appointment of Assurbanipal and <esp:glossary term="Šamaš-šumu-ukin (person)">Šamaš-šumu-ukin</esp:glossary> as his <esp:techterms term="succession">successors</esp:techterms> (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa02/P336598" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAA 2: 6</esp:link>), must have still been stored somewhere in the temple, or at least close nearby. The temple’s looters smashed them to pieces in the throne room, along with much rich <esp:techterms term="ivory">ivory</esp:techterms> furniture, some pieces of which—to judge by the style of their carvings - dated back to Sargon II or even Adad-nerari III’s time <esp:ref referent="mallowan1966" page="241 (vol. I)"/>, <esp:ref referent="oatesoates2001" page="199"/>.</p> 

<p>After a brief period of squatter occupation in its empty, roofless shell, during which time a bread oven was installed in Nabu’s sanctuary, there were short-lived attempts to repair the shrine and revive its cultic functions <esp:ref referent="mallowan1966" page="284-287 (vol. I)"/>. But there is no direct evidence for the worship of Nabu in <esp:link page="latekalhu">post-Assyrian Kalhu</esp:link>.</p>

<!-- further reading section-->
<esp:reading referent="black2008"/>
<esp:reading referent="oatesoates2001" page="111-123"/>
<esp:reading referent="parker1957"/>
<esp:reading referent="postgate1974"/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/>

<p>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/><br/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/></p>

<esp:author first-names="Eleanor" last-name="Robson"/>
</body></html>
</esp:page>
