<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
	<esp:name>Fort Shalmaneser</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Fort Shalmaneser, the royal arsenal</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>

<p class="firstpara">The building called by its excavators Fort Shalmaneser lay along the southern edge of the city of Kalhu. It was built on an impressive scale by <esp:link page="shalmaneser3">Shalmaneser III</esp:link> to act as his royal residence and a repository for his property. Its large inner courtyards were lined with workshops, treasuries, barracks, private quarters and magnificent state apartments decorated with painted friezes and glazed bricks. Among the objects found in the palace's ruins were exquisite carved ivories, military equipment and administrative tablets which document the life of the court and the army.</p>

<esp:h>Shalmaneser's "review palace": a design innovation</esp:h>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/fortshalmaneser-plan.jpg" description="Plan of Fort Shalmaneser, showing the rooms mentioned in the text" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/fortshalmaneser-plan-large.jpg" title="Large image of the plan of Fort Shalmaneser, showing the rooms mentioned in the text." hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img50"><b>Image 1</b></esp:bookmark>: Plan of Fort Shalmaneser, showing the rooms mentioned in the text. <esp:ref referent="dalleypostgate1984" page="xii"/>. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/fortshalmaneser-plan-large.jpg" title="Large image of the plan of Fort Shalmaneser, showing the rooms mentioned in the text" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link>. Photo: <esp:link page="copyright" bookmark="BISIimages">BSAI/BISI</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p><esp:link page="shalmaneser3">Shalmaneser III</esp:link> undertook a number of building projects in Kalhu, including the <esp:link page="ziggurat">ziggurat and its associated temples</esp:link>, and the <esp:link page="governorspalace">Governor's Palace</esp:link>. But his most ambitious project was undoubtedly the construction of the complex known to us as Fort Shalmaneser. This modern designation was coined by the excavators as a reflection of the building's function and author, after bricks inscribed with the name of Shalmaneser III revealed him to have been responsible for its construction. Inscriptions from the reign of Shalmaneser refer to the building simply as <i>ekallu</i> ("palace"). Only during the reign of <esp:glossary term="Esarhaddon (person)">Esarhaddon</esp:glossary>, who carried out <esp:link page="latekalhu" bookmark="esarhaddon-renovations">renovations to the palace</esp:link>, was the building given its full name, <i>ekal mašarti</i> ("review palace"). This name was an apt description of the structure, which served a dual purpose as the king's residence and a military <esp:techterms term="arsenal">arsenal</esp:techterms>, underlining the dual role of the Assyrian king as statesman and warrior. The function of a review palace is summarised in Esarhaddon's description of the <i>ekal mašarti</i> in <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary>:</p>

<blockquote><p>The review palace... built to maintain the camp (and) to keep thoroughbreds, mules, chariots, military equipment, implements of war, and the plunder of enemies, everything that the god <esp:glossary term="Aššur (deity)">Aššur</esp:glossary>, king of the gods, gave me as my royal share... At new year, in the first month, yearly, without ceasing, let me inspect in it all of the thoroughbreds, mules, camels, military equipment, implements of war, (and) all of the captured enemy soldiers. <esp:ref referent="leichty2011" page="Esarhaddon 1:v 42-45, vi 58-61"/></p></blockquote>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/Mesopotamia-n46-p113.jpg" description="Plans showing the position of the citadel and arsenal in the cities of Kalhu, Dur-Šarruken and Nineveh" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/Mesopotamia-n46-p113-large.jpg" title="Large image of plans showing the position of the citadel and arsenal in the cities of Kalhu, Dur-Šarruken and Nineveh." hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img54"><b>Image 2</b></esp:bookmark>: Plans showing the position of the <esp:techterms term="citadel">citadel</esp:techterms> and <esp:techterms term="arsenal">arsenal</esp:techterms> in the cities of Kalhu,  <esp:glossary term="Dur-Šarruken (place)">Dur-Šarruken</esp:glossary> and <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary>. <esp:ref referent="reade2011" page="113, Fig. 3"/>. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/reade2011-Mesopotamia-p113-large.jpg" title="Large image of plans showing the position of the citadel and arsenal in the cities of Kalhu, Dur-Šarruken and Nineveh" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link> Image: © MESOPOTAMIA, n. 46, p.113, Firenze, <esp:link url="http://www.lelettere.it/site/home.asp" hide-print="yes">Le Lettere</esp:link>, 2011.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Fort Shalmaneser was located in the southeast corner of the city enclosure, well away from the <esp:techterms term="citadel">citadel mound</esp:techterms> which housed the other royal buildings and temples. This became the norm for arsenals in other Assyrian cities. Both <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary> and <esp:glossary term="Dur-Šarruken (place)">Dur-Šarruken</esp:glossary>, for instance, contained review palaces located in the southeast corner of the city, away from the citadel and adjoining the city wall (<b>Image 2</b>). Presumably this was motivated by practical considerations: citadels were not big enough to house such large complexes, and the constant bustle of troops and equipment was better suited to a less central location. For security reasons, it may also have been thought prudent to keep the military structure and its troops away from the seat of power on the citadel.</p>

<esp:h>Parades and inspections</esp:h>

<p>The arsenal at Kalhu was built on a massive scale. Its thick walls enclosed an area of about 30 hectares, while the palace itself measured roughly 200 x 300 metres - about double the size of <esp:link page="assurnasirpal2">Assurnasirpal II's</esp:link> <esp:link page="northwestpalace">Northwest Palace</esp:link>. The size was directly linked to the building's function. Shalmaneser had created the concept of a "review palace" as a place where he could attend to important military matters without leaving his capital, or neglecting his other duties. The palace was composed of two principal parts (<b>Image 1</b>). The larger, northern section of the building was centred around four spacious courtyard areas. The southeast courtyard featured a throne dais inscribed with the name of Shalmaneser III, from which the king was able to preside over military parades and inspections. An even larger parade ground was located outside the palace, stretching some 200 metres to the north and 450 metres to the west. It could be accessed at both ends via the outer city wall, making it ideal during the training and mustering of <esp:techterms term="levy">levies</esp:techterms> which preceded the army's annual campaigns (<b>Image 2</b>).</p>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/BM-132699.jpg" description="Pierced copper plates used to make armour, found in Room SW 7 in Fort Shalmaneser" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img51"><b>Image 3</b></esp:bookmark>: Pierced copper plates used to make armour, found in Room SW 7 in Fort Shalmaneser. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=1341672&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes">BM 132699</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=550223&amp;objectId=1341672&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Around the palace's courtyards were numerous workshops, storage <esp:techterms term="magazine">magazines</esp:techterms>, and ceremonial and residential quarters. The northwest area of the palace was used primarily for the repair and storage of military equipment, the remains of which have been excavated there. The quantities involved must have been staggering: one clay <esp:techterms term="docket">docket</esp:techterms> records the inspection of no fewer that 36,242 bows! Some of the workshops in this area were unusually large and were probably used to accommodate chariots. Elsewhere, storage magazines housed booty and <esp:techterms term="tribute">tribute</esp:techterms>, as shown by an <esp:techterms term="ivory">ivory</esp:techterms> <esp:techterms term="plaque">plaque</esp:techterms> inscribed with the name of <esp:glossary term="Hazael (person)">Hazael</esp:glossary>, king of Damascus, and shells with the name of <esp:glossary term="Irhuleni (person)">Irhuleni</esp:glossary>, king of Hamath - both of whom were defeated by Shalmaneser III. The southwest quadrant of the palace contained four large water jars embedded in a mud-brick bench which kept them cool. The jars were connected to a row of spouts which provided easy access to drinking water for the palace.</p>

<p>The review palace was run by a senior official called <i>rab ekalli</i> ("palace overseer"), whose residence was in the northwest corner of the southeast courtyard (Rooms SE 1-3, 10-12; SW 6; NE 1-2). The decorated apartment was set over two levels, and included a bathroom and kitchen, as well as a well-stocked wine cellar. Excavations of the residence have yielded many fine ornaments, household objects, metal tools and weapons, and even an inscribed clay cylinder of king Esarhaddon.</p>

<esp:h>An elegant royal residence</esp:h>

<p>The southern section of the palace contained a group of state apartments dominated by an imposing throne room (Room T 1) in which the king officiated from atop a <esp:link page="shalmaneser3" bookmark="img60">carved platform</esp:link> depicting Shalmaneser III and his achievements. The walls of the state apartments displayed painted geometric patterns and scenes of the king and his courtiers, as well as protective magical figures and "<esp:techterms term="fish-man">fish-men</esp:techterms>". <esp:techterms term="glaze">Glazed</esp:techterms> bricks were used to decorate external walls and doorways. This part of the palace also housed the residential suites of the royal family (area S), including the <esp:techterms term="queen">queen</esp:techterms>. The apartments, grouped around inner courtyards and beautifully decorated with painted geometric patterns and images of rosettes, <esp:techterms term="pomegranate">pomegranate</esp:techterms> buds and flowers, hint at the luxury enjoyed by their occupants. Locks separated these private quarters from the more public areas of the palace. The queen's household was supervised by a female official, the <i>šakintu</i>. Legal documents belonging to the <i>šakintu</i> and other members of the queen's household have been found in Room S 10, demonstrating the wealth and power enjoyed by elite women <esp:ref referent="dalleypostgate1984" page="9-14"/>.</p>

<esp:h>Tablets, ivories and horse harnesses</esp:h>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/Met-60.145.11.jpg" description="A rare ivory statuette carved in the round, showing a Nubian carrying a monkey, oryx and leopard skins and found in the residence of the rab ekalli at Fort Shalmaneser" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img52"><b>Image 4</b></esp:bookmark>: A rare ivory statuette carved in the round, showing a <esp:glossary term="Nubia (place)">Nubian</esp:glossary> carrying a monkey, oryx and leopard skins. It was found in Room NE 2 of Fort Shalmaneser, and probably formed part of the collection of the <i>rab ekalli</i>, the senior official in change of the arsenal. Metropolitan Museum of Art, <esp:link url="http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/works-of-art/60.145.11" hide-print="yes">60.145.11</esp:link>. Metropolitan Museum of Art <esp:link url="http://www.metmuseum.org/research/image-resources" hide-print="yes">OASC licence</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.metmuseum.org/Collections/search-the-collections/325089#fullscreen" hide-print="yes">View large image on the Metropolitan Museum's website.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Excavations in the palace during the 1950s have uncovered a large quantity of objects, including military equipment such as <esp:techterms term="bronze">bronze</esp:techterms> horse harnesses, weapons and armour (<b>Image 3</b>), ornaments, pottery vessels and <esp:techterms term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> texts. Some of these cuneiform <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablets</esp:techterms> had been used by occupants after 612 BC to raise the floor levels (Rooms NE 48-49). The texts include records of wine rations distributed to the royal household and court officials. These so-called <esp:techterms term="Nimrud Wine Lists">Nimrud Wine Lists</esp:techterms> provide valuable information about the composition of the court at Kalhu, which apparently included foreign experts such as <esp:link page="hieroglyphs">Egyptian scribes</esp:link>. Another important group of texts, the <esp:techterms term="Nimrud Horse Lists">Nimrud Horse Lists</esp:techterms>, records details of musters of men, horses and mules, sometimes in very large numbers. <esp:techterms term="Assyriology">Assyriologists</esp:techterms> have used these lists to reconstruct a picture of the Assyrian army (see <esp:ref referent="dezso2006"/>).</p>

<p>Among the finest discoveries made at Fort Shalmaneser were thousands of fragments of carved <esp:techterms term="ivory">ivory</esp:techterms>, produced by <esp:glossary term="Phoenicia (place)">Phoenician</esp:glossary> craftsmen. Some of the ivories were discovered in workshops and magazines, where they were stored along with other tribute. Others decorated the apartments of select residents of the palace, such as the <i>rab ēkalli</i>, whose living quarters contained a particularly fine collection of ivory carvings (<b>Image 4</b>). Presumably these ivories were used to decorate the residential quarters of the palace at the time of its destruction in 612 BC, and so tell us something about the occupants' personal preferences as well as the high status that they enjoyed. These decorative plaques are now often referred to collectively as the <esp:techterms term="Nimrud ivories">Nimrud ivories</esp:techterms> and examples are held in museums across the world. <b>Image 5</b> shows an ivory from Room SW 12 featuring a winged griffin, which is now in the collection of Birmingham Museum and Art Gallery <esp:ref referent="herrmannlaidlaw2013in7" page="no. 231"/>.</p>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/BMAG-1965-A451_2.jpg" description="Carved ivory plaque depicting a winged griffin" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/BMAG-1965-A451_2-large.jpg" title="Large image of Carved ivory plaque depicting a winged griffin" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img155"><b>Image 5</b></esp:bookmark>: Carved ivory plaque showing a winged griffin, found in Room SW 12 of Fort Shalmaneser. This object is now in the collection at <esp:link url="http://www.bmag.org.uk/" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Birmingham Museum and Art Gallery</esp:link> accession number 1965A451.2 (ND 11099). This 2014 photo shows the ivory after <esp:link page="bmag-conservation">undergoing conservation treatment</esp:link> at the museum. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/BMAG-1965-A451_2-large.jpg" title="Large image of Carved ivory plaque depicting a winged griffin" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link>. © Birmingham Museums.</esp:caption></esp:image>
	
<esp:h>Skeletons and squatters</esp:h>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/mass-burial.jpg" description="Mass burial in room S 42 of Fort Shalmaneser, of individuals who had apparently been killed during the sack of Kalhu in 612 BC" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/mass-burial-large.jpg" title="Large image of the plan of Fort Shalmaneser, showing the rooms mentioned in the text." hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img53"><b>Image 6</b></esp:bookmark>: Mass burial in room S 42 of Fort Shalmaneser, excavated by <esp:techterms term="British School of Archaeology in Iraq">BSAI</esp:techterms>, 1950s. These people had apparently been killed during the sack of Kalhu in 612 BC, and were hastily buried when the locals returned to make their home among the ruins. <esp:ref referent="oatesoates2001" page="193, Fig. 119"/>. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/mass-burial-large.jpg" title="Large image of a mass burial in room S 42 of Fort Shalmaneser, of individuals who had apparently been killed during the sack of Kalhu in 612 BC" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link>. Photo: <esp:link page="copyright" bookmark="BISIimages">BSAI/BISI</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>The arsenal continued to be used by Shalmaneser's successors for military and administrative purposes. His grandson <esp:glossary term="Adad-nerari III (person)">Adad-nerari III</esp:glossary> (r. 810-783 BC) added to the building, as shown by bricks and thresholds inscribed with his name. However, the court's move away from Kalhu at the end of the 8th century - first to Dur-Šarruken and then to Nineveh, both of which had a "review palace" of their own - diminished Fort Shamaneser's importance. This may account for the dilapidation described by Esarhaddon in inscriptions celebrating his renovations of the palace.</p>

<p>Shalmaneser's arsenal continued to be used until the very end of the Assyrian empire. The city suffered a great deal of destruction during the two waves of <esp:glossary term="Media (place)">Median</esp:glossary> invasion in 614 and 612 BC, and Fort Shalmaneser was no exception. Evidence of fire is clearly marked on many of the objects found in the palace; even the throne room was not exempt. It seems that the inhabitants of Kalhu tried to repair the damage after the first attack, and re-buried <esp:techterms term="foundation deposit">foundation deposits</esp:techterms> with <esp:techterms term="apotropaic">apotropaic</esp:techterms> <esp:techterms term="figurine">figurines</esp:techterms> in an ultimately futile attempt to ward off further misfortune. After the final sack of 612 BC, the locals returned to the city, burying the dead (<b>Image 6</b>) and making hasty repairs to make the building habitable again. That this "squatter" occupation lasted for a significant period of time is shown by the fact that, in places, 2 metres of debris covered the original 612 BC level of the building.</p>
	
<esp:reading referent="dalleypostgate1984"/>
<esp:reading referent="dezso2006"/>
<esp:reading referent="hermann1992"/>
<esp:reading referent="kinnierwilson1972"/>
<esp:reading referent="oatesoates2001" page="144-194"/>
<esp:reading referent="postgatereade1976-1980" page="317-319"/>
<esp:reading referent="reade2011"/>

<p>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/><br/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/></p>
<esp:author first-names="Silvie" last-name="Zamazalová"/>

</body></html>
</esp:page>
