<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
	<esp:name>The Governor's Palace</esp:name>
	<esp:title>The Governor's Palace</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>

<p class="firstpara">The Governor's Palace is a modern designation given to a beautifully decorated building which lay to the northwest of Nabu's temple, <esp:link page="ezida">Ezida</esp:link>. The site proved to be the location of an important collection of cuneiform tablets, including texts relating to the activities of several governors which gave the building its name.</p>

<esp:h>A governor's residence?</esp:h>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/governorspalace-siteplan.jpg" description="Plan of the excavated areas of the Governor's Palace, showing the rooms mentioned in the text" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/governorspalace-siteplan-large.jpg" title="Large image of the plan of the excavated areas of the Governor's Palace, showing the rooms mentioned in the text." hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img46"><b>Image 1</b></esp:bookmark>: Plan of the excavated areas of the Governor's Palace, showing the rooms mentioned in the text. <esp:ref referent="oatesoates2001" page="133, Fig. 83"/>. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/governorspalace-siteplan-large.jpg" title="Large image of the plan of the excavated areas of the Governor's Palace, showing the rooms mentioned in the text" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link>. Photo: <esp:link page="copyright" bookmark="BISIimages">BSAI/BISI</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>The sumptuously decorated palace was located near the central part of Kalhu's <esp:techterms term="citadel">citadel</esp:techterms> mound, next to the important <esp:link page="ezida">temple of the god Nabu</esp:link>. Only a part of the structure has been uncovered so far. This area measures approximately 50 x 50 metres and seems to have lain at the heart of a much larger complex. A plan of the excavated areas (<b>Image 1</b>) gives some idea of the building's overall layout and function. Like most Assyrian palaces, it was built around a large central courtyard. This was flanked in the north and south by a number of large audience chambers which were used for official business. The palace walls were lavishly painted with geometric patterns in black, white, red and brilliant cobalt blue. The use of blue paint was particularly prominent in the northern suites of the palace, where such a vibrant colour must have had a striking effect on visitors. The palace also featured a well appointed ablution room, or <esp:techterms term="rite, ritual">ritual</esp:techterms> bathroom, which  was located in the south-west corner, next to room B. The room had been waterproofed using <esp:techterms term="bitumen">bitumen</esp:techterms> (a component of petroleum collected from springs) and included a carefully-constructed drainage system. The walls were decorated with black and white frescoes of concentric rosettes or circles (<b>Image 2</b>).</p>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/governors-palace-mallowan1950-iraq12-pl30_1.jpg" description="Detail of the ablution room in the southwest corner of the Governor's Palace" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/governors-palace-mallowan1950-iraq12-pl30_1-large.jpg" title="Large image of a detail of the ablution room in the southwest corner of the Governor's Palace." hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img47"><b>Image 2</b></esp:bookmark>: Detail of the ablution room in the southwest corner of the Governor's Palace. Remains of geometric paintings are visible on the walls, made using black and white paint. Striking red and cobalt blue colours were also used in other areas of the palace <esp:ref referent="mallowan1950" page="plate XXX, no. 1"/>. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/governors-palace-mallowan1950-iraq12-pl30_1-large.jpg" title="Large image of a detail of the ablution room in the southwest corner of the Governor's Palace" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link>. Photo: <esp:link page="copyright" bookmark="BISIimages">BSAI/BISI</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>The mud-brick palace was probably built by king <esp:link page="shalmaneser3">Shalmaneser III</esp:link> (r. 858-824 BC), as bricks inscribed with his name have been found embedded in the building's pavements. However, it has been suggested that these bricks were left over from Shalmaneser's construction of the <esp:link page="ziggurat">ziggurat</esp:link> and may have been re-used by his grandson, <esp:glossary term="Adad-nerari III (person)">Adad-nerari III</esp:glossary> (r. 810-783 BC), to build the Governor's Palace.</p>

<p>The <esp:techterms term="governor">Governor</esp:techterms>'s Palace was excavated under the direction of <esp:glossary term="Mallowan, Max (person)">Sir Max Mallowan</esp:glossary> during his first two <esp:techterms term="excavation season">seasons</esp:techterms> at Nimrud (1949 and 1950). It was given the initial designation of the "1949 building", but this was quickly replaced with the more imaginative "Governor's Palace" when cuneiform <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablets</esp:techterms> relating to the activities of several of Kalhu's governors came to light.</p>

<esp:h>The Governor's Palace archive</esp:h>

<p>The building has yielded some 230 tablets, most of which were found in three neighbouring rooms (K, M and S) in the northern part of the palace. Room S also contained a collection of over 100 pieces of fine <esp:techterms term="palace ware">palace ware</esp:techterms>, nicknamed the "<esp:link page="maapots" bookmark="dinner service">governor's dinner service</esp:link>" by the excavators, which rested on a mud-brick "platform" or "table" (<b>Image 3</b>). <esp:techterms term="cuneiform">Cuneiform</esp:techterms> documents were found underneath this platform, which perhaps originally served as a sort of filing cabinet for the tablets. The administrative wing of <esp:glossary term="Assurnasirpal II (person)">Assurnasirpal II's</esp:glossary> <esp:link page="northwestpalace">Northwest Palace</esp:link> used brick boxes for tablet storage, and a similar arrangement may have existed in the Governor's Palace. It would have been easy to fill in the boxes and convert them into a table when the tablets they housed were no longer needed.</p>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/BM-1992_0302_185.jpg" description="An example of one of the hundred or so pieces of pottery palace ware found in room S of the Governor's Palace" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=220401&amp;objectId=369231&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img48"><b>Image 3</b></esp:bookmark>: The beaker in the middle of this group of objects is one of the hundred or so pieces of pottery <esp:techterms term="palace ware">palace ware</esp:techterms> found in room S of the Governor's Palace. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=369231&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">BM 1992,0302.185</esp:link>. Many other museums hold examplesincluding Cambridge's <esp:link page="maapots">Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology</esp:link>  <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=220401&amp;objectId=369231&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>The tablets are now known as the Governor's Palace archive, but in fact they represent a collection of often disparate texts rather than a single coherent archive. They fall into three main groups: <esp:link page="legaldocuments">private legal documents</esp:link> (found mainly in rooms K and M),  administrative texts, and letters (both in room S). Some of the tablets were dated using the Assyrian system of <esp:techterms term="eponym">eponyms</esp:techterms> (<i>limmu</i>). With the exception of a single text which dates from the reign of Shalmaneser III, the rest of the dated tablets cover the period between 802 and 710 BC. We do not know why there were no new tablets after this date. The end of the archive coincides with the completion of <esp:glossary term="Dur-Šarruken (place)">Dur-Šarruken</esp:glossary>, <esp:glossary term="Sargon II (person)">Sargon II's</esp:glossary> purpose-built royal capital, which for a brief period replaced Kalhu as the administrative centre of the Assyrian empire. Although Dur-Šarruken was abandoned as a capital after Sargon's death, Kalhu never regained its previous status and the capital was moved to Nineveh instead. The move to Dur-Šarruken was perhaps linked to the changes in the Governor's Palace, which apparently ceased to perform its earlier administrative function. This also seems to confirm that the palace was not the seat of the governor of Kalhu, at least at the end of the 8th century: if it had been, we might expect to find documents from his archive even after 710 BC, since the city of Kalhu continued to function as the <esp:techterms term="province">provincial</esp:techterms> capital long after it lost the status of royal capital.</p>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/BM-130865.jpg" description="A fine cylinder seal made of translucent chalcedony, found in room B which adjoined the ablution room" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=369254&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img49"><b>Image 4</b></esp:bookmark>: <esp:techterms term="impression">Impression</esp:techterms> of a fine <esp:techterms term="seal, sealing">cylinder seal</esp:techterms> made of translucent <esp:techterms term="chalcedony">chalcedony</esp:techterms>, found in room B which adjoined the ablution room (<b>Image 2</b>). The head of the excavation, <esp:glossary term="Mallowan, Max (person)">Max Mallowan</esp:glossary>, thought that it must have belonged to the governor of Kalhu himself, but there is no evidence to confirm this. Read a detailed <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=369254&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">description of the scene carved onto object BM 130865</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=159736&amp;objectId=369254&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>The documents mention the names of five governors of Kalhu who held the office in the 9th and 8th centuries BC; some of the other tablets apparently belonged to members of the governors' households. As a result, the texts record a varied mix of private matters - such as property sales, receipts and loans - and official business in the form of administrative documents and correspondence <esp:ref referent="postgate1973" page="16-23"/>. These help to shed light on the everyday activities of the governor. Among the more interesting letters is a complaint from the governor of <esp:glossary term="Assur (place)">Assur</esp:glossary> to his colleague in Kalhu about a fire which resulted in the destruction of lands used for grazing: "Your subjects have set the desert on fire, and as far as the land of Suhu and as far as the land of Hadallu, it has eaten up the whole desert. Make enquiries... Who [    ] the fire?" <esp:ref referent="postgate1973" page="187-188, no. 188"/></p>

<esp:h>Destruction and post-Assyrian occupation</esp:h>

<p>The final days of the Governor's Palace are difficult to reconstruct since we have no textual sources after 710 BC, but the "governor's dinner service" found in room S seems to date from the very end of the Assyrian empire. This would suggest that the building - or at least parts of it - continued to be used into the late 7th century. When the Assyrian empire fell, the Governor's Palace was destroyed like many other buildings in Kalhu, such as <esp:link page="ezida">Ezida</esp:link> and the <esp:glossary term="Burnt Palace (place)">Burnt Palace</esp:glossary>. However, this did not deter squatters from making a home in its ruins, and even burying their dead there. The building continued to be inhabited into the <esp:techterms term="Hellenistic">Hellenistic</esp:techterms> period, when the central courtyard was turned into a burial ground.</p>

<esp:reading referent="fales2012"/>
<esp:reading referent="oatesoates2001"/>
<esp:reading referent="postgate1973"/>
<esp:reading referent="postgatereade1976-1980"/>

<p>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/>.<br/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/></p>
<esp:author first-names="Silvie" last-name="Zamazalová"/>
</body></html>
</esp:page>
