<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
	<esp:name>Late Kalhu</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Kalhu from the 7th century to the post-Assyrian period</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>

<p class="firstpara">At the end of the 8th century BC, <esp:glossary term="Sargon II (person)">Sargon II</esp:glossary> (r. 721-705 BC) moved the seat of royal power from Kalhu to his recently completed new capital, <esp:link url="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/sargon/essentials/cities/durarruken" hide-print="yes" rel="external">Dur-Šarruken</esp:link> (modern <esp:glossary term="Khorsabad (place)">Khorsabad</esp:glossary>). Although Dur-Šarruken was abandoned by the court after Sargon's death, Kalhu never regained its capital status. Nevertheless, it continued to serve as <esp:techterms term="province">provincial</esp:techterms> capital and an important centre of learning until the very end of the Assyrian empire, and was occupied into the <esp:techterms term="Hellenistic">Hellenistic</esp:techterms> period and beyond.</p>

<esp:h>Kalhu in the 7th century BC</esp:h>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/BM-90248.jpg" description="Clay brick with inscription of king Esarhaddon" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img31"><b>Image 1</b></esp:bookmark>: The <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/rinap/rinap4/Q003251" hide-print="yes" rel="external">inscription on this brick</esp:link> begins, “The palace of <esp:glossary term="Esarhaddon (person)">Esarhaddon</esp:glossary>, king of Assyria”, showing clearly that he intended to reside there, at least some of the time. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=1351957&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 90248</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=1097273001&amp;objectId=1351957&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>After the ominous death of <esp:glossary term="Sargon II (person)">Sargon II</esp:glossary> on a battlefield in <esp:glossary term="Anatolia (place)">Anatolia</esp:glossary> - where his body was lost forever - his son <esp:glossary term="Sennacherib (person)">Sennacherib</esp:glossary> made the decision to move his court away from Dur-Šarruken and its ill-fated associations. He didn't, however, return to Kalhu, which had served as the Assyrian royal capital since the reign of <esp:link page="assurnasirpal2">Assurnasirpal II</esp:link> (r. 883-859 BC). Instead, Sennacherib chose the ancient city of <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary> (modern <esp:glossary term="Mosul (place)">Mosul</esp:glossary>) and renovated it extensively. As a result, Kalhu was no longer the administrative centre of the empire, but it remained one of Assyria's key cities. As the seat of the <esp:techterms term="governor">governor</esp:techterms> of the province of Kalhu, it must have <esp:link page="governorspalace">continued to house local administration</esp:link>, even though such records from the 7th century have not been found.</p>

<p>The city had for some time represented an important centre of scholarship, and this role continued into the 7th century. It was home to many prominent <esp:techterms term="scholar">scholars</esp:techterms>, some of whom acted as senior advisors to the Assyrian king. The <esp:link page="ezida">temple of Nabu</esp:link> housed an impressive collection of literary and scholarly materials which were used by the king and his scholars to aid his decision-making and guide his relationship with the gods. Even after the court moved permanently to Nineveh, many of these men, such as <esp:link page="families">Nabu-zuqup-kena</esp:link>, spent at least some of their time in Kalhu. This is clear for instance from the <esp:techterms term="colophon">colophons</esp:techterms> (scribal postscripts) of many <esp:techterms term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablets</esp:techterms>, which record Kalhu as the place where they were written.</p>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/BM-140435.jpg" description="A clay figurine in the shape of a lahmu, a protective deity" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img32"><b>Image 2</b></esp:bookmark>: A clay <esp:techterms term="figurine">figurine</esp:techterms> in the shape of a protective <i><esp:techterms term="lahmu">lahmu</esp:techterms></i> spirit. Found at <esp:link page="fortshalmaneser">Fort Shalmaneser</esp:link>, the figure was used during the reigns of <esp:glossary term="Esarhaddon (person)">Esarhaddon</esp:glossary> and <esp:glossary term="Sin-šarru-iškun (person)">Sin-šarru-iškun</esp:glossary>, both of whom carried out building work at Kalhu. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=315028&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 140435</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=108982&amp;objectId=315028&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>In addition, the city of Kalhu was the location of important state documents, including perhaps the <esp:link page="vte-intro">Succession Treaties</esp:link> of king Esarhaddon (r. 680-669 BC). These documents record a series of loyalty oaths in which Assyria's <esp:techterms term="vassal">vassals</esp:techterms> swore to uphold Esarhaddon's <esp:techterms term="succession">succession</esp:techterms> plans. The treaties were destroyed by looters in Nabu's temple in 612 BC, but it is unclear whether they were originally stored there. However, the temple was certainly used to safeguard the <esp:link page="vte-intro" bookmark="h_thesealimpressions">three seals of the god Aššur</esp:link> which were <esp:techterms term="impression">impressed</esp:techterms> on to the treaties alongside the <esp:techterms term="seal, sealing">seal</esp:techterms> of the king - a sign of Ezida's continued importance in the 7th century.</p>

<esp:h><esp:bookmark id="esarhaddon-renovations" title="Esarhaddon's renovations at Kalhu">A royal capital once more?</esp:bookmark></esp:h>

<p>Much of the building activity now naturally focused on Nineveh, particularly during the reign of Sennacherib who carried out no new work at Kalhu. His son and successor Esarhaddon, however, took a great deal of interest in the city. Around 672 BC, towards the end of his reign, he rebuilt part of the city wall and made significant improvements to <esp:link page="fortshalmaneser">Fort Shalmaneser</esp:link>. He added a new terrace and created an impressive new entrance consisting of a vaulted ramp which led from a newly-rebuilt <esp:techterms term="postern gate">postern gate</esp:techterms> directly into the palace through a series of painted rooms. Inscriptions on both sides of the gate commemorated this construction work, as did clay cylinders which were perhaps originally deposited inside Fort Shalmaneser's walls (<b>Image 1</b>).</p>

<p>It is possible that Esarhaddon's activities at Kalhu were intended as a prelude to reclaiming it as royal capital. There is some, albeit very limited evidence, that he may have lived at Kalhu briefly towards the end of his reign: a partially preserved letter mentions that the king's courtiers "are all in Kalhu", perhaps indicating that the court had moved there from Nineveh (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa13/P334738/html" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAA 13: 152</esp:link>). While Esarhaddon's successors made their home at Nineveh, some at least continued to carry out building repairs at Kalhu. The last king to do so was <esp:glossary term="Sin-šarru-iškun (person)">Sin-šarru-iškun</esp:glossary> (r. 624-612 BC). His reconstruction of the <esp:link page="ezida">temple of Nabu</esp:link> was violently undone when the city was sacked and most of its buildings put to the torch by <esp:glossary term="Media (place)">Median</esp:glossary> invaders in 614 BC, and again two years later.</p>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/ND5202.jpg" description="Terracotta figurine in the Hellenistic style, showing mother and child" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/ND5202_large.jpg" title="Large image of a terracotta figurine in the Hellenistic style, showing mother and child." hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img33"><b>Image 3</b></esp:bookmark>: Terracotta figurine in the <esp:techterms term="Hellenistic">Hellenistic</esp:techterms> style, showing mother and child. It was found in a pit cut into the wall of the <esp:link page="ezida">temple of Nabu</esp:link>, and probably dates from the early 2nd century BC. ND 5202 <esp:ref referent="oatesoates2001" page="265, Fig. 170"/>. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/latekalhu_1_large.jpg" title="Large image of a terracotta figurine in the Hellenistic style, showing mother and child" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link>. Photo: Iraq Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<esp:h>Kalhu in the post-Assyrian period</esp:h>

<p>The fall of the Assyrian empire at the end of the 7th century BC represented a major historical and political  break, but in some ways life in Assyria continued as before. After the city's destruction, the locals returned to make their home among the ruins of the <esp:techterms term="citadel">citadel</esp:techterms> mound and Fort Shalmaneser, presumably because their walls offered a degree of protection. However, archaeological evidence shows that living in the city was far from safe: the Medes' first attack in 614 BC was followed by another in 612, and there is evidence that the occupants of post-Assyrian Kalhu suffered further destruction from unknown attackers on several occasions. The "<esp:link page="fortshalmaneser" bookmark="h_skeletonsandsquatters">squatter occupation</esp:link>" of the city's monumental ruins probably did not last long, as the material remains from this period, such as pottery, look no different from those of the late Assyrian period - clearly, they were not in use long enough for changes to appear.</p>

<p>However, this did not spell the end of the city. There is some evidence of occupation and rebuilding during the <esp:techterms term="Neo-Babylonian">Neo-Babylonian</esp:techterms> and <esp:techterms term="Achaemenid">Achaemenid</esp:techterms> periods in the 6th to 4th centuries, but unfortunately no written sources have survived to help us understand what was going on in Kalhu at this time. In 401 BC the Greek soldier and historian <esp:glossary term="Xenophon (person)">Xenophon</esp:glossary> passed by the city (which he calls Larissa) and reported that it was all but deserted, with only the dilapidated <esp:link page="ziggurat">ziggurat</esp:link> providing refuge to the local people (<i>Anabasis</i> III:4).</p>

<p>By far the most extensive remains come from the <esp:techterms term="Hellenistic">Hellenistic</esp:techterms> period, when a succession of small settlements sprung up in the citadel area. The village was destroyed in a fire but its inhabitants left behind coins, pottery and numerous other small finds (<b>Image 3</b>). These have enabled the excavators to date the village community to c.250-140 BC, and to build up a detailed picture of daily life in Hellenistic Assyria. We know, for example, that members of this community lived in small houses whose rooms were arranged around a small courtyard - much like the palaces on whose ruins they stood. And the ovens in which the villagers baked their bread resemble the ovens which are still used today, more than two millennia later.</p>

<esp:reading referent="oatesoates2001"/>
<esp:reading referent="postgatereade1976-1980"/>
<esp:reading referent="reade1982"/>

<p>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/>.<br/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/></p>

<esp:author first-names="Silvie" last-name="Zamazalová"/>

</body></html>
</esp:page>
