<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

	<esp:name>Northwest Palace</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Assurnasirpal's Northwest Palace</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>
	
<p class="firstpara">Early in his reign, king <esp:link page="assurnasirpal2">Assurnasirpal II</esp:link> commissioned a fabulous new palace, sited on the royal <esp:techterms term="citadel">citadel</esp:techterms> on the east bank of the <esp:glossary term="Tigris (place)">Tigris</esp:glossary> river. The palace covered 28,000 m<sup>2</sup>, some 7 acres, and was designed around three or four courtyards. All the public areas were sumptuously decorated, to instill awe and wonder into palace visitors. The more private areas included a burial place for female members of the royal family. Formal and informal excavations since the 1840s have scattered finds from the palace <esp:link page="museumsworldwide" bookmark="nwp-nd-map">all over the world</esp:link>.</p> 

<esp:h>Depicting Assyria's might</esp:h>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/nwpalace-plan-sm.jpg" 
description="Plan of Assurnasirpal's Northwest Palace in Kalhu" position="float"><esp:link  url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/nwpalace-plan.jpg" title="Plan of Assurnasirpal's Northwest Palace in Kalhu (large)" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img34"><b>Image 1</b></esp:bookmark>: Plan of Assurnasirpal's Northwest Palace in Kalhu, showing the room numbers mentioned in the text <esp:ref referent="oatesoates2001" page="Figs. 15 and 33"/>. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/nwpalace-plan.jpg" title="Plan of Assurnasirpal's Northwest Palace in Kalhu (large)" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link>. Photo: <esp:link page="copyright" bookmark="BISIimages">BSAI/BISI</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>All of the public spaces of the palace were sumptuously decorated, designed to impress and intimidate those privileged few who were allowed to enter. The walls were lined with <esp:techterms term="bas-relief">bas-relief</esp:techterms> sculptures, brightly coloured, which sent messages of Assyria’s glory. They focused on four themes in particular: the army’s strength and prowess; the king’s devout attention to the gods; the material prosperity; and the divine protection that flowed from those ways of behaving. Divine beings protected and blessed those that entered the palace, while warding off evil. Processions of dignitaries were shown, bringing <esp:techterms term="tribute">tribute</esp:techterms> to the king. Scenes of warfare illustrated the dire consequences of not capitulating to Assyria’s might. The king was depicted repeatedly making offerings and paying homage to the great god <esp:glossary term="Aššur (deity)">Aššur</esp:glossary> and the deities of war.</p> 

<p>Every one of the sculptured slabs was hewn by slave labour from nearby quarries, and dragged by rollers to the palace. There they were designed and carved by master craftsmen, who chose particular sets of images to fit the function of each room or suite. In this way, palace visitors and occupants were surrounded by messages about the king and his empire, which were suited to the context. For the benefit of those who could read <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/knpp/cuneiformrevealed" hide-print="yes" rel="external">cuneiform</esp:link>—but perhaps equally to impress those who could not—each panel was also overlain with a long inscription (the so-called <esp:link page="sia-intro">Standard Inscription</esp:link>) extolling Assurnasirpal’s ancestry, piety and military might, as well as a brief narrative of how the palace itself had been built.</p>

<esp:h>Managing the palace</esp:h>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/zt13.jpg" 
description="Room ZT 13 of Assurnasirpal's Northwest Palace in Kalhu, with storage jars and a cupboard in situ" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/zt13-large.jpg" title="Room ZT 13 of Assurnasirpal's Northwest Palace in Kalhu, with storage jars and a cupboard in situ (large)" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img35"><b>Image 2</b></esp:bookmark>: Room ZT 13 of Assurnasirpal's Northwest Palace in Kalhu was used as a storage area in the late 7th century BC. This photo, taken during 1950s excavations by <esp:glossary term="Mallowan, Max (person)">Max Mallowan's</esp:glossary> team, shows the pottery that was found there as well as a wall cupboard. The thick walls supported an external tower but also helped insulate the room from cold and heat <esp:ref referent="mallowan1966" page="176, Fig. 108"/>. <!--is ZT 13 the same as Room 31?--> <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/zt13-large.jpg" title="Room ZT 13 of Assurnasirpal's Northwest Palace in Kalhu, with storage jars and a cupboard in situ (large)" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link>. Photo: <esp:link page="copyright" bookmark="BISIimages">BSAI/BISI</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>The northernmost wing was the most public. It contained administrative offices and storerooms, workshops and the palace archives. The were probably two or three entrances: a ceremonial one to the east, a service entrance to the north which led to the administrative quarters of the god <esp:glossary term="Nergal (deity)">Nergal</esp:glossary>'s temple, and perhaps another to the west with stairs down to the river. At the northeast corner there was a reception suite (Rooms 21, 25–26 and 32–34), which was perhaps the office of the <i>rab ēkalli</i> ("palace overseer") or another senior administrator. Two smaller suites of offices were situated immediately next door (Rooms 12-16, 22, 24; and 11, 15).</p> 

<p>The oil and wine stores (Rooms 30-31) were also in this corner of the courtyard, where the administrators could keep an eye on them. One room contained enormous clay storage jars half-sunk into the ground for temperature control, and long benches on which smaller objects could be stacked (<b>Image 2</b>).</p>

<p>Further along the northern range was the <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablet</esp:techterms> archive (Room 4, sometimes also referred to as ZT 4), where in the late 8th century BC <esp:techterms term="scribe">scribes</esp:techterms> <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/aebp/essentials/archives/thenimrudletters" rel="external" hide-print="yes">filed over three hundred letters</esp:link> to kings <esp:glossary term="Tiglath-pileser III (person)">Tiglath-pileser III</esp:glossary> and <esp:glossary term="Sargon II (person)">Sargon II</esp:glossary>.</p>

<esp:h>Encapsulating the empire</esp:h>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/bm-me-124531.jpg" 
description="Stone bas-relief from behind the throne in Assurnasirpal's Northwest Palace in Kalhu, now in the British Museum" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/highlights/highlight_objects/me/s/stone_throne_room_relief.aspx" rel="external" title="The British Museum's page about the stone bas-relief from behind the throne in of Assurnasirpal's Northwest Palace in Kalhu" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img36"><b>Image 3</b></esp:bookmark>: Behind Assurnasirpal's throne was an imposing double image of the king, gesturing to the god <esp:link page="ashur">Aššur</esp:link>. On either side of him winged <esp:techterms term="genie">genies</esp:techterms> fertilised the so-called <esp:techterms term="sacred tree">sacred tree</esp:techterms>. The image was bigger than life size, at nearly 2 metres tall, and probably highly coloured. This carving is now in the British Museum (<esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=367057&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">BM 124531</esp:link>) but other <esp:link page="stonegenies">images from the throne room</esp:link> are now in Cambridge's Fitzwilliam Museum and many other collections worldwide <esp:ref referent="englund2003" page="43-58"/>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/highlights/highlight_objects/me/s/stone_throne_room_relief.aspx" rel="external" title="The British Museum's page about the stone bas-relief from behind the throne in of Assurnasirpal's Northwest Palace in Kalhu" hide-print="yes">Read more about this object on the British Museum's website. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Three monumental doorways in the south wall led from this outer court to the throne room. The walls between them were lined with low-relief sculptures of visiting dignitaries bringing gifts. The doorways themselves were flanked by monumental <esp:techterms term="colossal bull">winged bulls</esp:techterms>. Uniquely, the bulls wore small fish-skin cloaks on their heads, a reminder of the seven <esp:techterms term="sage">sages</esp:techterms> who had lived in ancient times before the <esp:techterms term="Flood">Flood</esp:techterms>, and brought knowledge to mankind. Their prominence here highlights the importance of scholarship and learning to Assurnasirpal's court.</p>

<p>The throne room itself was long and thin, running almost the whole width of the courtyard. Most people probably entered by the central doorway, where they saw an imposing double image of the king immediately opposite them, worshipping the god <esp:link page="ashur">Aššur</esp:link> while two winged <esp:techterms term="genie">genies</esp:techterms> fertilised the so-called <esp:techterms term="sacred tree">sacred tree</esp:techterms> (<b>Image 3</b>). They then had to turn to the left to see the king himself, seated on his throne on a dais in front of the narrow east wall. That wall too was decorated with a double image of the king and the Sacred Tree. When the audience was over, visitors would probably leave by the westernmost doorway to the outer courtyard, glimpsing yet another image of the king through the entrance to Room C to the west.</p>

<p>In between the focal royal images, the long walls of Assurnasirpal's throne room were lined with images of victorious sieges and battles, in two rows. The corners and doorways, meanwhile, were protected with full-height carvings of <esp:techterms term="demon">demons</esp:techterms> and genies to ward off evil spirits and attract the forces of good. Between the double registers of battle scenes, and across the middle of every full-size image of the king, sacred tree, and protective figure, was a cuneiform inscription. Although it was sometimes cut short to fit the space, this inscription is essentially always the same and is thus known now as the <esp:link page="sia-intro">Standard Inscription</esp:link> of Assurnasirpal.</p>

<p>The king himself, and his immediate entourage, probably entered and exited the throne room from one of the doorways closest to the throne dais. The eastern doorway from the outer courtyard had a deep alcove set into it, where the famous <esp:link page="sia-intro" bookmark="housewarming">Banquet Stela</esp:link> of Assurnasirpal was on show. On this large stone block was a long cuneiform inscription describing how Assurnasirpal rebuilt the city of Kalhu, including the palace and temples, and celebrated its completion with a gargantuan ten-day feast for nearly 70,000 people.</p>

<esp:h>Receiving honoured guests</esp:h>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/nms-a1956-362.jpg" 
description="Stone bas-relief from Room G in Assurnasirpal's Northwest Palace in Kalhu, now in the National Museums of Scotland, Edinburgh" position="float"><esp:link  url="http://www.nms.ac.uk/our_collections/highlights/assyrian_relief.aspx" rel="external" 
   title="National Museums Scotlands's page about the stone bas-relief from Room G in of Assurnasirpal's Northwest Palace in Kalhu" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img37"><b>Image 4</b></esp:bookmark>: Many of the low-relief sculptures from Assurnasirpal II's reception suites found their way to <esp:link page="museumsworldwide">museums all over the world</esp:link>, while others still remain in situ on the site of Nimrud  <esp:ref referent="englund2003" page="79-138"/>. This fine depiction of the king offering a <esp:techterms term="libation">libation</esp:techterms> in front of an attendant originally came from Room G in the Northwest Palace. It is now in the National Museum of Scotland, Edinburgh, (A1956-132) where it has recently been <esp:link url="http://www.nms.ac.uk/our_collections/highlights/assyrian_relief.aspx" rel="external" title="National Museums Scotlands's page about the stone bas-relief from Room G in of Assurnasirpal's North West Palace in Kalhu" hide-print="yes">conserved and redisplayed</esp:link>. Photo: © <esp:link url="http://www.nms.ac.uk/our_collections/highlights/assyrian_relief.aspx" rel="external" hide-print="yes">National Museums Scotland</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>A single doorway in the southern wall of the throne room led into an anteroom (F) to a central courtyard (Y), where the king took his intimates and special visitors to one of three suites for more private engagements.</p>

<p>Three parallel rooms to the west were almost certainly the palace banqueting suite (Rooms WG, WH and WK, with Rooms A, WJ, WI and WM). Like the conference rooms in an expensive hotel, they had no fixed furniture but could be reconfigured and re-equipped to suit the occasion. Most importantly they looked down on the Tigris, giving guests a magnificent view of the busy river and surrounding countryside, plus the benefit of cool air. Like the throne room, this West Suite was decorated with double-register images of Assyrian military conquest, suggesting that the activities held here were very similar in tone and style.</p>

<p>At the opposite end of the central courtyard, the East Suite was very different in function (Rooms G-O and R). The highly repetitive large images on the walls of Rooms G and H show the king with his weapons and an offering bowl, surrounded by <esp:techterms term="beneficent">beneficent</esp:techterms> genies (<b>Image 4</b>). The floors, unusually, are both paved and drained. Here, then, the king came to pour liquid offerings to the gods and to receive their blessing and purification. He must have had human attendants with him to help conduct the ceremonies appropriately, although the bas-reliefs do not hint at their presence. The L-shaped inner rooms, I and L, were even more highly secured from divine and human intruders. Double-layered images of protective <esp:techterms term="genie">genies</esp:techterms> and sacred trees lined the walls to the foot of each L, where niches and a drain allowed the king to wash and relieve himself in full privacy, perhaps with guards standing sentry at each entrance. However, by the 8th century BC, these rooms had been relegated to storage areas.</p>

<p>The South Suite (Rooms S, T and X) links the central courtyard with the dense cluster of rooms to the south, where the large royal family lived. Its layout echoes that of the rooms around the throne room (Rooms B, F and C) but its decoration is much more like the highly protected East Suite. However, the innermost Room X is undecorated except for the <esp:link page="sia-intro">Standard Inscription</esp:link>. Perhaps this room was hung with tapestries or carpets instead. This area must, then, have been the king's private residence suite, where he could relax a little with only his most intimate acquaintances, family members and staff to hand.</p>

<esp:h>Behind the scenes: living with the dead</esp:h>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/tomb3crown.jpg" 
description="Gold and lapis lazuli crown from Tomb III in the Northwest Palace, Nimrud" position="float"><esp:link  url="/nimrud/nimrud/images/ancientcity/tomb3crown-large.jpg" 
   title="Gold and lapis lazuli crown from Tomb III in the Northwest Palace, Nimrud (large)" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img38"><b>Image 5</b></esp:bookmark>: This gorgeous crown comes from Tomb III in the Northwest Palace, and is hung with bunches of grapes made from <esp:techterms term="lapis lazuli">lapis lazuli</esp:techterms>. Although it looks very delicate, it is in fact over 1kg in weight! It would be nice to think that the crown belonged to <esp:techterms term="queen">queen</esp:techterms> <esp:glossary term="Mullissu-mukannišat-Ninua (person)">Mullissu-mukannišat-Ninua</esp:glossary>, Assurnasirpal's wife. But in fact it was found on the body of a young woman whose head was much too small for it and we do not actually know for whom it was originally made <esp:ref referent="damerji2008" page="82"/>.<esp:link url="/nimrud/nimrud/images/ancientcity/tomb3crown-large.jpg" rel="external" title="Gold and lapis lazuli crown from Tomb III in the Northwest Palace, Nimrud (large)" hide-print="yes">View large image.</esp:link> Photo: Iraq Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p> The southern end of the palace contained the private living quarters of the royal family and their domestic staff. It was separated from the ceremonial northern half by Corridors P and Z, and presumably had at least one discreet exit to the outside world. Three underground chambers, accessed only from Room 74 via Room 75, may have served as the palace treasury. Water came from wells in Courtyards AB, AJ, NN and 80.</p> 

<p>Amongst the complex web of interconnecting courtyards and corridors, rooms and suites two configurations stand out. First is the series of long rooms with cupboards and adjacent dead-end bathrooms around a kitchen (Room ZZ) containing benches, a bread oven and cooking vessels. Second is the altogether larger suite to the south of Courtyard AJ (Rooms 42 and 59–61), which may have belonged to Assurnasirpal's <esp:techterms term="queen">queen</esp:techterms>. These rooms were decorated with wall paintings rather than stone bas-reliefs, with human, floral and geometrical designs. But the queen's rooms also had <esp:techterms term="ivory">ivory</esp:techterms> furniture with <esp:techterms term="gold">gold</esp:techterms> inlay.</p>

<p>This southern half of the palace did not only accommodate living occupants, however. Deep under the floors of Rooms MM, 49, 56 and 57 were four vaulted, brick-built tombs where prominent royal women were buried, along with their most precious belongings and jewels, over a period of about 150 years (<b>Image 5</b>). Inscriptions have identified some of the women as (in chronological order):</p>

<ul>
<li><esp:glossary term="Mullissu-mukannišat-Ninua (person)">Mullissu-mukannišat-Ninua</esp:glossary>, wife of Assurnasirpal and <esp:link page="shalmaneser3" bookmark="royal-women">mother of Shalmaneser III</esp:link> (Tomb III, under Room 57)</li>
<li><esp:glossary term="Yabaʾ (person)">Yabaʾ</esp:glossary>, wife of <esp:glossary term="Tiglath-pileser III (person)">Tiglath-pileser III</esp:glossary> (Tomb II, under Room 49)</li>
<li><esp:glossary term="Hamaya (person)">Hamaya</esp:glossary>, wife of Shalmaneser IV (Tomb III)</li>
<li><esp:glossary term="Banitu (person)">Banitu</esp:glossary>, wife of <esp:glossary term="Shalmaneser V (person)">Shalmaneser V</esp:glossary> (Tomb II)</li>
<li><esp:glossary term="Ataliya (person)">Ataliya</esp:glossary>, wife of <esp:glossary term="Sargon II (person)">Sargon II</esp:glossary> (Tomb II)</li>
</ul>

<esp:h>After Assurnasirpal</esp:h>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/bm-me-127412.jpg" 
description="Inlaid ivory panel found in the well in Room NN of the Northwest Palace, Nimrud" position="float"><esp:link  url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/highlights/highlight_objects/me/i/panel_of_lioness_devouring_boy.aspx" rel="external" 
   title="The British Museum's webpage on the inlaid ivory panel found in the well in Room NN of the Northwest Palace, Nimrud" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img39"><b>Image 6</b></esp:bookmark>: We do know when or why so many beautiful objects were thrown down the wells of Assurnasirpal's palace, but it may have happened during the destruction of the palace in 612 BC. Perhaps looters tore the gold leaf off particularly fine furnishings and hurled the remnants away. This exquisite ivory panel, perhaps part of a throne, was made in <esp:glossary term="Phoenicia (place)">Phoenicia</esp:glossary> in the 9th or 8th century BC and presumably came to Kalhu as tribute or booty. <esp:glossary term="Mallowan, Max (person)">Max Mallowan</esp:glossary>'s team found it in the well of Room NN, along with many other precious things <esp:ref referent="mallowan1966" page="I, 122-144"/>. The tiny <esp:link page="maadog">bronze animal figurine</esp:link> now in Cambridge's Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology comes from the same <esp:techterms term="findspot">findspot</esp:techterms>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/highlights/highlight_objects/me/i/panel_of_lioness_devouring_boy.aspx" rel="external" 
   title="The British Museum's webpage on the inlaid ivory panel found in the well in Room NN of the Northwest Palace, Nimrud" hide-print="yes">Read more about this object (BM ME 127412) on the British Museum's website.</esp:link> © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Only king Assurnasirpal's son and immedidate successor, <esp:link page="shalmaneser3">Shalmaneser III</esp:link>, continued to use the palace as it was originally intended. His own son <esp:glossary term="Adad-nerari III (person)">Adad-nerari III</esp:glossary> (r. 810-783 BC) built a new palace immediately to the south, while in the 8th century Tiglath-pileser III commissioned yet another residence in the centre of the citadel. When Sargon II's new city <esp:glossary term="Dur-Šarruken (place)">Dur-Šarruken</esp:glossary> was completed in 710 BC, he moved out completely. Notably, the latest official correspondence and queens' burials also date to the end of the 8th century BC.</p>

<p>In the 670s BC king <esp:glossary term="Esarhaddon (person)">Esarhaddon</esp:glossary> removed sculptures from the West Suite to re-use in his new residence elsewhere on the citadel. But even if the royal family no longer lived in the Northwest Palace, it continued to be used for offices and storerooms until the sack of Kalhu in 612 BC. At that point the invaders ripped through the building, ransacking its treasuries and throwing unwanted fragments of carved ivory furniture down the palace's many wells (<b>Image 6</b>). The building's last remaining guards also met that fate, if the manacled bodies discovered in the well of Courtyard 80 well are anything to go by.</p>

<p>Squatters occupied the ruins for a while, until the building fell into complete disrepair. Then, as described elsewhere, the Northwest Palace remained untouched and forgotten for around two and a half thousand years until rediscovered by <esp:glossary term="Layard, Austen Henry (person)">Austen Henry Layard</esp:glossary> in the 1840s. Subsequent excavations by teams of British, Polish, Italian and Iraqi archaeologists, as well as by more opportunist diggers, have scattered the palace's contents to the four quarters of the world. The process of reuniting them, <esp:link page="resources" bookmark="webresources">online</esp:link> if not in real life, will be a project for many further decades to come.</p>

<esp:reading referent="oatesoates2001" page="36-70, 78-104"/>
<esp:reading referent="roaf2008"/>
<esp:reading referent="russell1999" page="9-63"/>
<esp:reading referent="russell2008"/>

<p>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/>.<br/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/></p>
<esp:author first-names="Eleanor" last-name="Robson"/>

</body></html>
</esp:page>
