<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

	<esp:name>Discovering Ancient Assyria</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Discovering Ancient Assyria at the Fitzwilliam Museum</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>
	
<p class="firstpara">On Saturday 26 October 2013 the Nimrud project worked with the <esp:link url="http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/" hide-print="yes">Fitzwilliam Museum</esp:link> to hold an afternoon of Assyrian-themed activities in the Fitzwilliam's <esp:link url="http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/dept/ant/ane/" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Ancient Near East</esp:link> galleries. The event formed part of the <esp:link url="http://www.cam.ac.uk/festival-of-ideas" hide-print="yes">Cambridge Festival of Ideas</esp:link> 2013.</p>

<p>&#187; <esp:link url="/nimrud/downloads/discover-assyria-leaflet.pdf" title="Download the Discover Ancient Assyria event 'What's On' leaflet'" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Discovering Ancient Assyria event 'What's On' leaflet</esp:link> PDF (647 KB)</p>
 
<esp:h>Genies and kings get a makeover</esp:h>

<esp:image file="events/coloured-in-assyrian-king.png" description="Drawing of an Assyrian king, coloured-in with bright colours" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img6">The Fitzwilliam Museum’s Assyrian <esp:techterms term="relief">reliefs</esp:techterms> got a colourful makeover at the "Discovering Ancient Assyria" event on 26 October 2013.</esp:bookmark></esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Museum visitors learned about the Fitz’s Assyrian <esp:link page="stonegenies">relief panels of kings and genies</esp:link> in a series of mini-talks given by the project team.</p>

<p>Younger visitors successfully hunted down<esp:techterms term="genie"> genies</esp:techterms>, kings and tiny <esp:link page="langscripts">cuneiform tablets</esp:link> in our <esp:link bookmark="assyrianquiz">Assyrian-themed quiz</esp:link>, and had a go at designing their own Assyrian-inspired mixed up animals.</p>

<p>The Fitz’s Assyrian <esp:techterms term="genie">genies</esp:techterms> and kings also got colourful makeovers by younger visitors. Over 100 colour-in genies were completed in the galleries or taken home to finish off.</p>

<esp:image file="events/birdheaded-genie-small.png" description="Line drawing of bird headed genie, ready for colouring in" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img7">Colour in your own <esp:link page="eventsresources" bookmark="fitzcolouringenies">Fitzwilliam Museum genie</esp:link>.</esp:bookmark></esp:caption></esp:image>

<esp:h>Trainee cuneiform scribes</esp:h>

<p>During the afternoon 71 visitors of all ages became trainee Assyrian <esp:techterms term="scribe">scribes</esp:techterms>, learning how to make a clay tablet and write their name using cuneiform script. Our enthusiastic <esp:techterms term="Assyriology">Assyriology</esp:techterms> students Sarah and Christoph were on hand to explain the technique. Finished cuneiform tablets were carefully wrapped and taken home to air-dry – just like the Assyrians did 3000 years ago.</p>

<p>Trainee scribes also had chance to compare their efforts with those of genuine Assyrian scribes. Visitors viewed some of the Fitz's cuneiform tablets up close, in an object discovery session arranged by the Department of Antiquities. The Nimrud project team were also on hand to answer questions.</p>

<esp:h>Visitors' futures divined</esp:h>

<esp:image file="events/fitz-divination.jpg" description="Two museum visitors sit at a table watching a Babylonian diviner read their future from a tray of oil and water" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img8">A consultation with our resident diviner: museum visitors have their future read from oil and water.</esp:bookmark> Photo by Eleanor Robson.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>An expert <esp:techterms term="diviner">diviner</esp:techterms> (on special leave from 1800 BC Babylon) was ready and waiting in the Education Studio to interpret visitors’ destiny through oil and water. Our diviner, Alex, recreated the process of oil divination based on a corpus of Old Babylonian lecanomancy (oil omen) texts.</p>

<p>Around 40 museum visitors enjoyed finding out what the mighty gods of Ancient Assyria had in store for them. Thankfully, our diviner also had good advice for keeping the gods happy!</p>

<p>Many thanks to staff at the Fitzwilliam Museum, and to our volunteers, for making the afternoon such a success.</p>

<esp:h><esp:bookmark id="assyrianquiz">Try the Fitz quiz, or colour your own genie!</esp:bookmark></esp:h>

<esp:image file="events/assyria-quiz-thumb.jpg" description="Fitzwilliam Museum Assyria quiz" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img9">Download the Assyrian kings and genies quiz and try it for yourself in the Fitzwilliam Museum.</esp:bookmark> <esp:link url="/nimrud/downloads/fitz-assyria-quiz-A4.pdf" title="Download Genies and Kings Quiz" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Download the quiz (PDF, 3 MB)</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Want to hunt down the Fitz's Assyrian genies and kings for yourself? Then download our Genies and Kings from Ancient Assyria quiz, designed for use in the Fitzwilliam Museum's <esp:link url="http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/dept/ant/ane/" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Gallery 23 and Main Entrance staircase</esp:link>.</p>

<p>&#187; <esp:link url="/nimrud/downloads/fitz-assyria-quiz-A4.pdf" title="Download Genies and Kings Quiz" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Genies and Kings from Ancient Assyria quiz A4</esp:link> (PDF 5.6MB) &#150; version sized for A4 paper.</p>

<p>&#187; <esp:link url="/nimrud/downloads/fitz-assyria-quiz-A3.pdf" title="Download Genies and Kings Quiz" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Genies and Kings from Ancient Assyria quiz A3</esp:link> (PDF 5.5MB) &#150; version sized for A3 paper.</p>

<p>Or why not download and colour-in your very own <esp:link page="eventsresources" bookmark="fitzcolouringenies">Fitzwilliam Museum genie</esp:link>.</p>

<p>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/>.<br/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/></p>
</body></html>

</esp:page>
