<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
	<esp:name>Egyptian</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Egyptian in hieroglyphic script</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>

<p class="firstpara">The evidence for Egyptian writing in Assyria is limited and, for the most part, indirect. While Egyptians certainly lived in the Assyrian heartland, no materials produced by them in their native language have survived. However, <esp:techterms term="seal, sealing">seal</esp:techterms> <esp:techterms term="impression">impressions</esp:techterms> on more durable media attest to the continuing exchanges between Assyria and <esp:glossary term="Egypt (place)">Egypt</esp:glossary>.</p>

<esp:h>“Send me much gold!”</esp:h> 

<esp:image file="langscripts/BM-118898.jpg" description="Clay prism of king Tiglath-pileser I listing the achievements of his reign" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img144"><b>Image 1</b></esp:bookmark>: The Broken <esp:techterms term="obelisk">Obelisk</esp:techterms> of <esp:glossary term="Aššur-bel-kala (person)">Aššur-bel-kala</esp:glossary> from the Central Palace at <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary>, showing the Assyrian king standing in front of the symbols of two gods and holding two prisoners on a rope. The inscription records that "The king of Egypt sent a large female monkey, a crocodile (and) a 'river-man', beasts of the Great Sea" <esp:ref referent="grayson1991" page="103-104, A.0.89.7:iv 29-30"/>. The winged sun disc symbol shown hovering before the king may reflect the influence of Egyptian iconography. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=277955&amp;partId=1&amp;people=93722&amp;peoA=93722-4-7&amp;page=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 118898</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=269322&amp;objectId=277955&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>The earliest documented contacts between Assyria and Egypt go back to the 14th century BC, when Assyria was asserting itself as a brazen newcomer to the so-called Great Powers' Club, a group of powerful states which dominated the Ancient Near East of the late Bronze Age. Surviving correspondence from Tell el-Amarna in Egypt records diplomatic overtures made by the Assyrian king <esp:glossary term="Aššur-uballiṭ I (person)">Aššur-uballiṭ I</esp:glossary>. A passage from the letter reveals something of the contemporary attitudes to Egypt as sort of an ancient Eldorado of unlimited wealth. In the words of Aššur-uballiṭ:</p>

<blockquote><p>Gold in your country is dirt; one simply gathers it up. Why are you so sparing of it? I am engaged in building a new palace. Send me as much gold as is needed for its adornment. <esp:ref referent="moran1992" page="38-39, EA 16:13-18"/></p></blockquote>

<p>The exchange of precious articles was a vital means of cementing friendly diplomatic relations between kings, and such gift exchanges were not limited to precious metals. The perceived prestige of exotic animals, for instance, was such that they were included in monumental inscriptions of Assyrian kings. The <esp:link page="obelisk">Black Obelisk</esp:link> of the Assyrian king <esp:link page="shalmaneser3">Shalmaneser III</esp:link> commemorates such a gift (see also <b>Image 1</b>):</p>

<blockquote><p>I received <esp:techterms term="tribute">tribute</esp:techterms> from Egypt: two-humped camels, a <esp:techterms term="water buffalo">water buffalo</esp:techterms> (lit. a "river ox"), a rhinoceros, and antelope, female elephants, female monkeys (and) apes <esp:ref referent="grayson1996" page="149-150, A.0.102.89"/>.</p></blockquote>

<esp:h>From the Nile to the Tigris: Egyptians in Assyria</esp:h>

<esp:image file="langscripts/BM-84884.jpg" description="Fragment of a clay sealing from Nineveh impressed with the seal of the Kushite king Shabako, a contemporary of the Assyrian king Sargon II" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img145"><b>Image 2</b></esp:bookmark>: Drawing of a fragmentary clay <esp:techterms term="seal, sealing">sealing</esp:techterms> from Nineveh, impressed with the seal of the <esp:glossary term="Kush (place)">Kushite</esp:glossary> king  <esp:glossary term="Shabako (person)">Shabako</esp:glossary>, a contemporary of the Assyrian king <esp:glossary term="Sargon II (person)">Sargon II</esp:glossary>. The sealing appears to have been part of a <esp:techterms term="jar-stopper">jar-stopper</esp:techterms>. It depicts Shabako in the standard 'smiting' pose of an Egyptian pharaoh, while the hieroglyphic caption refers to "The good god Shabako, lord of action". <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=1424038&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 84884</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=894630&amp;objectId=1424038&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Egyptians were present at the Assyrian court from the 8th century BC. The <esp:techterms term="Nimrud Wine Lists">Nimrud Wine Lists</esp:techterms>, which record the distributions of wine rations, refer to Egyptian <esp:techterms term="scribe">scribes</esp:techterms> at the Assyrian court around 732 BC <esp:ref referent="kinnierwilson1972" page="62-63"/>. However, most of the evidence for the presence of Egyptians in Assyria comes from the 7th century BC. In particular, Esarhaddon's successful campaign against Egypt in 671 BC resulted in an influx of Egyptians from many different walks of life. They included learned experts in disciplines such as magic and the interpretation of dreams (Assyrian <i>harṭibu</i>) who formed part of the retinue of the Assyrian king. These men would have consulted materials written in their native Egyptian (most likely using the formal hieroglyphic script), but no such works have been found.</p>

<p><esp:link page="legaldocuments">Legal documents</esp:link> also attest to the presence of Egyptians in Assyria long before Esarhaddon's conquest. A clay <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablet</esp:techterms> from Nineveh dated to 692 BC documents the purchase of a house in the city by one <esp:glossary term="Ṣil-Aššur (person)">Ṣilli-Aššur</esp:glossary>. Despite his perfectly good Assyrian name, he is described as an "Egyptian scribe". The transaction was witnessed by several individuals who bear Egyptian names, including "<esp:glossary term="Šusanqu (person)">Šusanqu</esp:glossary>, the king's in-law" (<i>hatan šarri</i>, a term used to designate a relation by marriage) (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa06/P335268/html" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAA 6: 142</esp:link>). Šusanqu was an Assyrian rendering of the Egyptian Shoshenq, a name which was used by the ruling houses in the <esp:glossary term="Delta (place)">Egyptian Delta</esp:glossary>. Just how this Shoshenq came to Assyria is not clear. Possibly he was one of the Egyptian princes captured by <esp:glossary term="Sennacherib (person)">Sennacherib</esp:glossary> at the battle of <esp:glossary term="Eltekeh (place)">
Eltekeh</esp:glossary> in 701 BC, and subsequently linked to the Assyrian royal family through <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/aebp/essentials/diplomats/royalmarriage" hide-print="yes" rel="external">diplomatic marriage</esp:link>.</p>

<esp:image file="langscripts/BM-134322.jpg" description="Ivory plaque from Fort Shalmaneser in Kalhu (modern Nimrud)" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img146"><b>Image 3</b></esp:bookmark>: <esp:techterms term="ivory">Ivory</esp:techterms> <esp:techterms term="plaque">plaque</esp:techterms> from <esp:link page="fortshalmaneser">Fort Shalmaneser</esp:link> in Kalhu; one of the <esp:techterms term="Nimrud ivories">'Nimrud ivories'</esp:techterms>. Dating from the 9th-8th century BC, the plaque was manufactured in <esp:glossary term="Phoenicia (place)">Phoenicia</esp:glossary> in an Egyptianising style. It depicts a sphinx wearing the traditional double crown of Upper and Lower Egypt; on its chest is the uraeus, the symbol of the protective cobra goddess.  <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=369007&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 134322</esp:link>. <esp:link url="https://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/highlights/highlight_image.aspx?image=ps098822.jpg&amp;retpage=18819" hide-print="yes" rel="external">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>It is clear that an Egyptian community existed in central Assyria, and such a community would almost certainly have included its own scribes to draw up documents and correspondence in the Egyptian language. However, as these would have been written on <esp:techterms term="papyrus">papyrus</esp:techterms> which does not survive well in the Mesopotamian climate, no direct evidence of the Egyptian scribes' activity survives.</p>

<p>Excavations in the royal city of Nineveh in the 19th century uncovered clay sealings carved with hieroglyphic inscriptions. The sealings are incomplete but at least some can be identified as belonging to the <esp:glossary term="Kush (place)">Kushite</esp:glossary> king Shabako, a contemporary of the Assyrian king <esp:glossary term="Sargon II (person)">Sargon II</esp:glossary> (<b>Image 2</b>). Unfortunately we can only speculate about what items the seals enclosed or the exact nature of the two kings' relationship, as the seals alone have survived the ravages of time.</p>

<esp:h>Fashionably Egyptian: the Nimrud Ivories</esp:h>

<p>Egyptian art was inspiring interior decorators long before the modern era. Decorative objects which owed a debt to Egyptian art were popular throughout the ancient Near East, including Assyria. Among the most celebrated objects excavated in Kalhu are the Nimrud Ivories. These elaborately carved ivory plaques probably once served as decorations for luxury furniture. Many of the ivories are made in an instantly recognisable "Egyptianising" style. They depict typically Egyptian imagery such as papyrus and <esp:techterms term="lotus">lotus</esp:techterms> plants, sphinxes, divine figures and hieroglyphs enclosed in <esp:techterms term="cartouche">cartouches</esp:techterms> (<b>Image 3</b>).</p>

<esp:image file="langscripts/ND-7624.jpg" description="Broken ivory scarab of the Egyptian pharaoh Taharqa, from Fort Shalmaneser in Kalhu (modern Nimrud)" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/langscripts/ND-7624_large.jpg" title="Large image of a broken ivory scarab of the Egyptian pharaoh Taharqa, from Fort Shalmaneser in Kalhu (modern Nimrud)." hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img147"><b>Image 4</b></esp:bookmark>: Broken ivory <esp:techterms term="scarab">scarab</esp:techterms> of the Egyptian pharaoh <esp:glossary term="Taharqa (person)">Taharqa</esp:glossary>, from <esp:link page="fortshalmaneser">Fort Shalmaneser</esp:link> in Kalhu. The scarab is inscribed with Taharqa's royal titles. ND 7624 <esp:ref referent="hermann1992" page="78, no. 178; plate 38"/>. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/langscripts/ND-7624_large.jpg" title="Large image of a broken ivory scarab of the Egyptian pharaoh Taharqa, from Fort Shalmaneser in Kalhu (modern Nimrud)" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link>. Photo: <esp:link page="copyright" bookmark="BISIimages">BSAI/BISI</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Despite their appearance, the ivories were not actually manufactured in Egypt, or even by Egyptian artists. Rather, they were the products of the <esp:glossary term="Phoenicia (place)">Phoenicians</esp:glossary>, famous navigators who engaged in sea-based trade from their harbour cities along the eastern Mediterranean coast. The Phoenicians had a well deserved reputation as master craftsmen and purveyors of luxury goods, and enjoyed close trade links with Assyria. From the workshops of the Phoenician craftsmen many Egyptian-style objects made their way into the palaces of Assyria.</p>

<p>Genuine Egyptian ivories from Assyria, on the other hand, are far less common: one example is a <esp:techterms term="scarab">scarab</esp:techterms> inscribed with the cartouche of Taharqa, a member of the Kushite dynasty which ruled Egypt from the mid-8th century BC (<b>Image 4</b>). Esarhaddon's defeat of Taharqa and his conquest of Egypt in 671 BC may explain the scarab's presence in Assyria.</p>

<esp:reading referent="herrmannlaidlaw2013"/>
<esp:reading referent="oatesoates2001" page="(see under 'Egypt' and 'Egyptianising' in the index)"/>
<esp:reading referent="radner2009"/>
<esp:reading referent="radner2012"/>

<p>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/><br/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/></p>

<esp:author first-names="Silvie" last-name="Zamazalová"/>
</body></html>
</esp:page>
