<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
	<esp:name>Legal documents</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Legal documents</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>

<p class="firstpara">Among the thousands of <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablets</esp:techterms> excavated from the cities of ancient Assyria are numerous documents which record legal transactions. Since no collections of laws are known from the <esp:techterms term="Neo-Assyrian">Neo-Assyrian</esp:techterms> period, these texts give us a valuable insight into aspects of the Assyrian legal system. They also provide glimpses into Assyrian lives, albeit only those of a fairly narrow section of society.</p>

<esp:h>Charioteers, royal bodyguards... and a sheep rustler</esp:h>

<!-- New image below: Image 8 from Cuneiform on Clay (img 126), slave sale -->

<esp:image file="langscripts/nd_2325.jpg" description="Clay tablet with inscribed cuneiform text, with a circular seal stamped three times into the surface" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img126"><b>Image 1</b>: Cuneiform tablet from Nimrud, recording the sale of a slave woman named Arbela-lamur ("May I see <esp:glossary term="Arbela (place)">Arbela</esp:glossary>!").</esp:bookmark> An officer in the <esp:techterms term="crown prince">crown prince</esp:techterms>’s retinue has certified the sale by impressing his stamp seal on to the tablet. The tablet dates from the reign of king <esp:glossary term="Assurbanipal (person)">Assurbanipal</esp:glossary> <esp:ref referent="parker1954" page="42"/>, <esp:ref referent="parker1955" page="96, plate XXIV, no. 1"/>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=1549824&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">ND 2325</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image> 

<p>Most of the documents from royal archives belonged to high-ranking court officials and holders of military posts, such as the royal charioteers and commanders of the royal bodyguard who feature prominently in the <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary> archives. This may at first glance appear rather unusual until we consider the unique position of charioteers and bodyguards. Their unfettered access to the king put them in a position of great power, so it was vital to secure their loyalty. Lavish gifts were one way to do this, and their numerous transactions were a natural reflection of their wealth. At the same time, requiring them to share their business dealings with the palace allowed king to make sure that these individuals did not get so rich and powerful as to become a threat to him.</p>

<p>The vast majority of legal texts record private transactions. Other types of document, such as court decisions, are also represented, but they are much less common. Collections of laws - or even references to them - are noticeably absent. Most of the legal documents from Assyria deal with purchases of property, particularly of land and people, and with loans or other debt obligations. Purchases of people did not necessarily concern only slaves. Women could be sold into marriage (e.g. <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa14/P335252/html" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAA 14: 161</esp:link>, which records a woman being sold by her father and brother; <b>Image 1</b>), and children into adoption (e.g. <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa14/P224957/html" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAA 14: 442</esp:link>).</p>

<!--MOVE or DEL? <esp:image file="genres/BM-318.jpg" description="Agreement for a loan of silver" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img157"><b>Image 2</b></esp:bookmark>: Agreement for a loan of silver (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa14/P334990/html" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAA 14: 120</esp:link>). The tablet shows the "vertical" (wider than tall) format which was typical for loan documents. <esp:link url="https://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=314553&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">British Museum, K.318</esp:link>. <esp:link url="https://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=686230&amp;objectId=314553&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>-->

<esp:image file="langscripts/nd_211.jpg" description="Clay tablet with inscribed cuneiform text, which has been 'sealed' using the fingernails of 11 men. The fingernail impressions run in a horizontal row across the top of the tablet" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=1348689&amp;objectId=1536891&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img127"><b>Image 2</b>: A row of fingernail impression ‘signatures’ runs in a horizontal row across the top of this tablet from Nimrud, <esp:techterms term="seal, sealing">sealing</esp:techterms> the document as substitutes for personal seals.</esp:bookmark> It records <esp:glossary term="Bel-tarṣi-ilumma (person)">Bel-tarṣi-ilumma</esp:glossary> paying off a huge debt ("2 talents, 20 minas of bronze") for someone named Sabiri. From Room 6 of the <esp:link page="governorspalace">Governor's Palace</esp:link>, 793 BC <esp:ref referent="postgate1973" page="121"/>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=1536891&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">ND 211</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=1348689&amp;objectId=1536891&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Loans or debt notes usually involved <esp:techterms term="silver">silver</esp:techterms> and corn, but wine, birds, cattle, camels and people are also recorded. Less common types of transactions include receipts and records of court proceedings, which address a variety of matters ranging from adoption (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa14/P224968/html" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAA 14: 450</esp:link>) and property disputes to murder and theft (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa06/P335115/html" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAA 6: 264</esp:link>, a judgement against one Hani who had raided sheep belonging to the <esp:techterms term="crown prince">crown prince</esp:techterms> and killed a shepherd in the process; <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa14/P335111/html" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAA 14: 104</esp:link>).</p>

<!-- MOVE or DEL? <esp:image file="genres/BM-318a.jpg" description="Clay envelope for K.318" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img158"><b>Image 3</b></esp:bookmark>: Clay envelope for K.318 (<b>Image 2</b>). It records a loan of silver, the borrower's stamp seal <esp:techterms term="impression">impressions</esp:techterms> and the names of witnesses. A caption in <esp:link page="alphabetic">Aramaic</esp:link> on the left-hand edge (upper left photo) summarises the contents ("Concerning Mannu-ki-Arbail, the household administrator, silver") (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa14/P334991/html" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAA 14: 119</esp:link>). <esp:link url="https://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=314552&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">British Museum, K.318.a</esp:link>. <esp:link url="https://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=686234&amp;objectId=314552&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>-->

<esp:image file="langscripts/nd_3445.jpg" description="Photograph of inscribed clay tablet and the inscribed clay envelope that surrounded it" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img128"><b>Image 3</b>: Clay tablet (bottom) and its envelope (top).</esp:bookmark> This loan document from 636<esp:techterms term="eponym">*</esp:techterms> BC was excavated from Room 19 of Town Wall house 57, Nimrud <esp:ref referent="wiseman1953" page="143"/>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=1605930&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">ND 3445</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<esp:h>Power in the royal harem</esp:h>

<p>The legal corpus from Nineveh includes a number of tablets recording transactions by women connected to the <esp:techterms term="harem">harem</esp:techterms> (the women's quarters of the palace). From the tablets it is clear that these women enjoyed considerable wealth and influence. It seems that palace women, including concubines, were as free to engage in business outside the court and the city as other members of the palace elite. Just like male courtiers, they bought and sold property, and made loans of money and livestock (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa06/P335010/html" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAA 6: 81</esp:link>, <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa06/P335071/html" hide-print="yes" rel="external">84</esp:link>, <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa06/P335018/html" hide-print="yes" rel="external">97</esp:link>).</p>

<p>This freedom was not limited to the palace of women of Nineveh: a tablet from <esp:glossary term="Assur (place)">Assur</esp:glossary> shows that if a man failed to repay a debt owed to a woman, the woman was entitled to keep him as a debt slave. There is no evidence that any transactions were taboo for women, nor that there was a social stigma attached to men transacting with women. Married women did not automatically have to defer to their husbands in property matters: a tablet from Nineveh lists Amat-Su'la, "wife of Bel-duri, shield-bearing 'third man'" as part-owner of a house (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa06/P335268/html" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAA 6: 142</esp:link>).</p>

<esp:h>The medium and the message</esp:h>

<esp:image file="genres/BM-1881_0204_148.jpg" description="A triangular clay docket from Nineveh" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img159"><b>Image 4</b></esp:bookmark>: A triangular clay <esp:techterms term="docket">docket</esp:techterms> from the royal citadel in <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary>, c. 670 BC. It records the pledge of a child as security for a loan of silver. The docket probably originally secured a roll of leather inscribed with the terms of the pledge in <esp:link page="alphabetic">Aramaic</esp:link>. This particular docket is also inscribed in Aramaic, but dockets commonly contained an <esp:techterms term="Akkadian">Akkadian</esp:techterms> language inscription in <esp:techterms term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> script. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=294178&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">BM 1881,0204.148</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=109620&amp;objectId=294178&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Legal transactions were recorded either on clay tablets (Akkadian <i>ṭuppu</i>, <i>dannutu</i> or <i>egirtu</i>) or on rolls of leather (sometimes anachronistically translated as <esp:techterms term="parchment">parchment</esp:techterms>). Only the tablets, however, have survived the passage of millennia. Wooden wax-covered <esp:link page="materials-others" bookmark="h_writingboards">writing boards</esp:link> (<i>le'ȗ</i>) do not seem to have been used for this purpose, presumably because they were too easy to rewrite. The type of transaction directly determined the physical appearance of the document used to record it.</p>

<p>Purchase documents were written on a single <esp:techterms term="portrait format">portrait format</esp:techterms> (taller than wide) tablet (<b>Image 1</b>). Loans, on the other hand, were recorded on tablets which were <esp:techterms term="landscape format">landscape format</esp:techterms> (wider than tall) (<b>Image 2</b>). In the 7th century BC loan documents also came to be enclosed in clay envelopes (<b>Image 3</b>). Once the tablet was put inside, the envelope was <esp:techterms term="seal, sealing">sealed</esp:techterms> and inscribed with a duplicate of the text on the tablet. The addition of an envelope protected the tablet from damage, both accidental or deliberate. It also provided an extra layer of security for the parties: in the event of a dispute, they could break open the envelope and so settle any argument about the terms.</p>

<p><esp:bookmark id="loan dockets" title="loans in the form of triangular dockets">Documents recording debts of corn (<esp:techterms term="corn docket">corn dockets</esp:techterms>)</esp:bookmark> took a very different form. They consisted of a triangular piece of clay which was moulded around a piece of string. The <esp:techterms term="docket">docket</esp:techterms> and string were probably used to secure a roll of leather, though no such scrolls have survived. The terms of the debt were inscribed on the clay docket, which was then sealed by the debtor. The docket acted as a sort of substitute envelope: only by breaking the docket could the parchment be unrolled. The clay docket was usually inscribed with cuneiform script in the <esp:techterms term="Akkadian">Akkadian</esp:techterms> language but <esp:link page="alphabetic">Aramaic</esp:link> exemplars are also known, as are dockets documenting transactions other than corn debts (<b>Image 4</b>). The parchment, on the other hand, must always have been written in Aramaic. The fact that traditional cuneiform and the relatively new alphabetic script were used side by side illustrates the multilingual nature of the late Neo-Assyrian empire.</p>

<p>The practice for other types of documents was less standardised, no doubt because they were much less common. Receipts were usually written on <esp:techterms term="landscape format">"horizontal"</esp:techterms> tablets which were impressed with seals. Court proceedings tended to follow the same format, but sealings seem to have been optional.</p>

<esp:h>Witnesses, seals and fingernails</esp:h>

<!-- DELETE IMAGE <esp:image file="genres/K-326.jpg" description="Obverse of a clay tablet showing five sets of fingernail impressions as substitutes for personal seals" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img160"><b>Image 5</b></esp:bookmark>: <esp:techterms term="obverse, reverse">Obverse</esp:techterms> of a clay tablet showing five sets of fingernail impressions as substitutes for personal seals (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa06/P335355/html" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAA 6: 17</esp:link>). <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=314543&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">K.326</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=686277&amp;objectId=314543&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">View full image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>-->

<p>The Assyrians used two methods to authenticate legal tablets. The first involved the use of a seal to confirm the identity of the seller (in the case of property purchases) or the borrower (in the case of loans). The seller or debtor would impress his (or her) <esp:techterms term="seal, sealing">seal</esp:techterms> on to the tablet in front of witnesses. Those who did not own a seal could impress a fingernail (<i>ṣupru</i>) instead (<b>Image 5</b>). This was a relatively common practice in the 8th and early 7th century, and was even reflected in the wording of the tablet. A standard formula recorded that "Instead of their seals they impressed their fingernails". As stamp seals became more widely used in the 7th century BC, fingernail <esp:techterms term="impression">impressions</esp:techterms> on legal documents gradually disappeared.</p>

<p>The sealing of the tablet (or the marking of a fingernail) was carried out before witnesses (<i>šībūti</i>) whose names were listed after the operative part of the document, sometimes with a brief description of who they were. The <esp:techterms term="scribe">scribe</esp:techterms> responsible for drawing up the tablet was usually named as the final witness, and labelled as such (e.g. "Witness Šaulanu, scribe, keeper of the tablet" (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa06/P335355/html" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAA 6: 17</esp:link>)). The tablet was then dated using the <esp:techterms term="eponym">eponym</esp:techterms> dating system. There are isolated instances of tablets which invoke non-human witnesses, such as a document in which the king's statue and <esp:glossary term="Šamaš (deity)">Šamaš</esp:glossary>, the god of justice, lead the list of witnesses. However, these are very rare.</p>

<p>The function of witnesses was two-fold. They guaranteed that the document had been properly sealed, but their presence also ensured that the transaction was carried out in accordance with the parties' wishes. If there was a disagreement, the testimony of witnesses was given even more weight than the tablet itself. The fact that they might be called on to testify meant that witnesses had to be local. This explains why witnesses to transfers of land were often the property's neighbours. In many cases, the parties to the transaction also brought along their own witnesses.</p>

<esp:h>Where were they found?</esp:h>

<p>The Neo-Assyrian legal corpus consists of some 2,000 documents uncovered at about 30 sites within the empire, 9 of them in the <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/aebp/essentials/countries/centralassyria" hide-print="yes" rel="external">Assyrian heartland</esp:link>. The rest come from territories to the west, in what is now Syria, Turkey and Israel. The sites in Assyria proper include the major urban centres of <esp:glossary term="Assur (place)">Assur</esp:glossary>, Kalhu, <esp:glossary term="Dur-Šarruken (place)">Dur-Šarruken</esp:glossary> and <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary>, all of which at some point served as royal capitals.</p>

<p>The legal corpus includes documents from both private and royal archives. Surviving private archives come mainly from residential buildings in the city of Assur, but some have also been uncovered in Assyria's <esp:techterms term="province">provinces</esp:techterms>. However, the largest collection of legal texts comes from the palaces and administrative buildings of royal capitals. These include the <esp:link page="governorspalace">governor's residence</esp:link> and <esp:link page="fortshalmaneser">Fort Shalmaneser</esp:link> in Kalhu, and particularly the palace mound at <esp:glossary term="Kuyunjik (place)">Kuyunjik</esp:glossary> in Nineveh: this was the site of the royal palaces and administrative buildings in which most of the legal documents appear to have been found. Unfortunately we know little of their exact provenance, and so it is virtually impossible to reconstruct the original state of the archives. The Nineveh corpus covers a period from the reign of <esp:glossary term="Tiglath-pileser III (person)">Tiglath-pileser III</esp:glossary> in the mid-eigth century to the destruction of the city in 612 BC.</p>

<esp:reading referent="postgate1976"/>
<esp:reading referent="kwasmanparpola1991"/>
<esp:reading referent="mattila2002"/>
<esp:reading referent="radner2003"/>

<p>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/>.<br/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/></p>

<esp:author first-names="Silvie" last-name="Zamazalová"/>

</body></html>
</esp:page>
