<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

	<esp:name>Scholarly works</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Scholarly works</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>
	
<p class="firstpara">The written word formed the basis of all scholarly advice to the Assyrian king. Sometimes <esp:link page="professions">royal scholars</esp:link> quoted extracts from particular compositions in the letters and reports but more often learned writings formed the deep background to their thinking. Over 250 clay <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablets</esp:techterms> containing scholarly works have been found at Nimrud since the 1950s. Here we explore what they consisted of, and how they were stored and circulated. However, we should also bear in mind that much was also written on <esp:link page="materials-others" bookmark="h_writingboards">writing-boards</esp:link>, which have mostly been lost forever.</p> 


<esp:h>Ancient advice literature</esp:h>
<p>In <esp:techterms term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> culture, scholarly learning encompassed a vast range of disciplines and genres from mythology to mathematics, medicine to mourning <esp:techterms term="rite, ritual">rituals</esp:techterms>. However, no one individual, family or practice community engaged with the whole range of knowledge in circulation. Each archaeological <esp:techterms term="assemblage">assemblage</esp:techterms> - or "<esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/contexts/rethinkingthecuneiformlibrary">library</esp:link>" - of scholarly tablets reflects personal choices and professional interests, as well as the relative availability of source material. Not surprisingly, works written and consulted in and around the Assyrian royal court predominantly concern advice and protection for the king.</p>

<esp:sh>Reading the future</esp:sh>
<esp:image file="ancientcity/ND-5497_04-obverse.jpg" description="Cuneiform tablet with part of the Šumma Alu house omen series" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/ND-5497_04-large.jpg" title="View large image of Šumma Alu house omens" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img252"><b>Image 1</b>: A fragmentary tablet from Nabu's temple in Kalhu, which says it is from Chapter 72 of the omen series <i>Šumma Alu</i></esp:bookmark> (online translation: <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/P363458/html" rel="external" hide-print="yes">CTN 4: 43</esp:link>). British Museum, ND 5497/04. <!-- no BM COL entry? --> <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/ND-5497_04-large.jpg" title="View large image of Šumma Alu house omens" hide-print="yes">View large image (233 KB).</esp:link> </esp:caption></esp:image>



<p>Almost a quarter of the Nimrud scholarly tablets contain long extracts from <esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/theworldoftheipu/divinatoryseries/">standard collections of omens</esp:link>. Most are from the series <esp:techterms term="Enūma Anu Ellil"><i>Enūma Anu Ellil</i></esp:techterms>, "When (the gods) Anu and Ellil", on the meaning of sightings in the night sky. Then there are signficant numbers of tablets from the series <esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/theworldoftheipu/divinatoryseries/signsoftheearth"><i>Šumma Ālu</i></esp:link>, "If a city" (<b>Image 1</b>), and <esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/theworldoftheipu/divinatoryseries/birthomens"><i>Šumma Izbu</i></esp:link>, "If an anomaly", which make <esp:techterms term="omen">ominous</esp:techterms> meaning from observations on the ground and unexpected births.</p>

<p>Given <esp:link page="professions" bookmark="ashipu">the prominence of <i>āšipu</i>-healers</esp:link> in Kalhu, it is perhaps surprising that the two <esp:techterms term="omen">omen</esp:techterms> series traditionally associated with this profession are not well represented. Just a few tablets from <esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/theworldoftheipu/divinatoryseries/signsofthebody"><i>Sakikkû</i></esp:link>, "Symptoms", and <esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/theworldoftheipu/divinatoryseries/signsofappearance"><i>Alandimmû</i>,</esp:link> "Physiognomy", have been identified.</p>

<p>There are no tablets from the sacrificial divination series <esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/theworldoftheipu/divinatoryseries/signsfromentrails"><i>Bārûtu</i></esp:link>, "The Art of Seeing", from Kalhu either, only an elegant clay model of a sheep's lung, annotated with technical terminology which was found outside the temple. But that absence is less suprising, given <esp:link page="professions" bookmark="baru">the low profile of <i>bārû</i>-diviners</esp:link> in the 7th-century city.</p>

<p>A related genre consists of ominous calendars, detailing which activities are favourable or unfavourable on particular months. The
most widely attested of these is called <esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/theworldoftheipu/divinatoryseries/signsoftime/"><i>Iqqur īpuš</i> "he destroyed, he built"</esp:link>.</p>

<esp:sh>Warding off evil</esp:sh>

<p><esp:techterms term="incantation">Incantations</esp:techterms> and rituals account for over a fifth of Kalhu's scholarly tablets. Some are to protect individuals against evil <esp:techterms term="demon">demons</esp:techterms> (<i>Ardat lilî</i>, <i>Asakkū marṣūtu</i>, <i>Lamaštu</i>, <i><esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/theworldoftheipu/healingtexts/uttuklemntu">Utukkū lemnūtu</esp:link></i>) or witches (<esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/theworldoftheipu/healingtexts/maql"><i>Maqlû</i></esp:link>, <i><esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/theworldoftheipu/healingtexts/urpu">Šurpu</esp:link></i>). Others avert the evil portended by an omen (<i>namburbû</i>). Some are to be performed as acts of transformation: the consecration of a priest, the induction of a cult statue, the building of a grave. And some, such as <i>Muššuʾu</i>, "Rubbing", combine physical therapies like massage with ceremonial acts and utterances to <esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/saao/knpp/essentials/medicinehealing/#h_healinginpractice">effect a cure</esp:link>.</p>

<p>A rather smaller proportion of tablets contain therapeutic recipes, often used alongside incantations to deal with anything from wounds to epilepsy to witches. Lists of plants, stones, and other healing substances are also attested. </p>

<esp:sh>Invoking divine support</esp:sh>
<esp:image file="ancientcity/nd_4405_72o_sm.jpg" description="Cuneiform tablet with catalogue of šuila prayers" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/nd_4405_72.jpg" title="View large image of catalogue of šuila prayersu" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img256"><b>Image 2</b>: A fragmentary catalogue of  "hand-raising" (<i>šuillakku</i>) prayers to gods and goddesses</esp:bookmark>, <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/P363593/html" rel="external" hide-print="yes">CTN 4: 179</esp:link>. British Museum, ND 4405/72. <!-- no BM COL entry? --> <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/nd_4405_72o.jpg" title="View large image of catalogue of šuillakku prayers" hide-print="yes">View large image (246 KB).</esp:link> </esp:caption></esp:image>


<p>The 25 or so hymns and prayers found in Kalhu are precisely to those deities we might expect: to the great god Ashur and his Babylonian counterpart <esp:glossary term="Ellil (deity)">Ellil</esp:glossary>, as well as Ellil's temple <esp:glossary term="Ekur (place)">Ekur</esp:glossary>; to the warrior <esp:link page="ninurta">Ninurta</esp:link>; to the great goddess <esp:link page="ishtar">Ištar</esp:link>; to the
Babylonian god <esp:glossary term="Marduk (deity)">Marduk</esp:glossary> and his divine spouse Zarpanitu. There are <i>šuillakku</i>-prayers to <esp:link page="nabu">Nabu</esp:link>, god of wisdom, and his spouse <esp:glossary term="Tašmetu (deity)">Tašmetu</esp:glossary>, as well as Nabu's Babylonian equivalent <esp:glossary term="Ea (deity)">Ea</esp:glossary>  (<b>Image 2</b>).</p>

<p>Sometimes it is hard to distinguish between hymns, prayers, and incantations. Take, for instance, the so-called <i>lipšur</i> litanies: long lists of potential ways to anger the gods, with equally long lists of requests for indvidual gods to "absolve" the wrong-doer. Are they incantations, which dispel the causes of disease (or dis-ease), to be perfomed in a ritual context? Or prayerful requests to all
the gods to relent? Likewise,  the <i>tamītus</i> requesting favourable outcomes for <esp:techterms term="extispicy">extispicy</esp:techterms>: are they stand-alone prayers to the god <esp:glossary term="Šamaš (deity)">Šamaš</esp:glossary> or part of the larger ritual performance of extispicy? There is still a lot of research to be done.</p>

<esp:sh>Telling classic tales</esp:sh>


<p>Surprisingly few tablets from Kalhu — about a dozen — contain any of the great narrative works of cuneiform literature. Most relate to
kingship in some way. The <esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/scribalapprenticeship/literaryworks/gilgame/"><i>Gilgameš</i></esp:link> epic most obviously recounts the tale of Babylonia's most famous—and fallible—mythical ruler. The
so-called creation epic, <esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/scribalapprenticeship/literaryworks/enmaeli/"><i>Enūma eliš</i>, "When above"</esp:link>, was performed during the king's annual <esp:techterms term="akītu"><i>akītu</i></esp:techterms> festival at the spring
<esp:techterms term="equinox">equinox</esp:techterms>. Two narratives about the god Ninurta, <esp:link page="ninurta" bookmark="h_ninurtasexploitslugale"><i>Lugale</i></esp:link> and
<esp:link page="ninurta" bookmark="h_ninurtasreturntonippurangimdimma"><i>Angim dimma</i></esp:link>, focus on his military victories and post-battle celebrations, an obvious role-model for an Assyrian king.</p>

<p>More personal works include the powerful and sophisticated monologue  <esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes"
url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/scribalapprenticeship/literaryworks/ludlul/"><i>Ludlul</i>, "Let me praise"</esp:link>, some collections of proverbs, and a slapstick account of a fool or jester, <i>aluzinnu</i>.</p>


<esp:sh>Constructing textual meaning</esp:sh>
<esp:image file="ancientcity/ND-5497_22-reverse.jpg" description="Cuneiform tablet with the astronomical list Mul-Apin" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/ND-5497_22-large.jpg" title="View large image of Mul-Apin tablet" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img250"><b>Image 3</b>: Many deities had counterparts in the sky, as explained by the astronomical constellation list <i>Mul-Apin</i></esp:bookmark> (online translation: <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/P363443" rel="external" hide-print="yes">CTN 4: 28</esp:link>). British Museum, ND 5497/22. <!-- no BM COL entry? --> <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/ND-5497_22-large.jpg" title="View large image of Mul-Apin tablet" hide-print="yes">View large image (456 KB).</esp:link> </esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Just less than a quarter of the scholarly tablets from Kalhu are what <esp:techterms term="Assyriology">Assyriologists</esp:techterms> now call <esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes"
url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/scribalapprenticeship/lexicallists/">lexical lists</esp:link>. They originate in scribal schooling, where their function is to teach students the elements and  complexities of <esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/saao/knpp/cuneiformrevealed/">cuneiform script</esp:link>. They also drilled students in spelling and vocabulary, as well as the relationship between words in the <esp:link page="sumerian">Sumerian</esp:link> and <esp:link page="akkadian">Akkadian</esp:link> languages. The more advanced of these lists often found a place in collections of scholarly writings too, as they helped readers to find extra meanings in text through wordplay and manipulation of signs. They are often quoted in learned commentaries to standard works.</p>

<p>Most of the lexical lists from Kalhu are thematic vocabularies. The early chapters of <esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes"
url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/scribalapprenticeship/lexicallists/phasei/thematiclists/">Ura<sub>5</sub> = <i>hubullu</i></esp:link> contain business and legal expressions, followed by objects made of particular materials. Its commentary is called Mur-gud. <esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/scribalapprenticeship/lexicallists/phasei/listofprofessions/">Lu<sub>2</sub> = <i>šá</i></esp:link> is a list of professional titles, while <i>malku = šarru</i>, "king", gives synonyms for <esp:techterms term="Akkadian">Akkadian</esp:techterms> words. The list known as Izi = <i>išātu</i>, "fire", groups words acrographically, that is by their initial signs, while Uludin<sub>2</sub> = <i>nabnītu</i>, "creation", is based on parts of the body.</p>

<p>The Kalhu sign lists include <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/scribalapprenticeship/lexicallists/phaseii/eaanderimhu/" rel="external" hide-print="yes">E-a = A = <i>nâqu</i> "to wail"</esp:link>, a logogram list ordered by the complexity of the logographic sign, and the closely related a<sub>2</sub> = A = <i>nâqu</i>. Finally, the list <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/scribalapprenticeship/lexicallists/phaseii/diri" rel="external" hide-print="yes">DIRI = <i>atru</i>, "excess"</esp:link>, explains the readings of compound
<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/scribalapprenticeship/lexicallists/phaseii/diri" rel="external" hide-print="yes" >DIRI = <i>atru</i>, "excess"</esp:link>, which explains the readings of compound <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/knpp/cuneiformrevealed/aboutcuneiform/categoriesofsigns/" rel="external" hide-print="yes">logograms</esp:link>.</p>


<esp:h>Mobile libraries?</esp:h>
<p>Much of scribal training focused on memorisation and recall of texts, so in principle mature scholars did not have to constantly look things up. However, in practice most communities of learned men accumulated collections of scholarly writings. They could be kept in the family home, stored in temple buildings, and/or moved around as needed. So while most of the scholarly tablets known from Kalhu come from Nabu's temple, <esp:link page="ezida">Ezida</esp:link>, that only tells us what had been left there in the days and years before its destruction.</p>



<p>Small numbers of scholarly tablets have turned up in the <esp:link page="northwestpalace">Northwest Palace</esp:link>, in Room FF of the royal family's private quarters (CTN 2: 268–272, literary, ritual, lexical works <esp:ref referent="postgate1973"/>) as well as Rooms 4 and 25 the administrative wing (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/P363442,P363444" rel="external" hide-print="yes">CTN 4: 27, 29</esp:link>: hymn, <i>Enūma eliš</i>). Similarly, Rooms H and S of the <esp:link page="governorspalace">Governor's Palace</esp:link> yielded a <i>tamītu</i> prayer, a perfume recipe and a lexical text (CTN 2: 214-216). That doesn't necessarily mean that any of these locations normally housed a "library" of scholarly works. These tablets could just have been passing through.</p>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/BM-Sm1368-obverse.jpg" description="Cuneiform tablet with letter from Adad-šumu-uṣur" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?partid=1&amp;assetid=1513864&amp;objectid=296204"
title="View large image on British Museum website" hide-print="yes"
rel="external"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img249"><b>Image 4</b>: Letter from the <i>āšīpu</i>-healer Adad-šumu-uṣur to king Esarhaddon, promising to consult a writing-board that he keeps at home, on the correct procedure for a ritual against earthquakes (<esp:link url="http://oracc.museum.upenn.edu/saao/P334233" rel="external" hide-print="yes">SAA 10: 202</esp:link>).</esp:bookmark> <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=296204&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">Sm.1368</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?partid=1&amp;assetid=1513864&amp;objectid=296204" title="View large image on British Museum website" hide-print="yes" rel="external">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link> © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>We also know that the scholars kept scholarly works at home (<b>Image 4</b>). The Kalhu-based <esp:link page="professions" bookmark="ashipu"><i>āšipu</i>-healer</esp:link> <esp:glossary term="Adad-šumu-uṣur (person)">Adad-šumu-uṣur</esp:glossary> tells king Esarhaddon (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/knpp/P334233/html" rel="external" hide-print="yes">SAA 10: 202</esp:link>):</p>

<blockquote><p>Concerning what the king, my lord,wrote to me: ‘Why
haven’t you sent an answer to (my) letter?’— I had to drive to the
palace those rams that the chief cook had brought out for me, and the
writing-board was at my house. Now then, I can look at the
writing-board  and extract the relevant interpretation. Concerning the
ritual against earthquake [...]</p></blockquote> 

<p>It is likely, then, that Adad-šumu-uṣur and other members of the highly influential <esp:link page="families" bookmark="h_thedescendentsofgabbuilaniere">Gabbu-ilani-ereš family</esp:link> moved scholarly tablets as needed between Ezida, their homes, and wherever they were needed to serve the king and other clients. The scholar <esp:glossary term="Nabu-zuqup-kenu (person)">Nabu-zuqup-kenu</esp:glossary>'s writings certainly got transferred to Nineveh at some point after his death. The elite scholars of Kalhu did not seem to protect their literary holdings. Unlike <esp:techterms term="scribe">scribes</esp:techterms> elsewhere they did not tend to write injunctions or curses on their tablets to protect them from theft. This suggests that they were supremely confident that their knowledge was safely in their hands.</p>

<esp:image file="langscripts/BM131952.jpg" description="Hinged writing board made of ivory, which is scored in a cross hatch pattern to prepare the surface for the addition of wax. Several pieces of inscribed wax have survived and are still attached to the board" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=108327&amp;objectId=368919&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img132"><b>Image 5</b>: Part of a set of sixteen writing boards hinged together as a folding set.</esp:bookmark> The cuneiform inscription on the front cover says that they originally contained the omen series <esp:techterms term="Enūma Anu Ellil"><i>Enūma Anu Ellil</i>,</esp:techterms> written for king Sargon's new city Dur-Šarruken but it was found down a well in Nimrud. Some fragments of inscribed wax remain. ND  3566, <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=368919&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 131952</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=108327&amp;objectId=368919&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Nevertheless, whole collections of tablets could be moved wholesale, for instance to set up the new temple of Nabu at <esp:glossary term="Dur-Šarruken (place)">Dur-Šarruken</esp:glossary>, or out again when it was suddenly abandoned. One writing-board of <esp:techterms term="Enūma Anu Ellil"><i>Enūma Anu Ellil</i></esp:techterms> destined for Dur-Šarruken was even thrown down a well at Kalhu (<b>Image 5</b>). Presumably the ill-fated city name inscribed on its front cover rendered it unuseable elsewhere. And maybe it was not only Nabu-zuqup-kenu's tablets that went to Nineveh in the early 7th century. It may have been more convenient for his descendants to have a working collection at the royal court rather than in what was now just a <esp:techterms term="province">provincial</esp:techterms> capital.</p>

<p>In other words, the tablets that archaeologists have found at Nimrud does not represent the sum total of scholarly works that were composed and copied in ancient Kalhu. Some certainly got taken away. Older tablets, especially if they were not baked, could break and crumble. They could get lost in passing. Once integrated into archaeological <esp:techterms term="stratigraphy">strata</esp:techterms> they could get damaged or destroyed by later generations digging graves or foundations. It is certain, however, that very many more remain under the ground to be recovered by archaeologists still to come.</p>

<p>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/><br/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/></p>
<esp:author first-names="Eleanor" last-name="Robson"/>
</body></html>
</esp:page>
