<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

	<esp:name>1850</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Imperial splendour: views of Kalhu in 1850</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>
	
<p class="firstpara">In 1850, the young British explorer <esp:glossary term="Layard, Austen Henry (person)">Austen Henry Layard</esp:glossary> had been tunnelling into the site of Nimrud, on and off, <esp:link page="ndtimeline" bookmark="thevictorianera">for the past five years</esp:link>. He had found a spectacular series of <esp:link page="stonegenies">sculptures</esp:link> and <esp:link page="obelisk">other objects</esp:link>, and shipped them home to the <esp:techterms term="British Museum">British Museum</esp:techterms>. He had mapped the rooms of <esp:link page="obeliskdiscovery" bookmark="img68">a series of palaces</esp:link>, which seemed to belong to the fabled Old Testament city of <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary>. Back in London, his lively writings and illustrations had captured the imaginations of the Christian establishment and the men of empire alike. It was now time to leave Nimrud behind for a new career in diplomacy — but the names of Layard and Nimrud would remain inseparable for a long, long time to come. </p>

<esp:h>The view from Nimrud</esp:h>
<esp:image file="mound/mw196242.jpg" description="Mezzotint of Layard, made in 1850, now in the National Portrait Gallery" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="267"/><b>Image 1</b>: This portrait of <esp:glossary term="Layard, Austen Henry (person)">Austen Henry Layard</esp:glossary> was made in 1850. It celebrates his adventures by depicting him in 'oriental' dress against an exotic background with Nimrud in the distance.  The original oil painting, by <esp:glossary term="Phillips, Henry Wyndham (person)">Henry Wyndham Phillips</esp:glossary>, was copied as this <esp:techterms term="mezzotint">mezzotint</esp:techterms> engraving by <esp:glossary term="Reynolds Jr, Samuel Williams (person)">Samuel William Reynolds Jr</esp:glossary>, to enable its mass reproduction. NPG D37226, National Portrait Gallery, <esp:link url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0" rel="external" hide-print="yes">CC-BY-NC-ND 3.0</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.npg.org.uk/collections/search/portrait/mw196242/" rel="external"  hide-print="yes">View this image on the National Portrait Gallery's website.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Layard was not archaeologist as we would understand the term, but then very few people were in 1850. The idea of <esp:techterms term="stratigraphy">stratigraphic</esp:techterms> excavation, the systematic uncovering and recording of objects in context, layer by layer, was still very new and controversial <esp:ref referent="rowley-conwy2007"/>. It seemed to work well for the prehistoric burial mounds uncovered in Danish peat bogs but in Britain the conditions of archaeological preservation meant that these methods were difficult to replicate. And there were already two highly respected methods for researching the past: the collecting of <esp:techterms term="antiquarianism">antiquarian</esp:techterms> objects, and the study of ancient classical and biblical sources. These were both prestigious activities that were well established in the fabric of British intellectual life and would take many decades to dislodge. Layard was not an expert in either of these fields either — just a young man wanting to make a name for himself. But he had good contacts, and a lot of initiative and ambition.</p>

<p>So Layard followed the precedent of British antiquarians by tunnelling for artefacts in the ground. The idea that fieldwork consisted of finding specimens abroad, then shipping them home for research and display, was quite usual in early nineteenth-century Europe.  Some people dug for geological samples, others picked exotic flowers or trapped wild animals for London’s various museums and research institutions. In fact, Layard’s closest inspiration and rival, <esp:glossary term="Botta, Paul-Émile (person)">Paul-Émile Botta</esp:glossary>, was a <esp:techterms term="natural history">natural historian</esp:techterms> by training. He had been posted to <esp:glossary term="Mosul (place)">Mosul</esp:glossary> as the first French <esp:techterms term="consul">consul-general</esp:techterms> in order to dig for antiquities, just as he had hunted for butterflies or caught snakes for collectors in Paris, earlier in his career <esp:ref referent="mcgovernmcgovern1986"/>.</p>

<esp:image file="mound/layard_monuments_1_pl98_sm.jpg" description="View of Nimrud, from Layard's Monuments of Nineveh I pl. 98" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/layard_monuments_1_pl98.jpg" title="Large version of View of Nimrud, from Layard's Monuments of Nineveh I pl. 98" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="268"/><b>Image 2</b>: Mid-nineteenth century readers of Layard's books must have marvelled at the thought that the remains of a once-mighty empire could be discovered in such apparently unremarkable hills. To add visual interest to this view of NImrud from the west, the engraver has foregrounded local men, a nomads' encampment and a small cemetery <esp:ref referent="layard1849-53" page="I pl. 98"/>.   <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/layard_monuments_1_pl98.jpg"  hide-print="yes">View large image.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Layard’s Nimrud, then, was a dark and mysterious place, buried in a hillside (<b>Image 2</b>). It was delineated by the carved stone <esp:techterms term="bas-relief">bas-reliefs</esp:techterms> that lined the walls of the palaces, and populated with artefacts that were attractive and portable enough to be shipped to England for art historical analysis and display. In Layard’s Nimrud archaeological artefacts such as mud-brick walls and <esp:techterms term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablets</esp:techterms> were invisible. He and his workers could not distinguish them from the earth through which the men tunnelled. And the high mound at the northern end of the site was just a mound. No-one knew about ancient <esp:link page="ziggurat">ziggurats</esp:link> in 1850, and the Old Testament story of the Tower of Babel was just a story (<i>Gen</i> 11:1–9).</p>



<p>Layard did find cuneiform inscriptions, on the stone sculptures in the palace, but they were bafflingly complex. In 1850 only a handful of men had pretensions to understanding the script, and they were still several years away from agreeing that the principles of decipherment had in fact been achieved. As a well brought up <esp:techterms term="Protestant">Church of England</esp:techterms> man, if not a particularly devout believer, Layard therefore had to take the Old Testament as his primary guide to the ancient Middle Eastern past.</p>

<p>Even the ancient city of Kalhu was invisible to Layard. Like his contemporaries, he saw only the Biblical city of Nineveh. The Book of Kings, Isiaiah, Nahum and of course Jonah, are replete with references to Nineveh. Indeed it had been local veneration of<esp:glossary term="Nebi Yunus (place)"> Jonah’s tomb</esp:glossary> that had attracted Europeans to start exploring the ruin mounds around Mosul a generation or two before. For Layard, as for his predecessors and contemporaries, Nimrud, and the similar sites of <esp:glossary term="Kuyunjik (place)">Kuyunjik</esp:glossary> and <esp:glossary term="Khorsabad (place)">Khorsabad</esp:glossary>, were all districts of ancient Nineveh, "an exceedingly great city of three days journey in breadth", in the words of Jonah himself (<i>Jon</i> 3:3). As Kouyunjik, where Layard had also been working, and Khorsabad, Botta's main excavation site, were yielding apparently very similar finds, then this all made perfect sense.</p>

<esp:h>The view from London</esp:h>
<esp:image file="mound/layards_nineveh_sm.jpg" description="Front cover of Layard's Nineveh and its Remains" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/layards_nineveh.jpg" title="Front cover of Layard's Nineveh and its Remains" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="269"/><b>Image 3</b>: Later editions of Layard's hugely popular account of his discoveries at Nimrud and <esp:glossary term="Kuyunjik (place)">Kuyunjik</esp:glossary> became known simply as <i>Layard's Nineveh</i>, encapsulating the public's identification of the man with the site, and the site with the biblical city <esp:ref referent="layard1849"/>. Note the cuneiform-like lettering on the cover, evoking a script that could still barely be read.  <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/layards_nineveh.jpg"  hide-print="yes">View large image.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>
<p>If the ancient city was hard to discern in the gloomy chaos of the excavation mound, it came brilliantly alive in London. Finds from Nimrud began to arrive at the British Museum in 1847, and attracted huge amounts of attention and debate. Mid-Victorian Britain was soaked in Biblical scripture and fascinated by tangible evidence of its reality.  Here, at last, were the remnants of a real-life Biblical city — and an excitingly corrupt and decadent one at that. According to your Christian interests, you could use Nimrud to sermonise about sinfulness, extol the glories of imperialism, or simply marvel at its exoticism and antiquity.</p>

<p>People who could not go to London to see the sculptures and other objects for themselves could read about them instead, and look at pictures (<b>Image 3</b>). Layard had no cameras on site, despite <esp:glossary term="Talbot, William Henry Fox (person)">Henry Fox Talbot’s</esp:glossary> deputations to the British Museum that he should. He preferred to rely on the more tried and tested methods of artists’ sketches to illustrate his often self-aggrandising narratives of his adventures and discoveries. The technologies of reproduction may have been monochrome but Layard’s anecdotes were addictively technicolour in their vivacity and realism. His books on Nimrud, from cheap railway editions to luxury folios, sold wildly well. Many other authors were keen to jump on the Assyrian bandwagon too <esp:ref referent="malley2012a"/>.</p> 

<p>Between 1847 and 1850, the popular middlebrow weekly <esp:techterms term="Illustrated London News"><i>The Illustrated London News</i></esp:techterms> carried no less than nine separate reports of artefacts from Nimrud arriving at the British Museum, usually handsomely illustrated. The bumper Christmas edition for 1850, otherwise filled with <esp:glossary term="Dickens, Charles (person)">Dickensian</esp:glossary> jollity, presented the latest arrivals as very much in the same spirit. They would “undoubtedly prove attractive to Christmas visitors to the Museum,” the author opined <esp:ref referent="iln1850-12-21"/>.</p> 

<esp:image file="mound/iln_1850_505_sm.jpg" description="The Illustrated London News's depiction of a winged genie from Nimrud at the British Museum, 28 December 1850" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/iln_1850_505.jpg" title="Large version of The Illustrated London News's depiction of a winged genie from Nimrud at the British Museum, 28 December 1850" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="270"/><b>Image 4</b>: Soon after the arrival of sculptures from Nimrud at the British Museum, the popular weekly <esp:techterms term="Illustrated London News"><i>Illustrated London News</i></esp:techterms> singled them out as "foremost amongst the novelties at this truly national establishment, and especially fitted for the gratification of holiday visitors" over the 1850 Christmas break <esp:ref referent="iln1850-12-28" page="505"/>.  The well dressed visitor shown next to this winged <esp:techterms term="genie">genie</esp:techterms> certainly looks pleased to meet a like-minded fellow. © Gale. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/iln_1850_505.jpg"  hide-print="yes">View large image.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>
<p>The following week, in the New Year edition, a (much enlarged) winged <esp:techterms term="genie">genie</esp:techterms> made eye contact with a dapper man-about-town, their body-language and demeanour suggesting mutual approval and comfort in each other’s company (<b>Image 4</b>). This image of clubbable geniality was in sharp contrast to the portrayal of rough and ready San Francisco on the immediately preceding page, grouped with desert Bedouin and artefacts from a deposed Indian sultan. It is clear where the boundaries of civilisation were thought to lie <esp:ref referent="iln1850-12-28"/>.</p>
 
<p>Indeed, as historians such as Fred Bohrer, Stephen Holloway and Timothy Larsen have extensively shown, educated Britons flocked to the news stands, the book shops and the British Museum to catch a glimpse of Biblical Nimrud because it resonated with modern experience <esp:ref referent="bohrer2003"/>, <esp:ref referent="holloway2001"/>, <esp:ref referent="larsen2009"/>. In 1850 Britain was at the heart of an unprecedentedly extensive, hugely profitable and technologically innovative naval empire. In ancient Assyria they chose to see a highly effective precursor, whose eventual downfall could be ignored or attributed to its heathen brutality. In this light, Layard’s next step, a move into politics and diplomacy, was a natural career progression.</p>

<esp:reading referent="bohrer2003"/>
<esp:reading referent="brusius2012"/>
<esp:reading referent="diaz-andreu2007" page="131-166"/>
<esp:reading referent="larsen1996"/>
<esp:reading referent="malley2012"/>
<esp:reading referent="rowley-conwy2007"/>

<esp:author first-names="Eleanor" last-name="Robson"/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>
	</body></html>

</esp:page>
