<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

	<esp:name>1950</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Remnants of empire: views of Kalhu in 1950</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>
	
<p class="firstpara">By 1950, at last, serious investigations were underway to reveal the <esp:link page="ancientcity">geography and history</esp:link> of the ancient city of Kalhu. Under the direction of <esp:glossary term="Mallowan, Max (person)">Max Mallowan</esp:glossary> the archaeological site of Nimrud was active again, for <esp:link page="nd1850">the first time in about a hundred years</esp:link>. Much had changed in attitudes and approaches over the past century but much had stayed surprisingly the same.</p>

<esp:h>From empire to Mandate to quasi-independence</esp:h>
<esp:image file="mound/nimrud_1931.jpg" description="Photo of Mallowan, Barbara Campbell Thompson and Christie at Nimrud, 1926" position="float"><esp:link url="https://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/online_tours/middle_east/agatha_christie__archaeology/nimrud_1949-58.aspx" rel="external" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img275"/><b>Image 1</b>:  <esp:glossary term="Mallowan, Max (person)">Max Mallowan</esp:glossary> and <esp:glossary term="Christie, Agatha (person)">Agatha Christie</esp:glossary> first visited Nimrud in 1931, while working on the <esp:techterms term="British Museum">British Museum's</esp:techterms> excavations at nearby <esp:glossary term="Kuyunjik (place)">Kuyunjik</esp:glossary> (ancient <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary>). At the centre of the photo, by dig director <esp:glossary term="Thompson, Reginald Campbell (person)">Reginald Campbell Thompson</esp:glossary>, is his wife Barbara with Mallowan and Christie on either side. © British Museum. <esp:link url="https://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/online_tours/middle_east/agatha_christie__archaeology/nimrud_1949-58.aspx"  rel="external" hide-print="yes">View this image on the British Museum's website.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Most notably, Nimrud was no longer in an inaccessible eastern <esp:techterms term="province">province</esp:techterms> of the <esp:techterms term="Ottoman">Ottoman empire</esp:techterms>, which had collapsed in the aftermath of World War I. The site was now off a well-travelled road in the modern state of Iraq. The country had been nominally independent from <esp:techterms term="Mandate">British Mandate</esp:techterms> rule for nearly two decades now but was still a monarchy headed by the overtly anglophile king <esp:glossary term="Faisal II (person)"> Faisal II</esp:glossary>. As recently as 1948 the <esp:techterms term="Anglo-Iraqi Treaty">Anglo-Iraqi Treaty</esp:techterms>—highly unpopular with many Iraqis—had formally renewed British influence over the country’s military and foreign affairs, while the monopolistic <esp:techterms term="Iraq Petroleum Company">Iraq Petroleum Company</esp:techterms> was Iraqi only in name. It was in fact registered in London and jointly owned by big western companies such as BP, Shell, and a consortium of American oil producers. Iraq was very much part of Britain's informal empire, and its archaeology was no exception.</p>

<p>Throughout the Mandate era of the 1920s and early 30s, the British had treated Iraqi archaeological sites as a resource to be exploited, not unlike oil <esp:ref referent="bernhardsson2005"/>. Yet throughout this period Nimrud had remained untouched (<b>Image 1</b>). The flagship British expeditions—both run in collaboration with wealthy American partners—were further south at <esp:glossary term="Ur (place)">Ur</esp:glossary> and <esp:glossary term="Kish (place)">Kish</esp:glossary>. Meanwhile in Assyria it was the <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablet-rich</esp:techterms> site of <esp:glossary term="Kuyunjik (place)">Kuyunjik</esp:glossary>, ancient <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary>, to which the British Museum returned. When Director of Antiquities <esp:glossary term="Bell, Gertrude (person)">Gertrude Bell</esp:glossary> died in 1926 the <esp:techterms term="British School of Archaeology in Iraq">British School of Archaeology in Iraq</esp:techterms>, BSAI, was set up in her memory and began operations in 1932.</p>

<esp:h>The view from the mound</esp:h>
<esp:image file="mound/OatesOates2001-p105-Fig-63-Nimrud-citadel-BISI.jpg" description="Aerial photograph of the citadel mound at Nimrud taken in the 1950s, showing remains of ziggurat mound" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/OatesOates2001-p105-Fig-63-Nimrud-citadel-BISI-large.jpg" title="Aerial photograph of the citadel mound at Nimrud taken in the 1950s, showing remains of ziggurat mound, large version" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img154"/><b>Image 2</b>: Mallowan's <esp:techterms term="stratigraphy">stratigraphic</esp:techterms> excavation methods had long been normal archaeological practice and remain so today. Unlike <esp:glossary term="Layard, Austen Henry (person)">Layard's</esp:glossary> tunnelling they enable a clear view of the dig from the air, as shown by this photograph taken in the 1950s from the northwest of the mound <esp:ref referent="oatesoates2001" page="105, Fig. 63"/>.  Photo: BSAI/BISI. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/OatesOates2001-p105-Fig-63-Nimrud-citadel-BISI-large.jpg"  hide-print="yes">View large image.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>
<p>In 1950 the director of BSAI was Max Mallowan, Professor of Western Asiatic Archaeology at the <esp:techterms term="Institute of Archaeology">Institute of Archaeology</esp:techterms> in London and husband of crime writer <esp:glossary term="Christie, Agatha (person)">Agatha Christie</esp:glossary>. The reasons he later gave for choosing Nimrud vary in their emphasis but the figure of Layard consistently looms large <esp:ref referent="mallowan1966" page="I 13"/>, <esp:ref referent="mallowan1977" page="241-3"/>. Crudely put, Mallowan wanted what Layard had got: not only the monumental finds but also the prestige that went with them. So in many ways the Nimrud expedition of 1948–60 was modelled quite explicitly on its century-old precursor. Excavation sites were chosen in order to recover more of Layard’s glorious <esp:link page="ivories">ivories</esp:link>, as well as the <esp:techterms term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> tablets that had escaped him. But fortunately Mallowan was not entirely bound by Layard’s legacy and sought to explore the <esp:techterms term="citadel">citadel</esp:techterms> mound in much more modern ways as well, with all the tools of mid-century, large-scale archaeology at his disposal (<b>Image 2</b>).</p>

<p>Thus the ancient city of Kalhu <esp:link page="modernnimrud" bookmark="img90">began to emerge</esp:link> beyond the confines of the stone-lined walls that Layard’s men had traced. A systematic <esp:techterms term="survey">survey</esp:techterms> mapped the entire citadel mound, while <esp:techterms term="stratigraphy">stratigraphic</esp:techterms> excavations of buildings revealed the <esp:link page="anzu" bookmark="img189">Victorian burrowings</esp:link> of Layard and the sculpture hunters, as well as uncovering much more of the Northwest Palace. Elsewhere on the citadel, Mallowan's team brought to light city walls, private residences, administrative buildings and—for the first time—cuneiform tablets. This substantial archive of some 150 letters and records turned out to belong to the late 9th-century <esp:techterms term="governor">governor</esp:techterms> of Kalhu, one <esp:glossary term="Bel-tarṣi-ilumma (person)">Bel-tarṣi-ilumma</esp:glossary>. Mallowan’s wide-ranging explorations, and integration of historical and archaeological data, brought into focus the ancient city of Kalhu itself for the very first time. </p>

<esp:image file="mound/INT-F-417545-000.png" description="Colour photo of Christie watching excavation at Nimrud, 1956" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/INT-F-417545-0000_large.jpg" title="Colour photo of Christie watching excavation at Nimrud, 1956, large version" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img291"/><b>Image 3:</b> In this rare colour photo, taken in 1956, Agatha Christie watches her husband Max Mallowan and colleagues remove a particularly delicate artefact from the ground at Nimrud. © Archiv Friedrich / Interfoto/Alinari Archives. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/INT-F-417545-0000_large.jpg" title="Colour photo of Christie watching excavation at Nimrud, 1956, large version" hide-print="yes">View large image.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Much effort went into understanding of the evolution of the city—or at least the royal citadel—over the course of the early first millennium BC. However, Mallowan’s Nimrud was strictly a window onto early <esp:techterms term="Neo-Assyrian">Neo-Assyrian</esp:techterms> Kalhu. One early sounding reached 13th-century <esp:techterms term="Middle Assyrian">Middle Assyrian</esp:techterms> levels but was not pursued beyond the first <esp:techterms term="excavation season">season</esp:techterms>. Later in the 1950s, <esp:glossary term="Oates, David (person)">David and Joan Oates</esp:glossary> were reprimanded for excavating post-Assyrian remains in the director’s absence. In this way, and others, Mallowan maintained tight chronological controls on the meaning and value of the site.</p>

<p>Nimrud itself became a bastion of Britishness, with Mallowan forever hatted, suited, and upright—directing, rarely getting down into the dirt himself (<b>Image 3</b>). His wife Agatha Christie proved as big an attraction for British visitors as the site itself. Indeed, Mallowan was careful to portray Agatha as a key member of the team, knowing that her celebrity attracted publicity, sponsorship, and technical support from the Iraq Petroleum Company <esp:ref referent="trumpler2001a"/>. Tea with Agatha was offered to IPC wives in exchange for the loan of heavy lifting and transport equipment. However, if Agatha and Max were the front-of-house representatives of the project, behind the scenes much of the real work was spearheaded by less glamorous Brits.</p>

<esp:image file="mound/hyslop_parker_sm.jpg" description="Photo of Barbara Parker and Rachel Clay on a donkey in Cyprus, 1930s" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/culture-obituaries/8680069/Rachel-Maxwell-Hyslop.html" rel="external" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img276"/><b>Image 4</b>:  In 1934 <esp:glossary term="Parker, Barbara (person)">Barbara Parker</esp:glossary> and Rachel Clay (later <esp:glossary term="Maxwell-Hyslop, Rachel (person)">Rachel Maxwell-Hyslop</esp:glossary>) together made up 2/3 of the very first student intake of the <esp:techterms term="Institute of Archaeology">Institute of Archaeology</esp:techterms> in London. They became lifelong friends and colleagues, and were key members of Mallowan's team at Nimrud. Here they are taking a break from excavation in <esp:glossary term="Cyprus (place)">Cyprus</esp:glossary> in the late 30s, with Rachel on the front of the donkey and Barbara behind. © The Daily Telegraph.  <esp:link url="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/culture-obituaries/8680069/Rachel-Maxwell-Hyslop.html"  rel="external" hide-print="yes">View this image in <i>The Daily Telegraph</i>'s obituary of Rachel Maxwell-Hyslop.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>
<!-- NB swap out ancientcity/ziggurat image for this one, & replace with green plate from 50 years -->


<p>Foremost amongst them was <esp:glossary term="Parker, Barbara (person)">Barbara Parker</esp:glossary>, Secretary/Librarian of the BSAI (<b>Image 4</b>). She not only oversaw the building of the archaeologists' <esp:techterms term="dig house">dig house</esp:techterms> at Nimrud before excavations began but also did much of the on-site photography as work progressed. Her academic specialisms were in the <esp:techterms term="seal, sealing">cylinder seals</esp:techterms> and the <esp:link page="legaldocuments">legal and economic documents</esp:link> found on the citadel. Parker's low-key research publications did much to illuminate the mechanisms of Neo-Assyrian empire and society <esp:ref referent="parker1954"/>, <esp:ref referent="parker1955"/>, <esp:ref referent="parker1957"/>, <esp:ref referent="parker1961"/>, <esp:ref referent="parker1962"/>.</p>

<p>Another major difference from a century before was the formal involvement of Iraqi authorities and professional archaeologists. A <esp:techterms term="division of finds">division of finds</esp:techterms> was made each year by the <esp:techterms term="Director-General of Antiquities">Director-General of Antiquities</esp:techterms>, ensuring that the best discoveries remained in-country, whether on site, in the <esp:techterms term="Iraq Museum">Iraq Museum</esp:techterms> or, later, at the museum in nearby <esp:glossary term="Mosul (place)">Mosul</esp:glossary>. And, as the expedition progressed, a team of Iraqi <esp:techterms term="conservator">conservators</esp:techterms> moved in to prepare the site of Nimrud for future visitors, the <esp:techterms term="restoration">restoration</esp:techterms> and excavation programmes sometimes hindering but often inspiring each other in unexpected ways.</p>

<esp:h>International glimpses of Kalhu</esp:h>

<p>Mallowan also <esp:link page="stonegenies" bookmark="h_geniesonthemove1lostproperty">followed Layard’s lead</esp:link> in <esp:link page="museumsworldwide" bookmark="bsai-nd-map">using choice objects</esp:link>, allocated to the BSAI in the formal division of finds, as incentives for sponsors. But the gifts were mostly of ivories, now, rather than <esp:techterms term="bas-relief">bas-reliefs</esp:techterms>—and the recipients were <esp:link page="bmag-conservation">museums</esp:link> and <esp:link page="maadog">universities</esp:link>, rather than politicians and diplomats. While the dispersal of finds has created enormous headaches for subsequent generations of researchers, at mid-century, before mass travel and much mass media, it was an efficient and well-intentioned way of giving access to a little bit of Assyria to many more people than could ever reach Nimrud, <esp:glossary term="Baghdad (place)">Baghdad</esp:glossary> or London. As Mallowan later put it:</p>

<blockquote><p>The wise provisions of the Iraqi law at that time have allowed these two gems [i.e., <esp:link page="northwestpalace" bookmark="img39">the twin ‘Ethiopian’ ivories</esp:link>] to be distributed between two far distant capitals [i.e., London and Baghdad]: there could in this dangerous age be no better insurance against the total loss and destruction of both, and no better way of allowing the East and West to enjoy them <esp:ref referent="mallowan1977" page="261"/>.</p></blockquote>

<esp:h>The view from the press</esp:h>
<esp:image file="mound/iln_1950-07-22-29_sm.jpg" description="The Illustrated London News' front covers, 22 and 29 July 1950" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/iln_1950-07-22-29.jpg" title="The Illustrated London News' front covers, 22 and 29 July 1950" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img278"/><b>Image 5</b>: On 22 July 1950 <i>The Illustrated London News</i> led with a photo of an "11 foot monster", "winged, harnessed and posed to guard the king's majesty of <esp:glossary term="Assurnasirpal II (person)">Assurnasirpal the second</esp:glossary>" from "the most important Assyrian dig at Nimrud since Layard's time" <esp:ref referent="iln1950-07-22" page="121"/>. The following week, nostalgia for empire was replaced by a striking image of "one of the world's finest tank destroyers: a US bazooka on deployment in Korea <esp:ref referent="iln1950-07-29" page="163"/>.  News from Nimrud was relegated to the back pages of the paper.  © Gale. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/iln_1950-07-22-29.jpg"  hide-print="yes">View large image.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>For academic audiences, Mallowan and his team <esp:link page="resources" bookmark="articlesIraq">published preliminary reports</esp:link> in BSAI’s biannual journal <i>Iraq</i>, published back in London. But in presenting his finds to a wider public he deliberately emulated Layard  by writing for the now somewhat old-fashioned <esp:techterms term="Illustrated London News"><i>Illustrated London News</i></esp:techterms>. A more up-to-date choice might have been the <esp:techterms term="Picture Post"><i>Picture Post</i></esp:techterms>, for instance, that was started in the late 1930s. Like Layard, he placed pieces in two or three issues a year for almost every year of the excavation. In 1950, however, the emphasis was on finds in the field, rather than arrivals in the British Museum, and photography allowed a far greater emphasis on artefacts, buildings and the archaeological process than had been possible in Layard's day.</p>

<p>While Layard’s Nimrud <esp:link page="nd1850" bookmark="h_theviewfromlondon">was packaged</esp:link> as an extension of <esp:glossary term="Dickens, Charles (person)">Dickensian</esp:glossary> Christmas jollity, Mallowan’s Nimrud of 1950 was juxtaposed with terrifying images of the <esp:techterms term="Korean War">Korean War</esp:techterms> (<b>Image 5</b>). Victorian Britons could celebrate Assyria as an ancient allegory of Pax Britannica, imperiously self-confident. Just five years after the end of World War II, however, at a time of waning British power, Assyrian imperialism took on a more sinister hue <esp:ref referent="iln1950-07-22"/>, <esp:ref referent="iln1950-07-29"/>. </p>

<p>A winged lion graced the front cover of the <i>ILN</i> on 22 July 1950, “guard[ing] the king’s majesty of <esp:glossary term="Assurnasirpal II (person)">Assurnasirpal the second</esp:glossary>” while the following pages covered various aspects of royal pageantry in contemporary Britain. Nimrud was still as it always had been, a familiar part of the extended British empire. The next week, however, there was no escaping the new realities of warfare: an enormous bazooka dominated the front cover, while massed American tanks loomed over a symbolically fallen winged bull. An allegory for Britain’s newly reduced status in the world, if ever there was one, just a year after the formal creation of the self-governing Commonwealth out of the ashes of the former British empire.</p>

<esp:reading referent="mallowan1966"/>
<esp:reading referent="mallowan1977"/>
<esp:reading referent="mccall2001"/>
<esp:reading referent="trumpler2001a"/>

<esp:author first-names="Eleanor" last-name="Robson"/>
	</body></html>

</esp:page>
