<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

	<esp:name>1900</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Abandoned antiquity: views of Kalhu in 1900</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>
	
<p class="firstpara">If in 1850 ancient Kalhu was not yet clearly visible from the modern site of Nimrud, by 1900 Nimrud itself had lost all geographical reality in the English speaking world. There could be no view of Kalhu from Nimrud because there was <esp:link page="ndtimeline" bookmark="h_theearlytwentiethcentury">no-one on site</esp:link>, and no-one of any academic authority <esp:link page="ndtimeline" bookmark="h_thevictorianera">had set foot there for decades</esp:link>. And for the new generation of university-based <esp:techterms term="Assyriology">Assyriologists</esp:techterms>, the heroic story of <esp:glossary term="Layard, Austen Henry (person)">Layard's</esp:glossary> adventures still overshadowed attempts to understand the ancient city.</p>
 
<esp:h>The view from the field</esp:h>
<esp:image file="mound/nimrud-mound-stereoviews-c1910.jpg" description="Stereoview photographs of the mound at Nimrud with two local men in the foreground" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/nimrud-mound-stereoviews-c1910-large.jpg" title="Large version of Nimrud mound stereoview"  hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img271"><b>Image 1</b>: These <esp:techterms term="stereoview">stereoview</esp:techterms> photographs of the ruins of Nimrud present it as remote, romantic and entirely desolate. They were published by the New York firm of <esp:link url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Underwood_%26_Underwood" hide-print="yes" rel="external">Underwood and Underwood</esp:link> some time in the 1910s.</esp:bookmark> Source: private collection. The Nimrud Project CC-BY-SA 3.0 <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/nimrud-mound-stereoviews-c1910-large.jpg" title="Large image of Nimrud mound stereoview" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>In 1900 Nimrud looked much as it had done <esp:link page="onthemound" bookmark="img261">fifty years before</esp:link>, except that more sculptures had been removed from the <esp:link page="northwestpalace">Northwest Palace</esp:link> (<b>Image 1</b>). For a few years after Layard’s expedition to Nimrud had shut up shop, other adventurous entrepreneurs moved in to quarry for further <esp:techterms term="bas-relief">bas-reliefs</esp:techterms>. The most eager clients were north American <esp:techterms term="Protestant">Protestant</esp:techterms> colleges, who wanted concrete confirmation of Biblical truth, in the face of increasing scientism in popular culture <esp:ref referent="holloway2004"/>, <esp:ref referent="cohenkangas2010"/>. The figure of the winged <esp:techterms term="genie">genie</esp:techterms> was particularly resonant, because it had become identified with <esp:glossary term="Nisroch (deity)">Nisroch</esp:glossary>, the deity of the temple in which king <esp:glossary term="Sennacherib (person)">Sennacherib</esp:glossary> was supposedly murdered, according to the Old Testament Book of Kings (<i>II Kings</i> 19:36–37). However, we now understand both Nimrud and Nisroch to be later corruptions of the name of <esp:glossary term="Ninurta (deity)">Ninurta</esp:glossary>, the god of victory whose <esp:link page="ziggurat" bookmark="h_thezigguratandtempleofNinurta">temple</esp:link> Layard had unearthed just to the north of the palace at Nimrud.</p>

<p>The <esp:techterms term="Crimean War">Crimean War</esp:techterms> of the mid-1850s, and its decades-long aftermath, discouraged further European explorations. Nimrud had only <esp:link page="ndtimeline" bookmark="h_thevictorianera">sporadic visits</esp:link> from western travellers, in the 1860s and 70s, who made few further significant discoveries <esp:ref referent="green2008"/>. And then for several decades the site was left to its fate.</p>

<esp:h>The view from the museum</esp:h>
<esp:image file="mound/AN00029940_001_l.jpg" description="Large stela of Assurnasirpal II, found in Ninurta's temple" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=367076" rel="external"  hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img272"/><b>Image 2</b>: This enormous carving of king <esp:glossary term="Assurnasirpal II (person)">Assurnasirpal II</esp:glossary>, nearly 3m tall and weighing around 4 tonnes, was shipped from the ruins of <esp:link page="ziggurat" bookmark="h_thezigguratandtempleofninurta">Ninurta's temple</esp:link> to the British Museum. It is covered with a cuneiform inscription which enabled <esp:glossary term="Rawlinson, Henry Creswicke (person)">Rawlinson</esp:glossary> and Layard to identify Nimrud as the ancient Assyrian city of Kalhu (biblical Calah). BM 118005 © British Museum <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=367076" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View this image on the British Museum's website</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Although the site of Nimrud itself was now virtually inaccessible, in the <esp:techterms term="British Museum">British Museum</esp:techterms>, Layard’s discoveries still dominated the ground floor of the building. The Museum's catalogue of 1900 not only gives detailed descriptions of the monuments themselves but also reproduces Layard’s sketch plans of the Northwest Palace and the <esp:link page="obeliskdiscovery" bookmark="img68">citadel</esp:link> of Nimrud <esp:ref referent="britishmuseum1900" page="13-14"/>. Kalhu had, to all intents and purposes, moved to London.</p>

<p>The <esp:link page="inscriptions">inscriptional evidence</esp:link> gleaned from Nimrud had also become increasingly meaningful. Already by 1853, in <i>Discoveries in the Ruins of Nineveh and Babylon</i>, Layard presented summaries of the main monumental texts as deciphered by <esp:glossary term="Rawlinson, Henry Creswicke (person)">Rawlinson</esp:glossary> and <esp:glossary term="Hincks, Edward (person)">Hincks</esp:glossary>. Of particular importance was a huge <esp:techterms term="stela, stele">stela</esp:techterms> of “the early Nimroud king” which <esp:link page="anzu" bookmark="img189">he had found at the entrance</esp:link> to the temple of “the god of war” (that is, the stele of <esp:glossary term="Assurnasirpal II (person)">Assurnasirpal II</esp:glossary> from <esp:link page="ziggurat" bookmark="h_thezigguratandtempleofninurta">Ninurta's temple</esp:link>, now housed in the British Museum) (<b>Image 2</b>). It revealed that “the quarter of Nineveh now called Nimroud” had been known as Kalhu—Biblical Calah—in ancient times <esp:ref referent="layard1853" page="294"/>. Layard gave examples of the king’s military campaigns and noted the existence of “an account ... of the building of the north-west palace of Nimroud, which, when deciphered, will be of considerable interest, and may enable us to restore that edifice.” </p>

<esp:h>The view from the university</esp:h>
<esp:image file="mound/robertrogers.jpg" description="Photograph of R.W. Rogers" position="float"><esp:link url="https://uknow.drew.edu/confluence/display/DrewHistory/Robert+William+Rogers" rel="external"  hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img273"/><b>Image 3</b>: The <esp:glossary term="Rogers, Rev Robert William (person)">Reverend Robert William Rogers</esp:glossary> (1864-1930) was a typical turn-of-the century American Assyriologist, in that he was trained primarily in Old Testament history and theology, and taught in a seminary for training <esp:techterms term="Methodism">Methodist</esp:techterms> ministers. Image © Drew University. <esp:link url="https://uknow.drew.edu/confluence/display/DrewHistory/Robert+William+Rogers" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View image on Drew University's website</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>
<p>Sadly, however, few of Layard’s successors took him up on the offer, even though <esp:techterms term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> rapidly became a meaningful script. From the 1870s onwards, Assyriology moved from the field into the university, and became increasingly recognised as a valid subject of academic study <esp:ref referent="lyon1896"/>. In the years around 1900, several desk-bound academics wrote popular accounts of Assyrian (and <esp:glossary term="Babylonia (place)">Babylonian</esp:glossary>) history and culture (<esp:ref referent="jastrow1898"/>, <esp:ref referent="krall1899"/>, <esp:ref referent="sayce1900"/>. But few had ever set foot in the Middle East or even, perhaps, in the British Museum. Unsurprisingly they struggled to conjure the reality of the ancient city.</p>

<p>One of the most popular turn-of-the-century accounts of  Assyrian history, now long forgotten, was <esp:glossary term="Rogers, Rev Robert William (person)">Reverend Robert William Rogers'</esp:glossary> <i>A history of Babylonia and Assyria</i> <esp:ref referent="rogers1900"/>. Rogers has now faded into obscurity but was eminent in his day, as Professor of Hebrew and Old Testament <esp:techterms term="exegesis">Exegesis</esp:techterms> at <esp:techterms term="Drew Theological Seminary">Drew Theological Seminary</esp:techterms> in New Jersey and a life-long Visiting Fellow of <esp:link url="http://www.sjc.ox.ac.uk/" rel="external" hide-print="yes">St John's College, Oxford</esp:link>  (<b>Image 3</b>). His book, first published in 1900, ran to a sixth edition by 1915 and was widely considered to be a standard <esp:ref referent="jastrow1901"/>, <esp:ref referent="price1901"/>. Rogers devotes over 20 pages to <esp:link page="nd1850">Layard’s derring-do</esp:link> in discovering Nimrud but almost entirely ignores ancient Kalhu, dealing with it in a couple of paragraphs <esp:ref referent="rogers1900" page="I 138-160; II 13"/>. Instead, he cherry-picks Assurnasirpal and <esp:glossary term="Shalmaneser III (person)">Shalmaneser's</esp:glossary> Annals for their military content — endless conquests, endless victories — and by and large ignores these kings' detailed descriptions of constructing of Kalhu itself. Paradoxically, the geography of the edges of empire comes to the fore, while the centre vanishes from view.</p>



<esp:h>Other views</esp:h>
<esp:image file="mound/nesbit-amulet168_sm.jpg" description="Illustration of the Nisroch in E Nesbit's The Story of the Amulet" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/nesbit-amulet168.jpg" title="Large version of Illustration of the Nisroch in E Nesbit's The Story of the Amulet"  hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img274"/><b>Image 4</b>: <esp:glossary term="Millar, Harold Robert (person)">H.R. Millar</esp:glossary>, illustrator of <esp:glossary term="Nesbit, Edith (person)">Nesbit's</esp:glossary> <i>The Story of the Amulet</i>, shows "the strange and terrible figure" of the <esp:glossary term="Nisroch (deity)">Nisroch</esp:glossary>, or winged genie, who "raised his great arm and pointed at the wall of the dungeon” in order to help the children escape <esp:ref referent="nesbit1906" page="168"/>, <esp:ref referent="marchant2006"/>. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/nesbit-amulet168.jpg" title="Large image of Nimrud mound stereoview" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>
<p>Elsewhere in Britain, Layard’s <esp:link page="stonegenies">stone kings and genies</esp:link> had lost the power to impress the imperial classes. They gradually found their way from the private stately homes of his former patrons to public institutions such as the Fitzwilliam Museum in Cambridge. Ideas of empire had changed. Britain's so-called ‘white colonies’ of Canada, Australia, and New Zealand had been granted significant autonomy, while the increasing dominance of France, Russia and Germany meant that Britain’s monopoly on world power was not as clear cut as half a century before. Even though Layard—who had died only a few years before—had been elevated into the ranks of the great Victorian discoverers, Assyria was simply no longer fashionable amongst the ruling classes.</p>

<p>Devout Christianity was also on the wane, as Darwinism, geology and indeed archaeology became increasingly mainstream in British intellectual life <esp:ref referent="lindbergnumbers2003" page="139-202"/>. Paradoxically, the cuneiform inscriptions from Nimrud, and other Assyrian cities, played a large part in undermining belief in the literal veracity of the Christian scriptures. Some supposed Assyrian kings—Pul of the Book of Kings, for instance (<i>II Kings</i> 15:19)—were nowhere to be found in the Assyrian evidence itself <esp:ref referent="holloway2003"/>. Conversely, it turned out large swathes of Assyrian history passed entirely unremarked in the Old Testament. But most damning, perhaps, were those events preserved in both Biblical and Assyrian sources. Most famously, king Sennacherib’s siege of Jerusalem (e.g., <i>II Kings</i> 18-19) was now just the scene of an ambiguous military encounter rather than the cue for a divine miracle <esp:ref referent="kalimirichardson2014"/>. </p>

<p>Even the formerly awe-inspiring winged genies of Nimrud had lost their power to impress and terrify. One of the most popular British children’s authors of the day was <esp:glossary term="Nesbit, Edith (person)">E. Nesbit</esp:glossary>. Her book <esp:link url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Railway_Children" rel="external" hide-print="yes"><i>The Railway Children</i></esp:link>, and the <esp:link url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Railway_Children_%281970_film%29" rel="external" hide-print="yes">1970 film</esp:link> which is based on it, are still widely enjoyed in Britain today. In <esp:link url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Story_of_the_Amulet" rel="external" hide-print="yes"><i>The Story of the Amulet</i></esp:link> (1906) an ordinary middle-class family of children is accidentally transported to ancient <esp:glossary term="Babylon (place)">Babylon</esp:glossary>. The only way to get back is to summon “the strange and terrible figure” of a Nisroch, or winged genie (<b>Image 4</b>). He turns out to be a benign and helpful “dear” who happily helps the children return home <esp:ref referent="briggs2006"/>. There are few more pointed symbols than this of the British domestication of the once deeply alien Nimrud.</p>

<esp:reading referent="holloway2007"/>
<esp:reading referent="reade2008"/> 

<esp:author first-names="Eleanor" last-name="Robson"/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>


	</body></html>

</esp:page>
