<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

	<esp:name>2000</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Nimrud resurgent? Views of Kalhu in the new millennium</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>
	
<p class="firstpara">By the year 2000, ancient Kalhu was much more visible than it had ever been before, while the site of Nimrud had never been less accessible. The second half of the twentieth century had brought dramatic changes in the ways ancient Kalhu was viewed. The <esp:link page="northwestpalace">Northwest Palace</esp:link> was re-interpreted in detail, prior to its physical and virtual reconstruction. Other buildings on the royal <esp:techterms term="citadel">citadel</esp:techterms> were excavated and studied too. Off the mound, archaeologists explored <esp:link page="fortshalmaneser">Fort Shalmaneser</esp:link> and began mapping the lower town.  Although the <esp:techterms term="Neo-Assyrian">Neo-Assyrian period</esp:techterms> still dominated research agendas, it was becoming increasingly clear that Kalhu had been occupied for millennia. Work on site was forced to a halt by war in 1990, but this enabled a period of re-analysis and synthesis of earlier work. At the turn of the new millennium, a decade of far-reaching <esp:techterms term="sanctions">UN sanctions</esp:techterms> on Iraq seemed to be coming to an end, encouraging archaeologists to travel to and from Iraq, and new international working relationships to be forged.</p>


<esp:h>The view from the Northwest Palace</esp:h>
<!-- nwpalace from north -->
<esp:image file="mound/nw_palace_from_west_er_sm.jpg" position="float" description="Looking west over the southern end of the the NW Palace, March 2001"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/nw_palace_from_west_er.jpg" title="Looking west over the southern end of the the NW Palace, March 2001, large version" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img279"/><b>Image 1</b>: By March 2001, when Nimrud received a large international group of visiting archaeologists, a decade of enforced neglect was taking its toll on the reconstructed Northwest Palace. This view looks west across Courtyards 80 and 72b in the southernmost area of the palace. In the background queen <esp:glossary term="Yabaʾ (person)">Yabaʾ's</esp:glossary> tomb (Room 49) is protected by a makeshift metal roof. Photo by Eleanor Robson. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/nw_palace_from_west_er.jpg" title="Looking west over the southern end of the the NW Palace, March 2001, large version" hide-print="yes">View large image.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>

<p><esp:link page="nd1850">Layard's</esp:link> legacy could never be quite escaped. In the 1950s <esp:glossary term="Mallowan, Max (person)">Mallowan's</esp:glossary> team <esp:link page="nd1950">had revealed</esp:link> that the Northwest Palace was even larger and more complex than the Victorians had thought, while the few <esp:link page="stonegenies">sculptural panels</esp:link> and fragments still lining the walls of its reception rooms emphasised the extent to which it had been plundered—for the best of intentions—a century before. So the <esp:techterms term="British School of Archaeology in Iraq">BSAI's</esp:techterms> <esp:techterms term="backfill">backfill</esp:techterms> was removed and in 1974 a Polish team, led by <esp:glossary term="Meuszyński, Janusz (person)">Janusz Meuszyński</esp:glossary>, began a thorough reanalysis of the remaining <esp:techterms term="bas-relief">bas-reliefs</esp:techterms>. Building on <esp:glossary term="Gadd, Cyril John (person)">Cyril Gadd's</esp:glossary> pioneering work of the interwar period, they also sought to <esp:link page="museumsworldwide" bookmark="nwp-nd-map">re-locate all 196 stone sculptures</esp:link> that had been removed from the palace in the 19th century <esp:ref referent="gadd1936"/>. Despite Meuszýnski's sudden death in 1976, the team impressively succeeded in reconstructing the original decorative scheme, in print if not in the palace itself <esp:ref referent="meuszynski1981"/>, <esp:ref referent="paley-sobolewski1987"/>, <esp:ref referent="paley-sobolewski1992"/> .</p>

<p>At the same time, the Iraqi <esp:techterms term="State Board of Antiquities and Heritage">State Board of Antiquities and Heritage</esp:techterms> wanted to make Nimrud an attractive and exciting place for visitors. Iraqi archaeologists, architects and <esp:techterms term="conservator">conservators</esp:techterms> carried out a long-tem project to rebuild Northwest Palace's fragile <esp:techterms term="mud brick">mud-brick walls</esp:techterms> and protect the last of the sculptures <esp:ref referent="al-qaissi2008"/>. It was now possible for visitors to walk through the roofless throne room and reception suites of the palace, mentally recreating its original opulence and splendour (<b>Image 1</b>).</p>

<esp:image file="mound/muzahim_tomb_er_sm.jpg" position="float" description="Muzahim Mahmoud leading a tour to Yaba's tomb, March 2001"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/muzahim_tomb_er.jpg" title="Muzahim Mahmoud leading a tour to Yaba's tomb, March 2001" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img280"/><b>Image 2</b>: <esp:glossary term="Hussein, Muzahim Mahmoud (person)">Muzahim Mahmoud</esp:glossary>, Iraqi excavator of the royal burials of Nimrud, gives archaeological visitors a tour of Queen Yabaʾ's tomb in March 2001. Photo by Eleanor Robson. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/muzahim_tomb_er.jpg" title="Muzahim Mahmoud leading a tour to Yaba's tomb, March 2001" hide-print="yes">View large image.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>In the course of clearing rooms in the southern part of the palace, which Mallowan's team had not fully excavated, they literally hit gold <esp:ref referent="damerji2008"/>. Over the course of 1988-90 <esp:glossary term="Hussein, Muzahim Mahmoud (person)">Muzahim Mahmoud</esp:glossary> and colleagues excavated a series of four under-floor tombs containing the skeletons of long-dead Assyrian royal women and their grave goods, including a huge quantity of gorgeous <esp:techterms term="gold">gold</esp:techterms> jewellery (<b>Image 2</b>). This stunning discovery was only just gaining international attention when Iraq's invasion of Kuwait in the summer of 1990 led, via the <esp:techterms term="Gulf War">Gulf War</esp:techterms> and the <esp:techterms term="sanctions">UN sanctions</esp:techterms> regime, to over a decade of isolation and deprivation for the country's archaeologists (and populace as a whole).</p>


<esp:h>The view from the citadel</esp:h>
<esp:image file="mound/nimrud_google_earth_sm.jpg" position="float" description="Nimrud citadel on Google Earth 2002"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/nimrud_google_earth.jpg" title="Nimrud citadel on Google Earth 2002, large version" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img281"/><b>Image 3</b>: Google Earth's imagery of Nimrud dates to October 2002. It shows how intensively the surface of the royal <esp:techterms term="citadel">citadel</esp:techterms> was dug in the later 20th century. The restored palace and temples are particularly visible. © DigitalGlobe and Google. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/nimrud_google_earth.jpg" title="Nimrud citadel on Google Earth 2002, large version" hide-print="yes">View large image.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>As well as long-familiar Northwest Palace, many more buildings on Nimrud's <esp:techterms term="citadel">citadel</esp:techterms> had become increasingly visible and comprehensible during the second half of the twentieth century (<b>Image 3</b>). In the 50s, Mallowan's team had re-excavated other areas which Layard had first explored. To the north of the palace were the <esp:link page="ziggurat">ziggurat and its associated range of temples</esp:link>, while a cluster of buildings on the southwest corner of the mound proved to comprise <esp:link page="ezida">Nabu's temple</esp:link>, the <esp:link page="governorspalace">Governor's Palace</esp:link>, and the so-called <esp:glossary term="Burnt Palace (place)">Burnt Palace</esp:glossary>.</p>

<p>In the 70s Meuszyński and colleagues also explored the central area of the citadel, where they discovered a large cache of sculpted bas-reliefs <esp:ref referent="sobolewski1981"/>. These had been dismantled from <esp:glossary term="Tiglath-pileser III (person)">Tiglath-pileser III's</esp:glossary> so-called <esp:glossary term="Central Palace (place)">Central Palace</esp:glossary>, perhaps by <esp:glossary term="Esarhaddon (person)">Esarhaddon</esp:glossary>, ready for a redeployment that never came.  Iraqi <esp:techterms term="conservator">conservators</esp:techterms> consolidated and restored the temples for visitors, leaving the archaeologists' backfill to protect the rest for future generations.</p>

<esp:h>The view from the lower city</esp:h>
<esp:image file="mound/nd_town_survey.jpg" position="float" description="University of Turin survey map of Nimrud's lower town"><esp:link url="http://www.centroscavitorino.it/en/progetti/iraq/nimrud-prosp_topo.html" hide-print="yes" rel="external"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img282"/><b>Image 4</b>: The Italian <esp:techterms term="topographical map">topographical map</esp:techterms> of Nimrud's lower town was made by on-site <esp:techterms term="survey">surveying</esp:techterms> on the ground in the late 1980s. These days such techniques are supplemented by detailed study of aerial imagery, in order to identify features such as ancient roads and canals. © Centro Ricerche Archeologiche e Scavi di Torino. <esp:link url="http://www.centroscavitorino.it/en/progetti/iraq/nimrud-prosp_topo.html" hide-print="yes" rel="external">View this image on the University of Turin's website.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Finally, and perhaps most significantly, Kalhu was no longer seen as simply the royal citadel. Already in the 1950s and 60s, the BSAI expedition, led by Mallowan's young colleague <esp:glossary term="Oates, David (person)">David Oates</esp:glossary>, had started work on the enormous building at the southeastern corner of the site. This soon became known as <esp:link page="fortshalmaneser">Fort Shalmaneser</esp:link>, after its royal founder, and yielded literally thousands of beautiful <esp:link page="ivories">pieces of carved ivory</esp:link>. Originally dumped there as loot and <esp:techterms term="tribute">tribute</esp:techterms> from Assyria's western neighbours, some of the ivories were cannily redeployed as gifts to the British team's sponsoring institutes worldwide.</p>

<p>In the late 80s two new projects began, headed by John Curtis of the <esp:techterms term="British Museum">British Museum</esp:techterms> and <esp:glossary term="Fiorina, Paolo (person)">Paolo Fiorina</esp:glossary> of the University of Turin <esp:ref referent="curtisetal1993"/>, <esp:ref referent="fiorina2008"/>. Both were halted by Iraq's invasion of Kuwait and the subequent <esp:techterms term="Gulf War">Gulf War</esp:techterms> in 1990-91 before they could do more than preliminary work on Fort Shalmaneser. But the Italian team also surveyed the rest of the area within the extensive city walls. Like many ancient Mesopotamian cities, Kalhu had not been densely settled but enjoyed large areas of open space, especially in the south (<b>Image 4</b>).</p>

<p>Pottery finds also showed the Italians that people had lived on the site from at least the sixth millennium BC — that is, some 8000 years ago! — to the first centuries of Islam, only a thousand years in the past. These were tantalising glimpses of a Kalhu far more extensive and long-lived than the Neo-Assyrian royal enclave.</p>


<esp:h>Changing views from London</esp:h>
<p><i>Nimrud and its Remains</i>, Mallowan’s final report on his work, came out in 1966 <esp:ref referent="mallowan1966"/>. Both in title and in style it was a deliberate echo of <esp:glossary term="Layard, Austen Henry (person)">Layard's</esp:glossary> <i>Nineveh and its Remains</i> <esp:ref referent="layard1849-53"/>. It rejected systematic presentation of finds in the now accepted manner in favour of narrative descriptions of the landscape and life onsite, interspersed with archictural descriptions of the major buildings, monuments and artefacts. Much of the work carefully described in <esp:link page="resources" bookmark="articlesIraq">the preliminary reports</esp:link> published in BSAI's journal <i>Iraq</i> never made it into the final publication.</p>

<esp:image file="mound/iln_1990-09-03-52_sm.jpg" position="float" description="Queen Yaba's flowery crown in the ILN, September 1990"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/iln_1990-09-03-52.jpg" title="Queen Yaba's flowery crown in the ILN, September 1990, large version"/><esp:caption><b>Image 5</b>: Queen Yabaʾ's flowery crown is one of the highlights of the spectacular Nimrud Treasure. <i>The Illustrated London News</i> carried a three-page colour feature on the finds in September 1990. <esp:ref referent="iln1990-09-03"/>. © Gale. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/mound/iln_1990-09-03-52.jpg" title="Queen Yaba's flowery crown in the ILN, September 1990, large version">View large image.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>In parallel, the BSAI team were publishing the individual artefacts <esp:link page="resources" bookmark="BISIbooks">according to type</esp:link>—ivories, metalwork, <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablets</esp:techterms>, for instance <esp:ref referent="curtis2013"/>. This proved to be painfully slow work, hampered in the first place by the fact that finds <esp:link page="museumsworldwide" bookmark="bsai-nd-map">had been dispersed</esp:link> to collections all over the world. From 1990 onwards <esp:techterms term="sanctions">UN sanctions</esp:techterms> banned international travel to Iraq, making it impossible to work on the objects still in Nimrud, <esp:glossary term="Mosul (place)">Mosul</esp:glossary>,  and <esp:glossary term="Baghdad (place)">Baghdad</esp:glossary>. Yet the venerable <esp:techterms term="Illustrated London News"><i>Illustrated London News</i></esp:techterms> continued its 150-year interest in Nimrud, reporting both on the Iraqis' spectacular gold finds, now dubbed the Nimrud Treasures, as well as the latest British work on site <esp:ref referent="iln1990-09-03"/>.</p>


<p>Despite this frustrating inability to access the site, or all of its artefacts, the turn of the millennium brought concerted attempts to synthesise what was known so far <esp:ref referent="reade1982"/>, <esp:ref referent="russell1999"/>,<esp:ref referent="reade2002"/>, <esp:ref referent="englund2003"/>. David and Joan Oates’ landmark book <i>Nimrud: an Imperial City Revealed</i> of 2001 was the first major retrospective <esp:ref referent="oatesoates2001"/>. It was not so much a history of Kalhu as a description of what had been found at Mallowan’s Nimrud. Nevertheless, it was the first accessible overview of the site and a chance to salvage data that would have otherwise been lost. The text is tinted with nostalgia for late monarchy Iraq, for the authors’ youth and their early love. </p>

<p>In early 2002, as the UN sanctions regime seemed to be easing, the BSAI convened an international conference on Nimrud at the British Museum <esp:ref referent="curtisetal2008"/>. Iraqi archaeologists presented their research on the royal women's tombs while British and international colleagues evaluated past excavations and outlined new research agendas. It felt like the beginning of a new era – but just twelve months later the <esp:techterms term="Iraq War">Iraq War</esp:techterms> broke out.</p>

<esp:reading referent="curtisetal2008"/>
<esp:reading referent="george2012"/>
<esp:reading referent="oatesoates2001"/>

<esp:author first-names="Eleanor" last-name="Robson"/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/>
<esp:content-last-modified/>


	</body></html>

</esp:page>
