<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

	<esp:name>Ancient Kalhu</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Ancient Kalhu</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>
	
<p class="firstpara">For almost two centuries, from the early 9th to
the late 8th century BC, the city of Kalhu was the centre of the
world's mightiest empire. In the popular imagination Assyria is
rightly acknowledged as being a very impressive military power. But
even the best-equipped army cannot succeed without effective,
intelligent leadership. Expert knowledge—of imperial administration, of the natural world,
of the gods' intentions for Assyria—all contributed to the Assyrian
king's ability to rule his territories. In these pages we consider the
places, peoples, and writings that supported Kalhu's world dominance
for such a long period of time.</p>

<esp:h><esp:link page="ancientcity">The ancient Assyrian royal city of
Kalhu:</esp:link></esp:h> 
<esp:sh>History and geography</esp:sh>

<p>Kalhu served as the capital of the Assyrian empire for nearly 200
years, from the early 9th to the late 8th century BC, but was also
inhabited for many centuries before and after. In this section of the
site we trace its history from prehistoric settlement to the
Hellenistic period and beyond. We also look at the key buildings,
inhabited by both people and gods, in which Assyrian imperial
knowledge was created and communicated.</p>

<esp:h><esp:link page="people">The people involved in producing
knowledge in ancient Kalhu:</esp:link></esp:h> 
<esp:sh>Kings, deities, scholars and
administrators</esp:sh>

<p>Many different types of people were involved in thinking and
writing about the world in the Assyrian royal court. The king looked
to his <esp:techterms term="scholar">scholars</esp:techterms> for advice, ritual and healing. The scholars
themselves depended on the king for continued patronage and
favour. Senior administrators and scribes recorded the king's words
and composed letters and inscriptions on his behalf. The gods
announced their favour or disfavour through ominous signs and
revelations, which had to be interpreted and responded to.</p>

<esp:h><esp:link page="langscripts">Writing practices in ancient
Kalhu:</esp:link></esp:h> 
<esp:sh>Languages, scripts, media and genres</esp:sh>

<p>Assyria in the first millennium BC was a diverse country made up of
peoples from all parts of the empire. This section explores the
principal languages and scripts which were spoken and written in
Assyria, and the contexts in which they were used. It also provides
links to teaching resources on the Akkadian language and cuneiform
script.</p>

<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/>

	</body></html>

</esp:page>
