<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

	<esp:name>Catalogues</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Catalogues</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>
	
<p class="firstpara">Objects excavated from Nimrud are now housed in
collections all over the world. One day it will be possible, we hope,
to provide integrated online access to all that material. That
ambition is far beyond the scope of this small project. As a first
step, we provide several different portals to currently available
data. We welcome additions and corrections to this information.</p>

<esp:h><esp:link page="niod">Nimrud Inscribed Objects Database</esp:link></esp:h>
<p>A catalogue of inscribed objects from Nimrud created by Christopher
Walker and a group of volunteers at the <esp:techterms term="British Museum">British Museum</esp:techterms> and released
under a <esp:link page="copyright">Creative Commons Attribution Share-Alike license</esp:link>. You can link
to individual
pages using stable URLs, as described in the <esp:link page="niod">NIOD help page</esp:link>.</p>

<esp:h><esp:link page="nvtc">Nimrud Virtual Text Corpus</esp:link></esp:h>
<p>This corpus brings together all the textual content from Nimrud on
text corpus projects hosted by Oracc, including the <esp:link
url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Corpus of Ancient Mesopotamian
Scholarship</esp:link>; the <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/dccmt/"
rel="external" hide-print="yes">Digital Corpus of Cuneiform Lexical Texts</esp:link>; the <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/rinap/" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Royal Inscriptions of the
Neo-Assyrian Period</esp:link>; and the <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/" rel="external" hide-print="yes">State Archives of
Assyria online</esp:link>.</p>

<esp:h><esp:link page="museumsuk">Museums in the UK holding objects from Nimrud</esp:link></esp:h>
<p>We have compiled a list of 11 UK museums that hold material from
Nimrud and have provided links to online catalogue information where
available. We also give more detailed information on selected museums
that we have worked with particularly closely.</p>

<esp:h><esp:link page="museumsworldwide">Museums and collections worldwide holding objects
from Nimrud</esp:link></esp:h>
<p>We have compiled a list of museums and collections from 20
countries worldwide that hold material from
Nimrud and have provided links to online catalogue information where
available. Three Google Maps show how widely scattered the Nimrud
artefacts now are.</p>

<esp:h><esp:link page="resources">Online resources</esp:link></esp:h>
<p>In this section we have collected together a large number of online
publications on Nimrud: free PDFs from project partners <esp:techterms
term="British Institute for the Study of Iraq">BISI</esp:techterms>; books and articles
available on <esp:link url="http://www.jstor.org/" rel="external" hide-print="yes">JSTOR</esp:link> and other repositories (some of which are
subscription-only); and other websites.</p> 

<esp:content-last-modified/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/>
	</body></html>

</esp:page>
