<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
	<esp:name>Agatha Christie at Nimrud</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Agatha Christie at Nimrud</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>

<p class="firstpara">Crime writer Agatha Christie participated in archaeological life at Nimrud during the 1950s. She accompanied her husband Max Mallowan on all of his excavations and played her part in registering finds and photographing the site. She also famously cleaned some of the ivories with her face-cream.</p>

<p>Agatha Christie married Max Mallowan, an archaeologist from London University, in 1930. The two had met on the archaeological site at Ur, where the 25-year-old Max was an assistant on the dig and Agatha was an enthusiastic visitor. The Mallowans went on excavation together in the Near East throughout the 1930s, beginning in northern Iraq at Nineveh and Arpachiyah, and then on to Syria and the sites of Chagar Bazar and Tell Brak. When Max was appointed to lead the BSAI excavations at Nimrud from 1949, his wife Agatha accompanied him on the digs.</p>

<esp:sh>Crime fiction and artefact cleaning</esp:sh>

<p>Agatha was present at all of Max's digging seasons at Nimrud, continuing with her writing while out in the field. She completed her book <i>They Came to Baghdad</i> (1951) at the BSAI house in Baghdad and from around 1952 had her own room built onto the Nimrud dig house, where she could read and write in peace. Agatha describes this room in her autobiography, which she began writing while at Nimrud:</p>

<blockquote><p>[QUOTE FROM CHRISTIE 1977; check permission/licensing]<br/>
"I petitioned to be allowed to have a small room added of my own. This I would pay for myself. So for £50, I built on a small, square, mud-brick room, and it was there that I began writing this book. It had a window, a table, an upright chair, and the collapsed remains of [an armchair] so decrepit it was difficult to sit on, but still comfortable. ... On the door, Donald Wiseman, one of our epigraphists, fixed the placard in cuneiform, which announces that this is the Beit Agatha - Agatha's House, and in Agatha's house I went every day to do a little of my own work."<esp:ref referent="christie1977" page="524-525"/></p></blockquote>

<p>Yet Agatha's time at Nimrud was not only spent on writing: she also participated fully in archaeological life. Her contributions included registering newly-excavated finds, typing the field catalogue, taking and developing photographs of the site.<esp:ref referent="djw1976"/> Agatha also cleaned some of the ivories that had been discovered at Nimrud, including the famous 'Mona Lisa' of Nimrud. She describes removing the dirt from the ivories with “an orange stick, a very fine knitting needle… a dentist’s tool… and a jar of cosmetic face-cream, which I found more useful than anything else for gently coaxing the dirt out of the crevices”<esp:ref referent="christie1977" page="457"/>.</p>

<esp:sh>Solving an Assyrian jigsaw puzzle</esp:sh>

<p>Agatha Christie is also credited with solving the puzzle of one of Nimrud’s most challenging artefacts. She pieced together hundreds of fragments of ivory found down a well in the North West Palace, which were revealed to be rare examples of Assyrian <esp:link page="xxxxx"> writing boards</esp:link>.</p>

<p>While <esp:link page="xxxxx">excavating well AB in the North West Palace in 195XX</esp:link>, Max Mallowan’s team discovered hundreds of burnt ivory fragments. These rare survivals had been preserved within the sludge at the well bottom. According to archaeologists David Oates and Joan Oates, the pieces were “flat and undecorated except for shallow cross-hatched incisions on the flat surfaces and occasional raised edging. Some fragments also bore the impressions of hinges." ." It was not obvious to the team, at first, what these pieces were, or whether they were important. The broken fragments “constituted a jigsaw puzzle of impossible intricacy, since there were no designs to aid reconstruction, only the raised edges of some of the pieces, but these all looked alike."<esp:ref referent="oatesoates2001" page="97"/></p>

<p>The team brought the fragments into the dig house, and spread them out to dry across all of the available the tables in the house – including the dinner table. Some people presumed the task of assembling them impossible, but Agatha persevered with piecing them together. By the end of the season she had demonstrated that they were rectangular boards with hinges. In antiquity these <esp:link page="xxxx">hinged writing boards</esp:link> contained a layer of wax (small traces still remained), and cuneiform signs were pressed into the wax surface using a <esp:techterms term="stylus">stylus</esp:techterms>.</p> 

<p>Listen to archaeologist Joan Oates, who dug at Nimrud with the Mallowans, describe how Agatha assembled the ivory fragments into writing boards.</p> 

<blockquote><p>[AUDIO CLIP: audio to be compiled. Permission needed from Joan Oates.]<br/>
“All of the pieces of these writing boards came out of the same well. There were thousands of them. And of course they were wet, and they had to be dried slowly. … We knew that it was ivory—burnt ivory. And, there was the one with the bit with the writing on it -- that was quite easy to put together.
All of us were saying, you know, what are we going to do? Well, let's just put one together and throw the rest away. Because they were tiny little pieces. And they came into the house, and in order to dry them, they had to go on all the tables. Well, we were working on all the tables, and then there was a table we ate on. And that table was covered. Everything -- the whole house was covered. And most of us were muttering in the background, but Agatha was absolutely delighted. Now this, was a puzzle.
She was a good mathematician, just in terms of using numbers around (interviewer: yes), and something like this... she absolutely was excited about. And, by the end of the season, she had put one of those together. Now, none of the rest of us could have done that (interviewer: yes)—we wouldn't have had the patience. But it was just her sort of thing. A real puzzle. So it's entirely her work."<br/>
(1m30s)</p></blockquote>

<p>The ivory writing boards from well AB are now held in the Ashmolean Museum, Oxford; British Museum, London; Iraq Museum, Baghdad; and Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York.</p>


<esp:sh>Supporting excavation work</esp:sh>

<p>In addition to helping with archaeological tasks, Agatha supported the digs in other ways. She directly contributed funding through several anonymous donations and even donated the manuscript of one of her books, <i>A Pocket Full of Rye</i> (1953), to the BSAI <esp:ref referent="christie1953"/>. The royalty payments from this publication helped to finance five years of archaeological work, including the Nimrud excavations <esp:ref referent="mccall2001" page="192-193"/> <esp:ref referent="djw1976" page="i"/>.</p>

<p>Agatha’s fame also served as a means for supporting the excavation. Max Mallowan borrowed significant amount of equipment from the Iraq Petroleum Company, such as winching and lifting equipment for excavating wells and moving earth. In return for this generosity, Iraq Petroleum Company engieers and their wives came for tea with Agatha at the dig site.</p>

<p>Joan Oates describes how Iraq Petroleum Company engineers loaned equipment in return for a visit to see Agatha.</p>

 <blockquote><p>[AUDIO CLIP: audio to be compiled. Permission needed from Joan Oates.]<br/>
"Max borrowed enormous quantities of equipment from the Iraq Petroleum Company, which was an English company. The penalty, was that the wives of the engineers, who were lending Max all of this wonderful equipment …wanted to see Agatha. So on a Friday they would send a message, sometimes it got there and sometimes it didn't, and they would bring food with them, so they would come for a lunch on Friday. And the whole point of the exercise was the wives wanted to see Agatha."</p></blockquote>

<p>IMAGES: [Photo: Oates &amp; Oates 2001, 178. IPC winching equipment 1962.]</p>


<p>Agatha Christie’s autobiography gives a flavour of life at Nimrud <esp:ref referent="christie1977"/> and her earlier experiences of archaeological life in Syria are recounted in her book <i>Come, Tell Me How You Live</i> (1946) <esp:ref referent="christiemallowan1975"/>.</p>



<!--<esp:image file="XXXXXX.jpg" description="XXXXXXX" position="float" grid="pc30"><esp:caption>XXXXXXXXX <esp:link url="XXXXXXXXXX" rel="external">Some link if necessary.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>-->

<esp:reading referent="christie1977" page="456-458, 521-529"/>
<esp:reading referent="christiemallowan1975"/>
<esp:reading referent="mallowan1977"/>
<esp:reading referent="mccall2001" page="152-178"/>
<esp:reading referent="trumpler2001a"/>
<esp:reading referent="trumpler2008"/>

<esp:author first-names="Ruth" last-name="Horry"/>

<p><small>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/></small></p>

	</body></html>

</esp:page>
