<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
	<esp:name>Excavations BSAI</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Excavations at Nimrud by the British School of Archaeology in Iraq (BSAI), 1949-1963</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>

<p class="firstpara">The British School of Archaeology in Iraq (BSAI) undertook thirteen seasons of excavations at Nimrud between 1949 and 1963, at the site of Kalhu, the administrative capital city of Assyria in the 9th and 8th centuries BC. Each digging season lasted two-months in the late spring and was a large undertaking, involving a team of archaeologists and up to two hundred local workers.</p>

<p>BSAI excavations up to 1957 were directed by Max Mallowan (1874-1978), an archaeologist from London University, who was <esp:link page="excavations-bsai-christie">accompanied each year by his wife</esp:link>, the renowned crime writer Agatha Christie (1890-1976). David Oates (1927-2004) took over as Field Director for the excavations between 1958-1962 and Jeffery Orchard oversaw the final season in 1963. In the early seasons the BSAI team excavated the citadel of Nimrud, beginning with the <esp:link page="northwestpalace">North West Palace of Assurnaṣirpal II</esp:link>, which had been previously dug by Austen Henry Layard during the nineteenth century. Later digging seasons were focused on the royal arsenal building, now known as <esp:link page="fortshalmaneser">Fort Shalmaneser</esp:link>.</p>

<p>Many thousands of objects were unearthed within the ancient palaces, temples and houses of Kalhu. Artefacts excavated by BSAI now reside in at least 26 museum collections across the world, with the most spectacular pieces housed in the Iraq Museum, Baghdad. The discoveries from the BSAI excavations ranged from impressive royal monuments to small everyday objects comprising the physical remains of palace life, as well as cuneiform tablets containing official correspondence of the Assyrian kings. Perhaps the most well-known finds, though, are the thousands of pieces of carved ivory, often known collectively as the Nimrud ivories, which were hoarded within Fort Shalmaneser’s storerooms. The archaeological work has increased academics’ understanding of the city of Kalhu and its inhabitants.</p>

<esp:sh>Excavating at Nimrud</esp:sh>

<p>During thirteen seasons of excavation, the BSAI team excavated numerous palaces, buildings and temples, including the North West Palace, the Burnt Palace (also known as the South East Palace), the city governor’s residence, the temple of the god Nabu, and Fort Shalmaneser, the royal arsenal. Much of the specialist work, including tracing mud-brick walls, was carried out by skilled Sharqati workmen from the district of Assur. Sharqati men built their own houses using mud-bricks and could identify the features of ancient mud-brick walls easily.</p>

<p>As well as recording the positions of walls and building structures, the team also unearthed a wealth of artefacts. Each find that was to be kept was allocated a unique identification number, which was prefixed with ‘ND’ for Nimrud (see <b>Image X</b>). Each item was then recorded and described in the field catalogue. These excavation numbers, or ‘Nimrud numbers’ as they have become known, have become important in tracing Nimrud material that has been dispersed to museum collections across the world.</p>

<esp:image file="XXXXXX.jpg" description="Pottery vessels, each inscribed in ink with an excavation number beginning with the letters 'ND'." position="float"><esp:caption>Pottery vessels from BSAI excavations at Nimrud showing the excavation number, also known as a 'Nimrud number', marked on each one. This unique number, prefixed with 'ND', is used to keep track of every find from the excavation. The numbers have since become important for tracing Nimrud material that has been dispersed to museum collections worldwide. Pottery vessels [NDXXXX, NDXXXX etc.] are now housed in the <esp:link url="http://maa.cam.ac.uk/maa/" rel="external">Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology</esp:link>, University of Cambridge (MAA ACCESSION NUMBERS).</esp:caption></esp:image>

<esp:sh>'Rows of feet' in the North West Palace</esp:sh>
<p>Between 1950-53 the team excavated parts of the North West Palace of Assurnasirpal II, greatly extending the known extent of the building. Traces of Layard’s nineteenth-century expeditions could be seen in the Palace; his workmen had previously removed large quantities of stone reliefs from the North West Palace and left dumps of earth which the BSAI excavation had to dig through. Some reliefs bore chisel marks where Layard had attempted to remove them, but abandoned the attempt mid-way through.</p>

<p>[Image: king’s head with chisel marks round it, same image as ILN 29 July 1950, 183. OR Oates &amp; Oates 2001, 46, showing NWP throne room as re-excavated by Mallowan.]</p>

<p>Archaeologist Joan Oates excavated at Nimrud between 1952 and 1963(?). She describes seeing the remnants of genie reliefs, which Layard's team had removed from the North West Palace, with just a row of feet left behind:</p>

<blockquote><p>[AUDIO CLIP: audio to be compiled. Permission needed from Joan Oates.]<br/>
"We tried to avoid… wasting money, and time, just to go back and dig where somebody else has dug, and taken everything away probably. But we did do a clean-up of the façade of the throne room of the North West Palace. ... There is quite a lot of the North West Palace, Assurnasirpal’s palace at Nimrud, where … the slabs are in the British Museum, but if you look at them, the feet aren’t there. And if you start cleaning along that wall at Nimrud, there’s about <i>this</i> much [<i>gestures c.50cm</i>] of the bottom of the stone. And the feet are there. …  – I think I have a couple of pictures, of feet. Nothing but feet."</p></blockquote>

<esp:sh>Treasure thrown down palace wells</esp:sh>

<p>The BSAI team discovered three deep wells within the rooms of the North West Palace. One proved too dangerous and remained unexplored until Iraqi excavators made it safe in 1975. Mallowan’s team did manage to excavate the other two wells, which each contained a treasure trove of objects. Among them were some of the most well-preserved and significant artefacts ever found at Nimrud.</p>

<p>The team came across a deep well in the corner of room NN of the North West Palace in April 1951. It was lined with burnt bricks to a depth of around 25 metres and some of the bricks were stamped with king Assurnasirpal's name. Excavating the well was difficult and dangerous at first, as rising water from the river Tigris entered faster than the team could remove it. The attempt was abandoned until the following year, when Mallowan's team returned armed with heavy-duty winching equipment borrowed from the Iraq Petroleum Company.</p>

<p>The well shaft was full of what Mallowan described as a "belt of rich sludge, of the consistency of plaster of Paris".(1) In the later stages of digging, water was drawn out each night, which allowed the well-workers to extract the sludge during the day. Sludge was scooped out into an oil drum by a man at the well bottom, and drawn up using the winch. The dense sludge itself contained many remarkable surprises: it provided ideal conditions for preserving materials that would otherwise have decayed, such as fragments of Assyrian rope and wooden well equipment. A remarkable haul of artefacts were found down palace well NN, having been thrown down there in antiquity - perhaps by invaders ransacking the building. The artefacts included fragments of beautifully carved ivory, shell ornaments, pieces of horse harnesses, and a group of bronze dog figurines. Most famous among the ivory pieces was a finely carved ivory female head, nicknamed the ‘Mona Lisa’ of Nimrud by Dr Naji al Asil, the director-general of Iraqi antiquities, and which gained much publicity on the front page of the <i>Illustrated London News</i> on 16 August 1952 <esp:ref referent="mallowan1966" page="260"/><esp:ref referent="iln1952-08-16" page="1"/>.</p>

<p>A second well, discovered in room AB, also contained remarkable finds. It was excavated by Hassan Abdullah, a highly experienced Sharqati workman who had worked previously with Walter Andrae in 1913. Large numbers of wood and burnt ivory fragments were discovered at a depth of around 22m. The ivory pieces were assembled by Agatha Christie and were later revealed to be a group of ivory writing boards, a rare survival that had been preserved in the well-bottom sludge. Shortly after the writing boards were recovered, the bottom of this well also collapsed and had to be abandoned. Nimrud archaeologists David and Joan Oates describe the danger involved:</p>

<blockquote><p>“The excavation of the well involved descending literally in a bucket, and sending up the well sludge, which contained the objects, in a second bucket, with two workmen operating the pulley at the top. A pre-arranged signal of two short pulls was to indicate danger, and a quick ascent…; fortunately the workmen on the pulley were fully focused when the signal came, and [Hassan Abdullah] rose to the surface just as the sides of the well below crashed in.”<esp:ref referent="oatesoates2001" page="99-100"/></p></blockquote>

<esp:sh>Hoarded war booty in Fort Shalmaneser</esp:sh>

<p>During the 1957 season, the team began excavating a building now known to be the royal arsenal of king Shalmaneser III, now known as ‘Fort Shalmaneser’.  Within its rooms the excavators uncovered vast quantities of ivory carvings. Almost 1600 pieces of ivory were discovered in the largest storeroom (SW37) alone, mixed with mudbrick debris and heaped up to a height of almost two metres <esp:ref referent="mallowanhermann1974"/><esp:ref referent="hermann1986a"/> <esp:ref referent="hermann1986b"/>. These ivory elements are the remains of furniture, which was most likely broken in antiquity, perhaps acquired as loot from Sargon II’s imperial conquests <esp:ref referent="parkermallowan1986"/>. Mallowan’s team took almost four years to excavate Fort Shalmaneser in its entirety.</p>


<esp:sh>The 'division' of finds</esp:sh>

<p>At the end of each digging season, all of the excavated objects were reviewed by members of the Iraq Department of Antiquities in a process known by the archaeologists as ‘the division’. The most important and unique artefacts were all designated for the Iraq Museum in Baghdad, and the remaining finds were sorted into trays, categorised by type of object. In Agatha Christie’s words, “any ‘duplicates’, as they were called, would be divided up and the excavator would get a fair share.” [Ref: Christie 1977, 521]. Artefacts were divided up into trays containing comparable material. The trays were laid out in the dig house and scrutinised by a delegation from the Iraqi Antiquities Authority, led by the Director-General. The Director-General would select one tray to remain in Iraq at the Baghdad museum, and the comparable tray would be gifted to the BSAI excavation.</p>

<p>Archaeologist Joan Oates describes the process of the division:</p>

<blockquote><p>[AUDIO CLIP: audio to be compiled. Permission needed from Joan Oates]<br/>
"What happens each year is that you have this division. ... Normally this would have taken place in the museum [in Baghdad] but there was so much stuff coming out at Nimrud …that the officials came from Baghdad up to Nimrud for the division. … Every room in the [dig] house had a table that had... trays by each other: <i>this</i> one with cylinder seals and <i>this</i> one with cylinder seals, and the [Baghdad] museum could choose which of these they wanted to take themselves. All of the unique or really interesting things went straight to the [Baghdad] museum, … there was no question about that. But we found so much. We had to use something like three rooms with tables out. … Each double tray... meant one of them [was] to go to the [Baghdad] museum and one of them [was] to go to us.”</p></blockquote>


<esp:sh>Gifting artefacts to museums</esp:sh>

<p>The share of artefacts allocated to BSAI after each division each season sent to London and housed temporarily in London University’s Institute of Archaeology. Once there, the finds were photographed, and some were repaired by conservators. A portion of these artefacts remained within the Institute, but the rest were further distributed as gifts to institutions, either universities or museums, that had donated money for that season’s digging. Each year, artefacts from Nimrud were sent from London to museums worldwide.</p>

<p>Joan Oates describes the gifting of artefacts to museums:</p> 

<blockquote><p>[AUDIO CLIP: audio to be compiled. Permission needed from Joan Oates.]<br/>
"After the division at Nimrud, the half that came to the English expedition was packed in cases and shipped back to England. … The Institute did quite a lot of repairing, and, you know, ‘faking up’ of the pottery. Which made it look a lot nicer in a museum when it was sent. Max was getting money from somewhere in Australia, from San Francisco, from the Metropolitan Museum, from the British Museum. … Most museums were very happy to get things from Nimrud, and hand over a little money. You gave the money for the dig, and then you waited to see what you were going to get for it. And with something like Nimrud, where Max had between 200 and 300 workmen, you were going to find something somewhere! Well, that was Max’s idea! … They had no idea in advance what they were going to get, but with a site like Nimrud it was a good guess that they would find something that they would like to put on display."</p></blockquote>

<p>While individual museums had no knowledge of what type of objects would be gifted to them, the sheer quantity of material emerging from Nimrud made it likely that each institution would receive suitable material for display. Museums that gave money each season and became major funders of the excavation acquired large collections of objects.</p>


<esp:sh>Publicity and funding</esp:sh>

<p>Mallowan's team could only dig at Nimrud each season if enough money was secured.  Agatha Christie noted that money was "not much to start with" but "as our finds grew, it increased".<esp:ref referent="christie1977" page="522"/> As large numbers of signigicant finds emerged, several major museums and universities donated money in return for gifts of artefacts.</p>

<p>Success in attracting funding also depended on Mallowan's ability to publicise the discoveries. Mallowan allowed visitors onto the dig site as a means of raising the profile of the excavations. Agatha Christie describes how visitors became increasingly frequent in later seasons, including at one point “whole charabancs of school-children” <esp:ref referent="christie1977" page="526-527"/>. Some visitors were major funders to the digs, such as the owners of Penguin Books, who visited in April 1951 <esp:ref referent="mallowan1977" page="288-289"/>.</p>

<p>Mallowan was also a skilled publicist of his team's discoveries. As well as producing yearly excavation reports in academic journal <i>Iraq</i>, he authored a series of articles for a wider readership in the <i>Illustrated London News</i>. These articles presented the latest discoveries about Assyrian civilization made at Nimrud and interpreted artefacts in an engaging and accessible way. Many of his identifications and descriptions of particular artefacts have remained in circulation to the present day.</p>

<p>Among the discoveries featured in the newspaper was what Mallowan described as “the largest and finest carved ivory head ever found in the ancient Near East", found down well NN in the North West Palace. The ivory female head appeared on the front cover, at natural size, on 16 August 1952 <esp:ref referent="iln1952-08-16" page="1"/>. Mallowan captioned the photograph as the ‘Mona Lisa’ of Nimrud, using the nickname given by the Director-General of Iraqi antiquities. This famous object - now in the Metropolitan Museum, New York - is still known by this nickname today.</p>

<p>Mallowan had witnessed the benefits of publicising expedition results as a young man working under Leonard Woolley at the site of Ur in the 1920s. Woolley had ensured that the most spectacular finds, such gold and lapis lazuli jewellery from the royal graves, were regularly featured in the <i>Illustrated London News</i> <esp:ref referent="mccall2001" page="46-51, 72"/>. The newspaper had first presented Layard's findings at Nimrud and Nineveh to the British public in the 1850s, and continued to do so a century later.</p> 

<p>As public appetite for Nimrud discoveries increased, Mallowan secured financial supp ort from museums that were interested in acquiring and displaying Nimrud material.</p>

<esp:sh>Museums holding Nimrud material from BSAI excavation</esp:sh>

<p>Around 26 museums worldwide now hold Nimrud artefacts from the BSAI excavations.  The largest collection is held in the Iraq Museum, Baghdad. In the UK, the largest collection is held by the British Museum, London, followed by the Ashmolean Museum, Oxford, the Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology, Cambridge, and Birmingham Museum and Art Gallery. Worldwide, the Metropolitan Museum, New York also has a significant collection.</p>


<p><object type="text/html" width="425" height="350" data="https://maps.google.co.uk/maps/ms?msid=204599863567827172960.0004efb545a81189b870c&amp;msa=0&amp;z=1&amp;output=embed">
</object></p>

<p><esp:link url="https://maps.google.co.uk/maps/ms?msid=204599863567827172960.0004efb545a81189b870c&amp;msa=0" rel="external">View larger version of map using Google Maps</esp:link><br/>
<esp:link url="bsai-museums-nimrud.kml" title="Map showing museums worldwide with Nimrud material from BSAI excavations, 1949-1963">Download map content to view using Google Earth or re-use within your own custom maps (KML file, 21 KB)</esp:link></p>

<p>Compiling a list of museums that hold Nimrud objects from the BSAI excavations has been made possible using documentation held by individual museums, and data compiled by Christopher Walker. Tracing the movement and final location of individual objects, though, is a more difficult task. The original field records have never been published, and were not intended to record that information. The Nimrud project cannot aim to trace each individual object, but instead has studied the dispersal through particular case studies.</p>

<p>Our research has shown that groups or sets of similar objects were often separated in the division and subsequent dispersal by BSAI, for example, a group of <esp:link page="xxxxx">bronze dog figurines</esp:link> found together down a well in room NN of the North West Palace. One of each type of object was gifted to a major donor museum, ensuring that representative objects were shared out. While this practice ensured that different museums had material to display, the wide dispersal has since made studying Nimrud objects challenging.</p>

 <!-- could add / swap example of apkallu figurines found in foundation box: ie meant to be a set, not just a group found in same locus. See notes. -->

<!--<esp:image file="XXXXXX.jpg" description="XXXXXXX" position="float" grid="pc30"><esp:caption>XXXXXXXXX <esp:link url="XXXXXXXXXX" rel="external">Some link if necessary.</esp:link></esp:caption></esp:image>-->

<esp:reading referent="mallowan1952"/>
<esp:reading referent="mallowan1977"/>
<esp:reading referent="mccall2001" page="152-178"/>
<esp:reading referent="mccall2008"/>
<esp:reading referent="oatesoates2001" page="90-100"/>


<esp:author first-names="Ruth" last-name="Horry" />

<p><small>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/></small></p>

	</body></html>

</esp:page>