<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	
	<esp:name>Technical terms</esp:name>
	
	<esp:title>Technical terms</esp:title>
	
	<html>
		<head></head>
		<body>
		<p class="firstpara">These are the technical terms used in this website.</p>
		
			<esp:techterms-list>

<!-- EXAMPLE OF CROSS REFERENCING <esp:termsdefinition term="zikurudani">Literally "throat-cutting", a magical <esp:techterms term="Rite, ritual">ritual</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition> -->


<!-- A -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="acetone">Chemical compound, formula
(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CO, used in museum conservation work as a
solvent, to remove dirt and unwanted material from the surface of
archaeological artefacts.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Achaemenid">Term for the Persian dynasty
and empire that ruled Babylonia (and the region from the <esp:glossary term="Indus (place)">Indus</esp:glossary> Valley
to western Turkey),
539–330 BC. Named after their founding ancestor Achaemenes (r.705–675 BC).</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="acropolis">Greek word meaning "top of the
city"; used by some archaeologists to describe the large
<esp:techterms term="citadel">citadel</esp:techterms> mound at
Nimrud and other Assyrian sites.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="acrylic paint">Type of synthetic paint
which can be diluted with water but is water-resistant when dry. Used
in museum conservation work to cover modern restorations of
archaeological artefacts so that they blend in with them but can still
be distinguished from the original.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="akītu">[1] New Year festival, performed
over 11 days at the spring equinox, and featuring the gods'
renewal of the king's right to rule. [2] Also the name of a temple
outside the walls of a city, in which part of the <i>akītu</i>
festival was performed. King <esp:link page="sennacherib">Sennacherib</esp:link> built an <i>akītu</i> temple for
the god <esp:link page="ashur">Aššur</esp:link> just outside
<esp:glossary term="Assur (place)">Assur</esp:glossary>. [3] At Kalhu,
an annual <esp:techterms term="sacred marriage">sacred
marriage</esp:techterms> <esp:techterms term="rite,
ritual">ritual</esp:techterms> for <esp:link
page="nabu">Nabu</esp:link> and <esp:glossary term="Tašmetu (deity)">Tašmetu</esp:glossary>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Akkadian"><esp:techterms term="Semitic language">Semitic
language</esp:techterms> of ancient
Mesopotamia, conventionally divided into two dialects: Assyrian from the
north and Babylonian from the south. It was usually written in the
<esp:techterms term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> script. See the <esp:link
page="langscripts">writing practices</esp:link> section for
more details.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="alabaster">Term for the type of light
grey stone
used for the <esp:techterms term="bas-relief">relief sculptures</esp:techterms> in Assyrian palaces, a form of calcium carbonate, formula
CaCO<sub>3</sub>. It is also known as
<esp:glossary term="Mosul (place)">Mosul</esp:glossary> marble because it was quarried from local deposits.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="amulet">Object thought to have healing powers, often with an image or inscription on it, and usually worn round the neck or attached to a person's clothes.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Anglo-Iraqi Treaty">Signed in 1948. The final one of three treaties between the United Kingdom and Iraq, the first signed in 1922, which were nominally declarations of alliance. In fact they gave a great deal of power to the UK, especially in matters of foreign relations, military planning, and natural resources such as oil. Despite a great deal of Iraqi opposition, the final treaty remained in force from 1948 to the end of the Iraqi monarchy in 1958.</esp:termsdefinition>


<esp:termsdefinition term="apkallu"><esp:techterms
term="Akkadian">Akkadian</esp:techterms> word for "sage". Depending on context, refers to [1]
one of the mythical <esp:techterms term="sage">Seven Sages</esp:techterms> or [2] a
winged <esp:techterms term="genie">genie</esp:techterms> carved on Assyrian palace
<esp:techterms term="bas-relief">reliefs</esp:techterms>. See also
<esp:techterms
    term="fish-man">fish-man</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="apsu">Mythical underground source of all fresh
water, abode of the god <esp:glossary term="Ea
(deity)">Ea</esp:glossary> and the <esp:techterms term="sage">Seven
Sages</esp:techterms>; origin of the English word abyss.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="anthropomorphic">Being of human form. Beginning sometime in the third millennium BC, gods were imagined as having human form, although so far no divine statue has survived the ages.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="antiquarianism">Literally, the study of antiquities. A precursor to modern archaeology, in which excavation is mostly seen as a means of recovering artefacts rather than as a source of useful data in itself. </esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="apotropaic">Preventative, designed to ward
off evil <esp:techterms term="demon">demons</esp:techterms> or
unfavourable events foretold by <esp:techterms term="omen">omens</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Aramaic"><esp:techterms term="Semitic language">Semitic
language</esp:techterms>, spoken originally of ancient Syria but which
spread all over the ancient Middle East as it was written in a
convenient <esp:link page="alphabetic">alphabetic script</esp:link>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="arsenal">Place where weapons are made,
stored, and/or issued, often used to describe <esp:link
page="fortshalmaneser">Fort Shalmaneser</esp:link> in
Kalhu.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="assemblage">Group of archaeological
artefacts found together in excavation, for instance, a collection of
tablets or vessels. Looking at assemblages can help archaeologists
understand the functions and values of individual objects as well as
the relationships between them, much better than studying them in
isolation.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Ashmolean Museum">The University of Oxford's
museum of
art and archaeology, founded in the 18th century to house the
collection of Elias Ashmole; a major recipient of artefacts from
Nimrud in the 1950s.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Assyrian Expedition Fund">Short-lived private venture set up in London to fund the archaeological work of <esp:glossary term="Loftus, William Kennett (person)">William Kennett Loftus</esp:glossary> in Assyria and Babylonia in 1853-4. It was seen as a rival to the British Museum's interests in the region and met with formidable opposition from <esp:glossary term="Rawlinson, Henry Creswicke (person)">Rawlinson</esp:glossary>.</esp:termsdefinition>


<esp:termsdefinition term="Assyriology">The academic study of
ancient Assyria, especially its history and languages; nowadays also
used to mean the study of all <esp:techterms term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> culture.</esp:termsdefinition>
<esp:termsdefinition term="astrologer"><esp:techterms term="scholar">Scholar</esp:techterms> responsible for
reading and interpreting <esp:techterms term="omen">omens</esp:techterms> from the positions of the stars,
planets, and other heavenly bodies, as well as the
weather.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="astrology">In Assyrian times,
<esp:techterms term="astrologer">astrologers</esp:techterms>  divined
the gods' intentions for the future of the state through observing the
movements of the heavenly bodies and reading celestial <esp:techterms
term="omen">omens</esp:techterms>  from them; they did not cast
personal horoscopes on the basis of a client's birth date. See the
page on <esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/saao/knpp/essentials/celestialterrestrialdivination/">celestial and terrestrial divination</esp:link> at the Knowledge and
Power website.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="augur"><esp:techterms term="scholar">Scholar</esp:techterms> who reads <esp:techterms
term="omen">omens</esp:techterms> from the flights of birds in the
sky. In Kalhu, all attested augurs were from kingdoms to the northwest
of Assyria.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="auspicious">Carrying a good <esp:techterms
term="omen">omen</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- B -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="backfill">At the end of the <esp:techterms term="excavation season">excavation season</esp:techterms> archaeologists re-fill their trenches with earth to preserve the finds that remain in situ and to prevent looting.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="bas-relief">Flat stone panel carved to
make the images on it stand slightly proud of their background. The
ceremonial spaces of Assyrian palaces were lined with <esp:techterms
term="alabaster">alabaster</esp:techterms> bas-reliefs depicting scenes of military victory,
kingly piety, and divine protection.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="beneficent">Kindly, doing good; often used
to describe <esp:techterms term="genie">genies</esp:techterms> and
other semi-divine beings. Its opposite is <esp:techterms term="maleficent">maleficent</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="bitumen">The heavier fractions of crude
oil, which in Assyrian times were collected from springs on the
<esp:glossary term="Euphrates (place)">Euphrates</esp:glossary> river,
and used for waterproofing, adhesive, medical, and ritual purposes.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="boss">Another word for knob or protrusion;
a feature of Assyrian shields and some architectural
styles.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="brazier">Metal vessel for burning fuel
for heating or <esp:techterms term="incense">incense</esp:techterms>
offerings.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="British Institute for the Study of Iraq">London-based charitable 
institute that promotes humanities and social science research and
education on all aspects of Iraq's history, culture, and
languages. Also known as <esp:link rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://www.bisi.ac.uk">BISI</esp:link>; successor to the <esp:techterms
term="British School of Archaeology in Iraq">British School of
Archaeology in Iraq</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="British Museum">Public museum in London,
which was founded in the 1750s and greatly expanded a century later. The museum sponsored <esp:glossary term="Layard, Austen Henry (person)">Layard</esp:glossary>'s explorations at Nimrud and
<esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary>
in the 1840s and has been at the forefront of research on ancient
Assyria ever since.</esp:termsdefinition>


<esp:termsdefinition term="British School of Archaeology in Iraq">Research organisation founded 1932 in memory of <esp:glossary term="Bell, Gertrude (person)">Gertrude
Bell</esp:glossary>; ran British excavations in Iraq until 1990,
including those directed by <esp:glossary term="Mallowan, Max (person)">Max Mallowan</esp:glossary> at Nimrud. Also known as
BSAI. Superceded by <esp:techterms term="British Institute for the
Study of Iraq">The British Institute for the Study of Iraq</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition> 

<esp:termsdefinition term="bronze">Hard, tough metal alloyed from
copper and tin. Used in Assyria for weapons, large vessels, and elements of horse harnesses.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="buff ware">Type of finely made unglazed pottery,
shaped into several different distinctive forms and
fired to a very pale brown ("buff") colour.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="byssus">Very fine and expensive type of
<esp:techterms
term="flax">linen</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- C -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="cartouche">In <esp:link page="hieroglyphs">hieroglyphic Egyptian inscriptions</esp:link>, a
royal name surrounded by an oval line and a straight line underneath
or to the left.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="cauldron">Large vessel suspended over an
open fire, for cooking or for heating liquids. In Assyrian times,
often made of <esp:techterms term="bronze">bronze</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="cedar">Cedar trees are native to the east
coast of the Mediterranean Sea, especially the area of the Lebanon
mountain range. The Assyrians prized this strong yet flexible wood for
building work.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="celestial">Of the skies or heavens, including (for the Assyrians) the weather.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="cella">The main shrine of a temple, where the statue of the god stood.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="chalcedony">Semi-precious stone composed of
different types
quartz crystals, resulting in a wide range of colours, especially
greys and browns. Agate (dark brown and white bands) and carnelian (a
solid red) are both varieties of
chalcedony. All were favoured materials for <esp:techterms
term="seal, sealing">seals</esp:techterms> in Assyrian
times.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="citadel">Fortified area of a city, in
Assyrian times often on a high mound, where the royal palaces, elite
residences and major palaces were built. Archaeologists sometimes use
the alternative term <esp:techterms
term="acropolis">acropolis</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="clay hand">Architectural feature of
Assyrian palaces and temples in the shape of a larger-than-life fist with curled up fingers, made
of baked clay and sometimes inscribed in <esp:techterms
term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms>. May have been used to support beams or as
decorative <esp:techterms term="boss">bosses</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="colophon">Note at the end of a <esp:link page="scholarlyworks">scholarly
work</esp:link>, giving information such as the <esp:techterms term="scribe">scribe</esp:techterms> and/or owner
of the tablet, the date and place of writing or copying, and/or the
reason it was made.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="colossal bull">Huge <esp:techterms
term="alabaster">alabaster</esp:techterms> statue of a
<esp:techterms term="beneficent">beneficent</esp:techterms> divine being, with a bull's body, human
head and large wings, placed on either side of a major entrance to an
Assyrian temple or palace. They have five legs so that they appear to
stand facing those that enter the gateway and walk out with those that
leave. At Kalhu alternative designs were lions and even fish at
<esp:link page="ezida">Nabu's temple</esp:link>.</esp:termsdefinition>	

<esp:termsdefinition term="composite">In modern editorial practice, a
text reconstructed from two or more ancient manuscripts to show how
the complete work may have looked originally.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="conservation">In modern archaeological and
museum practice, the work carried out on an ancient artefact to
protect and stabilise it so that it can withstand long-term storage,
public display, and handling by reearchers.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="conservator">Highly trained specialist technician in
the work of archaeological <esp:techterms
term="conservation">conservation</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="consul">Person charged to represent a country's diplomatic and commercial interests in a particular city or region, instead of, or reporting to, an ambassador.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="conveyance"><esp:link page="legaldocuments">Legal document</esp:link> recording the transfer of ownership of
a piece of land, whether through sale or inheritance.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="corn docket"><esp:link page="legaldocuments">Legal document</esp:link> recording a
debt of corn. These clay tablets have a distinctive triangular shape
and are moulded around a piece of string, possibly indicating they
were used to secure a piece of <esp:techterms term="parchment">parchment</esp:techterms>
(which no longer survives).</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Crimean War">Fought in 1853-56, between Russia on one side and an alliance of the <esp:techterms term="Ottoman">Ottoman</esp:techterms> empire, France and Great Britain on the other. It was nominally about the rights of Christians in the Ottoman-controlled "holy land" of the <esp:glossary term="Levant (place)">Levant</esp:glossary>, but more deeply about territorial control of the Middle East. The war put a halt to European explorations and excavations in the Middle East for several years.</esp:termsdefinition>


<esp:termsdefinition term="crown prince">Prince nominated by the
reigning king to succeed him, not necessarily his eldest son (or
indeed any son). See the page on the <esp:link rel="external"
hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/saao/knpp/essentials/royalfamily/">Assyrian royal family</esp:link> at the
Knowledge and Power website for more details.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="cultural heritage">Legacy of the past
considered worth preserving, from archaeological sites and ancient
artefacts to traditions of music and dance, regardless of its monetary
value.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="cuneiform">Complex system of writing made
of <esp:techterms term="wedge">wedge-shaped</esp:techterms> impressions, usually made by a
<esp:techterms term="stylus">stylus</esp:techterms> in the surface of a clay tablet or a
waxed <esp:techterms term="writing board">writing board</esp:techterms>. Cuneiform had many
hundreds of different signs, which could take on different meanings
depending on their context. See the <esp:link
page="langscripts">writing practices</esp:link> section for
more details.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="curator">Person in charge of a museum collection, or part of it, usually with specialist academic knowledge of the field.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="cursive">Written in informal script, as
opposed to monumental</esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- D -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="Da'esh/ISIS">Arabic and British English abbreviations respectively for the so-called Islamic State of Iraq and Syria, an extremist jihadi organisation which took control of much of northern Syria in 2013 and northern Iraq in 2014, including the area around Nimrud. Local people, and their <esp:techterms term="cultural heritage">cultural heritage</esp:techterms> and archaeology, have suffered terribly as a result. </esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Daily Telegraph">British newspaper, founded in 1855, which took a great interest in Assyrian archaeology in the first decades of its existence. in 1871 it sponsored an expedition to <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary> and Nimrud, headed by <esp:glossary term="Smith, George (person)">George Smith</esp:glossary>, to find further cuneiform evidence for the <esp:techterms term="Flood">Flood</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="date palm">Date palms were commonly
cultivated in <esp:glossary term="Babylonia
(place)">Babylonia</esp:glossary>, both for their very sweet fruit
(the syrup of which was used as a sweetener instead of the much rarer
honey) and for their fronds, fibres and trunks which all had practical
uses. Because the trees were hand-pollinated they became a symbol of
fertility. See also <esp:techterms term="sacred tree">sacred tree</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="day book">Technical diary used, for
instance, by archaeologists and <esp:techterms
term="conservator">conservators</esp:techterms> to record their work
day by day.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="demon">Demons were considered to be the
agents of death and illness. They were not fully under the control of
the gods, and could move easily between the divine and human
worlds. Many were visualised as being composed of body parts from a
variety of creatures. See also <esp:techterms
term="genie">genie</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="diachronic">Concerning change or sameness over time.</esp:termsdefinition>


<esp:termsdefinition term="diadem">Royal crown in the form of a highly
decorated band
that runs all the way round the head. </esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="dig house">On more remote archaeological sites,
the building(s) where the team lives and works on the objects it has excavated.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Director-General of Antiquities">Senior government official in charge of archaeology in Iraq, reporting to the <esp:techterms term="Ministry of Culture">Ministry of Culture</esp:techterms>. Their responsibility includes the management of Iraq's museums, local and international archaeological projects, and—before 1975—overseeing <esp:techterms term="division of finds">division of finds</esp:techterms>. In the <esp:techterms term="Mandate">Mandate</esp:techterms> era, the DGA was always British or European; since independence the post has always been held by an Iraqi.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="diviner"><esp:techterms term="scholar">Scholar</esp:techterms>  who reads the gods'
intentions from <esp:techterms term="omen">omens</esp:techterms>; see
also <esp:techterms term="astrologer">astrologer</esp:techterms>, <esp:techterms term="augur">augur</esp:techterms>,
<esp:techterms term="exorcist">exorcist</esp:techterms>, and <esp:techterms term="haruspex">haruspex</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="division of finds">Before Iraqi antiquities
law was amended in 1975, the <esp:techterms term="State Board of
Antiquities and Heritage">State Board of Antiquities and Heritage</esp:techterms>
agreed with archaeological teams at the end of each <esp:techterms
term="excavation season">season</esp:techterms> which
excavated objects belonged to the Iraqi state and which could remain
the property of the excavators and leave the country. Nowadays under
Iraqi law all antiquities are state property and cannot be exported.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="docket">Clay tablet which was originally
attached to another object, usually to serve as a label or <esp:link
page="legaldocuments">legal document</esp:link> of some kind. Holes
for string or the impressions of long-perished sealings are typical
features of dockets.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Drew Theological Seminary">Training college for future <esp:techterms term="Methodism">Methodist</esp:techterms> ministers in New Jersey; now Drew University.</esp:termsdefinition>


<!-- E -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="East India Company">British trading
company, founded in 1600, with a royally-granted monopoly on commerce with the
Indian subcontinent. It eventually became so thoroughly embroiled in
local governance and
politics that it was in practice a branch of the British goverment. It
had a <esp:techterms term="Residency">Resident</esp:techterms> in
<esp:glossary term="Basra (place)">Basra</esp:glossary> from 1763 and one in <esp:glossary term="Baghdad (place)">Baghdad</esp:glossary> from 1798, to
secure overland communication routes and protect against the
French. EIC officials such as <esp:glossary term="Rich, Claudius James
(person)">Claudius James Rich</esp:glossary> and <esp:glossary
term="Rawlinson, Henry Creswicke (person)">Henry Creswicke
Rawlinson</esp:glossary> also became involved in the rediscovery of Assyria. The EIC was effectively nationalised and dissolved after the
so-called Indian Mutiny of 1857. </esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="ecstatic">Some cultic personnel received messages from the gods not through the
observation or induction of omens  but through direct communication
while in a trance-like state. Ecstatic trances could be induced (for
instance by drugs or ritual  actions) but could also overwhelm any
individual unexpectedly. See also <esp:techterms term="prophet(ess)">prophet(ess)</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="emissary">Assyria exchanged diplomats with
its allies and <esp:techterms term="vassal">vassal</esp:techterms> states who represented their rulers at the
foreign court and acted as their representatives in
oath-taking ceremonies. They also accompanied the annual
<esp:techterms term="tribute">tribute</esp:techterms> due to the Assyrian king. The Assyrian term, <i>ṣīru</i>, literally means "excellency", reflecting the emissaries' high status.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Epic of Creation">The <i>Epic of Creation</i> existed in two forms. The <esp:glossary term="Babylonia (place)">Babylonian</esp:glossary> version describes how the heroic god <esp:glossary term="Marduk (deity)">Marduk</esp:glossary> defeated the monstrous sea <esp:glossary term="Tiamat (deity)">Tiamat</esp:glossary> and her evil army in a cosmic battle, created the world from her body, and thereby became head of the gods. The Assyrian version replaces Marduk with <esp:glossary term="Aššur (deity)">Aššur</esp:glossary>. It was performed on the fourth day of the <esp:techterms term="akītu"><i>akītu</i></esp:techterms>  festival.</esp:termsdefinition>


<esp:termsdefinition term="Enūma Anu Ellil">The standard series of
<esp:techterms term="celestial">celestial</esp:techterms>
<esp:techterms term="omen">omens</esp:techterms>,
named after its first line: literally "When the gods <esp:glossary
term="Anu (deity)">Anu</esp:glossary>, <esp:glossary term="Ellil
(deity)">Ellil</esp:glossary>  (and <esp:glossary term="Ea (deity)">Ea</esp:glossary>  established in council the plans of the sky and earth)".</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="epithet">Adjective or phrase which describes a person or event, usually in a positive or negative light.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="eponym">
    In the Assyrian empire, years  were not counted but named after
    the king, high officials and provincial governors. These people
    are collectively called eponym officials. <esp:techterms term="scribe">Scribes</esp:techterms>  maintained
    standard reference <esp:link hide-print="yes" rel="external" url="http://oracc.org/saao/aebp/eponymlistsandchronicles/">lists of eponyms</esp:link>, which are now invaluable
    resources for understanding Assyrian chronology. However, the surviving
lists run out in the mid-seventh century BC, even though the system
continued to be used for several decades afterwards. These so-called
<em>post-canonical eponym</em> dates, whose order we cannot be sure of, are
typically marked with an asterisk, e.g., 620* BC.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="equinox">Twice a year, daytime and
nighttime are of equal length. In the modern dating system the spring
and autumn equinoxes fall on or near to 20 March and 23 September. In
Assyrian times the first appearance of the crescent moon in the
evening sky after the spring equinox signalled the new year. See also
<esp:techterms
    term="akītu"><i>akītu</i></esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Eton College">British private school for
boys, founded in the 15th century. Highly infuential, it has educated
many future politicians, diplomats, and powerful men.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="eunuch">Castrated man, usually a palace
courtier.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Euphrates Expedition">Project funded by the British government and the <esp:techterms term="East India Company">East India Company</esp:techterms> in 1835, to determine whether or not the river <esp:glossary term="Euphrates (place)">Euphrates</esp:glossary> could be used for river traffic to shorten the long journey between Britain and India.  As part of their mapping duties, its members surveyed several archaeological sites near the river, including Nimrud.</esp:termsdefinition>


<esp:termsdefinition term="excavation season">Period during
which an archaeological team is working on the excavation site, any
time from a few weeks to several months a year. The length and timing
of an excavation season depends on many factors, from the academic
teaching commitments of the archaeologists, the funding available for
the dig, and the typical weather conditions at the site.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="exegesis">Explanation and interpretation of difficult passages of holy scripture.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="exorcist">Traditional translation of a
type of <esp:techterms term="scholar">scholar</esp:techterms> called <i>āšipu</i> in
Assyrian. Their intellectual
interests were wide but centred on healing. At the Assyrian court their expertise was often called to
ritually protect the king from harm.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="extispicy">Divination through the
observation of the entrails of a
sacrificed sheep or ram, carried out by a <esp:techterms
term="haruspex">haruspex</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- F -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="faience">Glass-like material made of
crushed quartz or sand, mixed with small amounts of other
materials. It can be moulded and modelled like clay. When fired its
exterior turns a glassy blue or green, depending on the additives
used.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="figurine">Small clay model or statue, often
used in <esp:techterms term="rite, ritual">rituals</esp:techterms> to represent supernatural beings - either
<esp:techterms term="apotropaic">apotropaic</esp:techterms> <esp:techterms
term="genie">genies</esp:techterms>  to ward off evil, or the
<esp:techterms term="demon">demon</esp:techterms> or witch  thought to be the cause of the
misfortune. Apotropaic figurines were preserved and ritually buried;
<esp:techterms term="maleficent">maleficent</esp:techterms> figurines were ritually destroyed,
sometimes by throwing them into a river.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="findspot">Location of discovery of an
archaeological artefact, ideally recorded in in three co-ordinates and
documented in relation to the surround <esp:techterms
term="assemblage">assemblage</esp:techterms> and archaeological context.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="fish-man">Hybrid <esp:techterms term="demon">demon</esp:techterms> or <esp:techterms term="genie">genie</esp:techterms>,
half man and half fish, which was often associated with 
the <esp:techterms term="sage">Seven Sages</esp:techterms> from before
the <esp:techterms term="Flood">Flood</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="flax">
An annual crop with beautiful blue flowers, native to the Middle East
and beyond. It is grown for its fibrous stalks, which are woven into
linen, and for its highly nutritious seeds, from which linseed oil is
made.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Flood">
    Assyrian scholars divided past time into a mythical, primeval era
    and more recent human history, demarcated by a great flood. As
    well as one human family, rescued by the great god <esp:glossary
    term="Ea (deity)">Ea</esp:glossary>, seven
    <esp:techterms term="sage">sages</esp:techterms> - half-human, half-fish - survived to bring the ancient
    arts of civilisation to contemporary humanity.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="foundation deposit">Collection of ritual
objects ceremonially placed in the foundation of an Assyrian palace, temple or
fortification wall, often including a <esp:techterms
term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> <esp:link page="inscriptions">inscription</esp:link> identifying and praising the initiator of the
construction work; in most cases, this was the
king</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="foundation course">The lower part of a
wall, designed to remain underground or protrude only slightly above
it. In Assyrian times, foundation courses were often made of fired
brick, even when the rest of the building was made of less durable materials.</esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- G -->

<esp:termsdefinition term="Gantt chart">Bar chart used to visualise
a project's schedule, showing multiple elements positioned on a timeline, named after its inventor.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="gelatinous">Sticky and thick like gelatine,
the key ingredient in jelly.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="genie">Supernatural being that was
considered to protect human clients from <esp:techterms
term="demon">demons</esp:techterms> and other <esp:techterms
term="maleficent">maleficent</esp:techterms> forces. On the <esp:techterms
term="bas-relief">reliefs</esp:techterms> of the <esp:link page="northwestpalace">Northwest Palace</esp:link> at Kalhu, genies
were mostly depicted as human-like figures with wings, sometimes with
eagles' heads. See also <i><esp:techterms term="apkallu">apkallu</esp:techterms></i>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="glaze">Glassy layer on the surface of some
types of pottery, applied as a powder or solution before firing and
used for decoration, waterproofing and/or to strengthen the vessel.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="gold">Almost all Assyrian gold came
ultimately from <esp:glossary term="Egypt
(place)">Egypt</esp:glossary>, whether through direct trade,
collection of <esp:techterms term="tribute">tribute</esp:techterms>
from <esp:techterms term="vassal">vassals</esp:techterms> or capture
of booty from conquered cities in the region.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="governor">Highest official in a <esp:techterms term="province">province</esp:techterms> of the Assyrian empire, personally selected and appointed by the king to govern this subdivision of the state on his behalf. In addition to their local administrative duties, governors were in charge of collecting and distributing taxes, and of mustering and supporting contingents of soldiers for the Assyrian army. </esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="griffin">Modern term for eagle-headed
<esp:techterms term="demon">demon</esp:techterms>
with a lion's body, often with wings.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Gulf War">Fought January-February 1991. On 2 August 1990, the Iraqi army invaded neighbouring Kuwait, precipitating an international crisis. The United Natiosn first imposed a range of <esp:techterms term="sanctions">sanctions</esp:techterms> on the government of Iraq to force them to leave. When that appeared to have no effect, the UN backed an international coalition of armies, led United States of America. The war ended with Iraq's withdrawal from Kuwait and an increased sanctions regime. In the aftermath of the war, anti-government rebellions in the south of Iraq were heavily quashed; some <esp:techterms term="province">provincial</esp:techterms> museums were looted and damaged.</esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- H -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="hand-copy">In <esp:techterms
term="Assyriology">Assyriology</esp:techterms>, a black-and-white
scale drawing of a cuneiform tablet.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="harem">Literally "house of the women": a
part of the royal palace containing the living quarters of the female
members of the court headed by the queen, managed by a female
administrator and
guarded by a <esp:techterms term="eunuch">eunuch</esp:techterms>..</esp:termsdefinition> 

<esp:termsdefinition term="haruspex">Type of <esp:techterms term="scholar">scholar</esp:techterms>  specialising in <esp:techterms term="extispicy">extispicy</esp:techterms>, i.e., determining the divine will by reading the entrails of sacrificed sheep; the Assyrian term is <i>bārû</i>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Hellenistic">Period of c.300 years from the
death of Alexander the Great in 323 BC, during which Greek language,
culture, and political power dominated the Middle East; also applied
to typical features of that era.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="humidity">How damp the air is; important to
control in museums and
<esp:techterms term="conservation">conservation</esp:techterms> work because some ancient artefacts are particularly
sensitive to changes in humidity.</esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- I -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="iconography">Conventional meanings attached to images (such as love, for a heart); and the academic study of those meanings and the ways in which they are represented visually.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="idolatry">Worship of idols; that is, images or statues of gods, saints or other divine beings.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Illustrated London News">Pioneering illustrated news magazine, which was founded in 1842 and folded in 2003, after decades of declining circulation. Throughout its history the ILN took a strong interest in the excavations and discoveries at Nimrud, and the arrival of finds at the British Museum.  </esp:termsdefinition>


<esp:termsdefinition term="impression">Mark left, especially on clay
tablets, by other objects such as <esp:techterms term="seal, sealing">seals</esp:techterms>, cloth, or fingernails pushed
into the surface.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="incantation">Words spoken or chanted in <esp:techterms term="rite, ritual">ritual</esp:techterms> context to communicate with a deity, <esp:techterms term="demon">demon</esp:techterms>, or <esp:techterms term="genie">genie</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="incense">Mixture of aromatic plant products, designed to be burnt in a censer to release fragrant smoke during <esp:techterms term="rite, ritual">rituals</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="inclusion">Grit, plant matter, and other
tiny particles in clay, often added deliberately; for instance to
increase its flexibility when working with it, or
help steam escape during firing so the pot doesn't
break. <esp:techterms term="tablet">Tablet</esp:techterms> clay
may also have accidental or deliberate inclusions.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="inscribed brick">Assyrian bricks were very
large, square and flat, more like modern paving stones than modern
house bricks. Some bricks used in important buildings such as temples
and palaces had a small inscription stamped into their top surface,
typically recording information such as the name and function of the
building, the king who commissioned it, and the god(s) who inspired him.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Institute of Archaeology">Formerly
a department of the University of London, now part of University
College London, this was the institutional base for <esp:glossary
term="Mallowan, Max (person)">Max Mallowan</esp:glossary> (Professor
of Western Asiatic Archaeology, 1947–62) and
other members of the team who worked on Nimrud in the
1950s.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Iraq Museum">Museum founded in the
1920s by <esp:glossary term="Bell, Gertrude (person)">Gertrude
Bell</esp:glossary> in <esp:glossary term="Baghdad (place)">Baghdad</esp:glossary> and now Iraq's national
museum. Holds many artefacts excavated from Nimrud in the 20th century.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Iraq Petroleum Company">Founded by a consortium of international companies after the discovery of oil in northern Iraq in 1927, the IPC held a virtual monopoly on oil production in Iraq for nearly half a century. It was nationalised in 1972.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Iraq War">The United States of America led an invasion of Iraq in March 2003 on the grounds that it had developed chemical, biological and/or nuclear weapons in contravention of the <esp:techterms term="sanctions">UN sanctions</esp:techterms> regime. Those claims proved unfounded but the Iraqi army was swiftly defeated and for many years Iraq remained occupied by international forces.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="ivory">Teeth or tusks of elephants or
<esp:glossary term="Egypt (place)">Egyptian</esp:glossary>
hippopotami. Elaborately carved and inlaid ivory objects, from tiny
boxes to thrones and bedsteads, were highly prized by the
Assyrians. Large quantities of decorated ivory <esp:link page="ivories">have been found</esp:link> by
archaeologists in Assyrian palaces, much of which seems to have been
plundered as booty from other cities. Ivory requires <esp:link page="bmag-conservation">special conservation techniques.</esp:link></esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- J -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="jar-stopper">Object made to fit inside the narrow
opening of a pot or jug in order to stop its contents leaking
out.</esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- K -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="kettledrum"><esp:techterms
					   term="lamenter">Lamenters</esp:techterms>
used enormous hemispherical drums in their <esp:techterms
term="rite, ritual">ritual</esp:techterms> performances to dooth divine
anger. The drums, made of oxhide and bronze, were themselves ritually
constructed.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Korean War">Fought between North Korea and South Korea, June 1950-July 1950. The United States allied with the South, the Soviet Union with the North. It is seen by many historians as one of the starting points of the Cold War perios, several decades of heightened international tension during which capitalist western nations faced off against communist Eastern countried.</esp:termsdefinition>


<esp:termsdefinition term="Kuyunjik collection">Large collection of cuneiform
<esp:techterms term="tablet">tablets</esp:techterms> now housed in the <esp:techterms term="British Museum">British Museum</esp:techterms>, mostly found during <esp:glossary
term="Layard, Austen Henry (person)">Layard's</esp:glossary>
excavations through the <esp:techterms
term="citadel">citadel</esp:techterms> mound at <esp:glossary
term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary>, whose modern
name is Kuyunjik. For more information see the <esp:link
rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://oracc.org/asbp">Ashurbanipal Library
Project</esp:link>'s website</esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- L -->

<esp:termsdefinition term="label run">Type of museum labelling where text is written on a long, thin label strip. Usually placed at the bottom of the case or on a shelf edge.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="lahmu">Literally, "hairy": benevolent
protective spirit or <esp:techterms term="genie">genie</esp:techterms> in the form of a curly-haired hero.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="lamenter">Scholar responsible for performing propitiatory (soothing,
or apologetic) <esp:techterms term="rite, ritual">rituals</esp:techterms>
with chanting and kettledrums to calm the gods' mood after a <esp:techterms term="diviner">diviner</esp:techterms>
had detected unfavourable omens. The aim was to reverse the
gods' decision and persuade them to be favourable once more. The Assyrian word is <i>kalû</i>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="landscape format">Alternatively, horizontal
format: when a document is written with the script parallel to the
long edge. The opposite is <esp:techterms term="portrait
format">portrait format</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="lapis lazuli">Intensely blue semi-precious stone from Afghanistan that was highly valued in Assyria. Sparkling yellow flecks on the stone's surface were thought to resemble the twinkling stars in the night sky. </esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="levy">Summoning part-time soldiers from their peacetime occupations, such as farming, in perparation for
military activity.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="lexical list">Scribal training invariably included the copying and memorisation of long, standardised lists of cuneiform signs, words and phrases, usually with both Sumerian and Akkadian spellings.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="libation"><esp:techterms term="rite, ritual">Rituals</esp:techterms> often included the sacrifice of a liquid offering to a god or supernatural being. The libation, usually wine but sometimes also beer or milk, was poured into the ground from a special libation bowl.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="lime">Mortar or cement, more particularly
its main ingredient, powered
calcium oxide (CaO), which is made by heating limestone to very high temperature.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Linked Open Data">Principle of structuring online
information, and allowing it to be reused, in order to intregrate data
on a common theme from many
different sources.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="lotus">Egyptian white water-lily, which has
large round leaves that float on the water and large, many-petalled
flowers. Its highly characteristic buds, which bulge at the bottom,
taper in the middle and open wide at the top, were a popular motif in
ancient Near Eastern art, for instance on the <esp:techterms
term="Nimrud ivories">Nimrud
ivories</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Louvre">Public museum in Paris, opened in 1793 during the French Revolution, in a grandiose former royal palace. Amongst its vast holdings are finds from <esp:glossary term="Botta, Paul-Émile (person)">Botta's</esp:glossary> explorations in Assyria in the 1840s.</esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- M -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="magazine">Storeroom or warehouse,
especially for weapons.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="magnate">Literally "great one": a designation for one of the Assyrian king's senior political or military advisors.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="maleficent">Doing evil. The opposite of
beneficent.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Mandate">Period, 1920–32, when Britain
ruled Iraq under a mandate issued by the League of Nations, a
forerunner to the United Nations. More generally, an official order to
act on someone's behalf.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="marble">Type of crystalline limestone that
is particularly suitable for carving. Assyrian marble came from
quarries around modern-day <esp:glossary term="Mosul
(place)">Mosul</esp:glossary> in the heartland of the empire. See also
<esp:techterms term="alabaster">alabaster</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Methodism"><esp:techterms term="Protestant">Protestant</esp:techterms> Christian movement, founded in the eighteenth century, with an emphasis on social inclusion and therefore also <esp:techterms term="missionary">missionary</esp:techterms> work.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="methylated spirits">Solvent based on ethanol, formula CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>OH, with various additives. Used by <esp:techterms term="conservator">conservators</esp:techterms> for cleaning archaeological artefacts; useful because it can be mixed with water.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Metropolitan Museum of Art">Large art museum in New York, founded in 1870, which was one of the major sponsors of the <esp:link page="nd1950">1950s excavations</esp:link> at Nimrud. It houses a significant number of finds from the site.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="mezzotint">Engraving technique that enables the artist to depict very delicate differentations of shade and light.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="microfilm">Before the advent of digital photography, an efficient way to reproduce documents and books in portable form was to photograph them onto film, which could then be read with a special magnifying machine.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Middle Assyrian">Period of Assyria's first major
empire, in the late second
millennium BC, c.1392-1056 BC; also the dialect of <esp:techterms
term="Akkadian">Akkadian</esp:techterms> and form of <esp:techterms
term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> script written at that
time. </esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="mina">Weight measure roughly equivalent to
     0.5kg, which was divided into 60 shekels.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Ministry of Culture">Iraqi government ministry which manages archaeology in the country, and has done so for much of the country's history. For three years, 2012-2015, archaeology was under the direction of a separate Ministry of Tourism and Antiquities.</esp:termsdefinition>


<esp:termsdefinition term="missionary">Person sent to do religious
work in another country; particularly refers to nineteenth-century European and north
American <esp:techterms term="Protestant">Protestant</esp:techterms> Christians who tried to convert others to their religion.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="mayor">Either the representative of a city
(or a city quarter, as in <esp:glossary term="Assur
(place)">Assur</esp:glossary>) or a temple (like the <esp:link
page="ezida">temple of Nabu</esp:link> in Kalhu); chosen by the king
from among the local population.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Mosul Museum">Public museum in <esp:glossary term="Mosul (place)">Mosul</esp:glossary> which displayed antiquities from northern Iraq, especially from Nimrud, <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary> and <esp:link url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hatra" hide-print="yes" rel="external">Hatra</esp:link>. Closed for many years for refurbishment, it was ransacked by <esp:techterms term="Da'esh/ISIS">Da'esh/ISIS</esp:techterms> in early 2015.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="mud brick">Bricks made of mud or clay and left to harden in the sun instead of being baked in a kiln. They are much cheaper to produce than baked bricks, and so were often used in antiquity. But they are not as weather-proof and are therefore problematic for <esp:techterms term="restoration">restoration</esp:techterms> projects. </esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- N -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="natural history">Study of nature and its history, through observation of natural objects; a counterpart to <esp:techterms term="antiquarianism">antiquarianism</esp:techterms> and a precursor to the modern disciplines of biology, botany, etc.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Neo-Assyrian">Period of Assyria's greatest
empire, c.883–612 BC; also the dialect of <esp:techterms term="Akkadian">Akkadian</esp:techterms> and form of <esp:techterms
term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> script written at that time. </esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Neo-Babylonian">Period of Babylonian
imperial rule, c.623–539 BC; more generally the dialect of <esp:techterms term="Akkadian">Akkadian</esp:techterms> and form of <esp:techterms
term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> script written in
<esp:glossary term="Babylonia (place)">Babylonia</esp:glossary>
in the first half of the first millennium BC.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="New Year Festival">Religious festival
performed over several days at the spring <esp:techterms term="equinox">equinox</esp:techterms>, and featuring the gods'
renewal of the king's right to rule; See <i><esp:techterms term="akītu">akītu</esp:techterms></i></esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Nimrud Horse Lists">Forty-two letters form
<esp:glossary term="Nabu-šumu-iddina (person)">Nabu-šumu-iddina</esp:glossary>,
<esp:techterms term="mayor">mayor</esp:techterms> of <esp:link page="ezida">Nabu's temple</esp:link> in Kalhu, concerning
deliveries of horses to <esp:link page="fortshalmaneser">Fort
Shalmaneser</esp:link>. See further <esp:link page="templestaff" bookmark="h_royalliaisonofficersthehazannuandqpu">Royal liaison officers</esp:link>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Nimrud ivories">Archaeologists have found
many thousands of carved, inlaid, and/or gilded
<esp:techterms term="ivory">ivory</esp:techterms> fragments—of furniture, domestic objects and ornaments—at
Nimrud. They were mostly made in Egypt and the Levant and were taken
to Assyria as tribute or war booty. Specialist art historians study
their decorative motifs and styles of production. See the page on their <esp:link page="ivories">object biographies</esp:link> and the page on <esp:link page="bmag-conservation">their conservation</esp:link> for more details.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Nimrud Wine Lists">About 30 ration lists of
bread and wine found in <esp:link page="fortshalmaneser">Fort Shalmaneser</esp:link>, dating from the reigns of
<esp:glossary term="Adad-nerari III (person)">Adad-nerari
III</esp:glossary>  and <esp:glossary term="Tiglath-pileser III
(person)">Tiglath-pileser III</esp:glossary>. These texts may represent regular allocations to court personnel and
visiting dignitaries, or extra distributions on special occasions. See
also <esp:link page="professions"
bookmark="h_scholarsatcourtin8thcenturykalhu">Scholars at court in 8th
century Kalhu</esp:link>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- O -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="obelisk">Tall, needle-like monument made of
a single piece of stone, often decorated with images and/or
inscribed with text. See for instance the <esp:link page="obelisk">Black Obelisk</esp:link>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="oblate">Woman or man dedicated (often by
a patron or senior family member) to a deity, to work for and/or worship them in perpetuity.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="obverse, reverse">Front and back of a
cuneiform <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablet</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Old Assyrian">Period of <esp:glossary
term="Assur (place)">Assur</esp:glossary>'s greatest
influence as a city state, c.1910–1740 BC; also the dialect of <esp:techterms term="Akkadian">Akkadian</esp:techterms> and form of <esp:techterms
term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> script written at that time.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="omen">Plural sometimes "omina";
adjective "ominous". Assyrian omens take the form, "If X
is observed, then Y will happen", where X is any event or phenomenon
in the sky, on earth, or on a person's body. The outcome Y (which
could be favourable or unfavourable) was not inevitable but could
be averted by <esp:techterms term="rite, ritual">rituals</esp:techterms>
performed by expert <esp:techterms
term="lamenter">lamenters</esp:techterms>. Specialist <esp:techterms
term="diviner">diviners</esp:techterms> such as <esp:techterms
term="astrologer">astrologers</esp:techterms>, <esp:techterms
term="augur">augurs</esp:techterms>, <esp:techterms
term="exorcist">exorcists</esp:techterms>, and <esp:techterms
term="haruspex">haruspices</esp:techterms> were responsible for
reading and interpreting ominous signs by means of standardised collections of omens. </esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="oracle">Message from the gods, usually
sent to a <esp:techterms
term="prophet(ess)">prophet(ess)</esp:techterms> through a dream or
trance; but it can also mean the divine answer to an <esp:techterms
term="extispicy">extispicy</esp:techterms>
query.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Ottoman">Empire based in modern-day Turkey
that ruled the Middle East from the mid-fifteenth century to the eve
of the First World War; also a form of Turkish spoken and written in Arabic
script.</esp:termsdefinition>


<!-- P -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="palace ware">Finely made <esp:techterms term="glaze">unglazed</esp:techterms> pottery
with few <esp:techterms term="inclusion">inclusions</esp:techterms>,
in elegant shapes suitable for use by members of the royal court.</esp:termsdefinition> 

<esp:termsdefinition term="papyrus">Early form of paper, made from
the pith of the papyrus reed that grows in the Nile valley, and
imported into Assyria from <esp:glossary term="Egypt
(place)">Egypt</esp:glossary>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="parasol">In Assyria the parasol was as much a status symbol as it was a sun-shade. In palace <esp:techterms term="bas-relief">bas-reliefs</esp:techterms> showing outdoor scenes, the Assyrian king is fequently depicted standing or sitting under a parasol, held aloft by a personal servant. </esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="parchment">Using a pen and ink, texts in
<esp:link page="alphabetic">alphabetic Aramaic script</esp:link> were commonly recorded on leather scrolls. While the term "parchment" is frequently used as a translation for these scrolls, this is anachronistic and should be avoided as "parchment" refers to a very specific leather-derived product prepared according to a recipe not yet attested in Assyrian times.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="pasha"><esp:techterms
				      term="province">Provincial
governor</esp:techterms> of the <esp:techterms term="Ottoman">Ottoman</esp:techterms>
empire.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="physician">In the Assyrian court, a
     <esp:techterms term="scholar">scholar</esp:techterms>  with particular responsibility for the physical wellbeing of the royal family; Assyrian <i>asû</i>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Picture Post">Popular British weekly magazine, published from 1938 to 1957, featuring photographic essays on a range of journalistic topics. It was very different in style and politics to its more conservative rival <esp:techterms term="Illustrated London News"><i>The Illustrated London News</i></esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>


<esp:termsdefinition term="plaque">Flat object used for decoration or
display; may be made of precious materials and usually carries an
image and/or inscription.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="polyptych"><esp:techterms term="writing board">Writing
board</esp:techterms>  with several waxed writing surfaces hinged together.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="polyvinyl acetate">Adhesive commonly known as PVA, formula (C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>6</sub>O<sub>2</sub>)<sub>n</sub>. Used by <esp:techterms term="conservator">conservators</esp:techterms> to consolidate fragile organic materials such as <esp:techterms term="ivory">ivory</esp:techterms>, or to glue pieces together.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="pomegranate">Fruit tree native to the
Middle East, whose sweet multi-seeded fruit was popular as a food and,
symbolising fertility, also in <esp:techterms term="rite, ritual">rituals</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="potsherd">Also sherd; a broken fragment of
pottery.</esp:termsdefinition> 	

<esp:termsdefinition term="portrait format">Alternatively, vertical
format: when a document is written with the script parallel to the
short edge. The opposite is <esp:techterms term="landscape
format">landscape format</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="postern gate">Minor or private entrance.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="prophet(ess)">Individual who receives
messages from the gods through <esp:techterms term="oracle">oracles</esp:techterms>. They can be attached to a temple.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Protestant">Christian who does not
recognise the authority of the Pope; for instance followers of the
Church of England. In the nineteenth century, some British and
American Protestant churches sent <esp:techterms term="missionary">missionaries</esp:techterms> to the Middle East to
try and convert Muslims and Catholic Christians to their faith.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="provenance">In US English, provenience. The life history and/or origins of
an artefact, including past ownership and, for archaeological objects, any <esp:techterms
term="findspot">findspot</esp:techterms> information. Also refers to documentary evidence of
this life history. </esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="province">Large-scale administrative unit
of an empire. Assyria was divided into about 70 provinces, each under
the control of a governor (Assyrian <i>pāhutu</i> or <i>bēl
pāhete</i>) personally appointed
by the king. The three provinces (<i>vilayets</i>) of the
<esp:techterms term="Ottoman">Ottoman</esp:techterms> empire
that roughly correspond to modern-day Iraq were centred on
<esp:glossary term="Mosul (place)">Mosul</esp:glossary>,
<esp:glossary term="Baghdad (place)">Baghdad</esp:glossary> and <esp:glossary term="Basra (place)">Basra</esp:glossary>. Each was governed by a <esp:techterms term="pasha">pasha</esp:techterms>. Iraq is now divided into 19 provinces or governorates, including the three that make up Kurdistan.</esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- Q -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="queen">Literally "woman of the palace": the
official wife of the Assyrian king and usually also the mother of the
<esp:techterms term="crown prince">crown prince</esp:techterms>. Many of the early <esp:techterms term="Neo-Assyrian">Neo-Assyrian</esp:techterms> queens were buried in the <esp:link page="northwestpalace" bookmark="h_behindthesceneslivingwiththedead">Northwest Palace</esp:link>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="queen mother">[1] The widow of the preceding king; [2] the ruling king's
mother.</esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- R -->

<esp:termsdefinition term="registration number">Unique number assigned to an object upon entry to a museum collection. Used for identification purposes and usually inscribed upon the object itself.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="relief">See <esp:techterms term="bas-relief">bas-relief</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Residency">Post of senior representative of
the <esp:techterms term="East India Company">East India
Company</esp:techterms> (EIC) and/or that person's official residence; in
early nineteenth-century
Mesopotamia there were EIC Residencies at <esp:glossary term="Basra (place)">Basra</esp:glossary> and <esp:glossary term="Baghdad (place)">Baghdad</esp:glossary>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="restoration">Archaeological restoration involves preserving a building or settlement to help give researchers and visitors a sense of what it must have originally been like. Restoration should not damage the original fabric of the structure but it should also protect it from wear and tear. A closely related method is reconstruction, which uses new materials in the restoration. Good reconstruction projects are careful to differentiate the original structure from the new additions.</esp:termsdefinition>


<esp:termsdefinition term="ring base">Many pots and containers are
made with flat bases so that they can stand upright
unsupported. Others have rounded bases to enable easy internal
cleaning, or even heat distribution when suspended over a fire. In
some cases, either of these types may have an extra horizontal ring added to the
base for increased stability.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="rite, ritual">At its simplest, a ritual is
a socially agreed set of symbolic actions and/or utterances, performed
in a stylised way. Rituals may be performed at set times or as the
need arises. In Assyria rituals could have any combination of
religous, magical, political, social, or healing significance; they
could be perfomed by <esp:techterms term="scholar">scholars</esp:techterms>  or priests on behalf of a client (such as the king). The word "rite" is usually reserved to describe predominantly religious rituals. </esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="rock crystal">Transparent type of quartz stone
which looks like modern glass.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Royal Asiatic Society of Great Britain and Ireland">London-based learned society
founded in 1823 to study the history, languages, cultures and
religions of Asia, from the Middle East to the Far East and <esp:link
rel="external" hide-print="yes" url="http://www.royalasiaticsociety.org/">still in
existence today</esp:link>. In 1830 the
<esp:glossary term="Bombay (place)">Bombay</esp:glossary>
Literary Society (which had been running for some 25 years already)
affiliated with it as the Bombay Branch of the Royal Asiatic Society,
publishing its own journal.</esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- S -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="sacred marriage"><esp:techterms
						term="rite, ritual">Ritual</esp:techterms>
in which two deities, or a goddess and a king, were symbolically
united. At Kalhu, the <esp:techterms
term="akītu"><i>akītu</i></esp:techterms> ritual featured an annual marriage
between the gods <esp:link page="nabu">Nabu</esp:link> and
<esp:glossary term="Tašmetu (deity)">Tašmetu</esp:glossary>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="sacred tree">Modern name for the highly
stylised tree shown on <esp:techterms
term="bas-relief">bas-reliefs</esp:techterms> in the ceremonial spaces
of Assyrian palaces, especially the <esp:link
page="northwestpalace">Northwest Palace</esp:link> in Kalhu.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="sage">Wise person; in Assyria, one of the
seven semi-divine scholars from before the great <esp:techterms term="Flood">Flood</esp:techterms>, who brought
wisdom and learning to humankind.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="sanctions">In August 1990, in response to Iraq's invasion of Kuwait, the United Nations imposed a heavy ban on international trade and communication with Iraq. The original aim was to force the withdrawal of Iraqi troops without declaring war. However, even after the 1991 <esp:techterms term="Gulf War">Gulf War</esp:techterms>, the sanctions regime remained in place and was tightened further. It began to be lifted only after <esp:techterms term="Iraq War">Iraq War</esp:techterms> of 2003.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="sarcophagus">Monumental coffin, usually
made of stone.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="scarab">Semi-precious stone cut in the
shape of an oval beetle, with an inscription or decoration carved on
the flat underside; often used as a <esp:techterms term="seal, sealing">seal</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="scholar">The Assyrian court employed a
variety of learned, literate men to advise the king on his
relationship with the gods. The scholars  included <esp:techterms term="astrologer">astrologers</esp:techterms>, <esp:techterms term="augur">augurs</esp:techterms>, <esp:techterms term="exorcist">exorcists</esp:techterms>, <esp:techterms term="haruspex">haruspices</esp:techterms>, <esp:techterms term="lamenter">lamenters</esp:techterms>, and <esp:techterms term="scribe">scribes</esp:techterms>. <esp:link page="professions">Such roles</esp:link>, and the specialist education they entailed, were often handed down <esp:link page="families">within families</esp:link>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="scribe">Professionally literate person,
who may have been as lowly as a secretary or as eminent and powerful
as the king's senior <esp:techterms
term="scholar">scholar</esp:techterms>. Scribes might write on
<esp:techterms term="papyrus">papyrus</esp:techterms>  or
<esp:techterms term="writing board">writing boards</esp:techterms>  as well as, or instead of, clay <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablets</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="seal, sealing"><esp:techterms
					    term="tablet">Tablets</esp:techterms>,
<esp:techterms term="writing board">writing boards</esp:techterms>,
<esp:techterms term="papyrus">papyri</esp:techterms>, and other
objects could be sealed with clay, either to prevent unauthorised
access to them or to mark them with the symbol of the official or
individual responsible for them. The sealing official either impressed
the clay with a stamp-seal, or rolled out the inscribed or decorated
surface of a cylinder-seal, and left it to dry before releasing the object.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Semitic language"><esp:techterms term="Akkadian">Akkadian</esp:techterms>, <esp:techterms term="Aramaic">Aramaic</esp:techterms>, and
Hebrew and Arabic, amongst other languages, all share a set of common
features. One of the monst important of these is that the basic
meanings of words are carried by two to four <esp:link
url="http://oracc.org/saao/knpp/cuneiformrevealed/akkadianlanguage/nounsandadjectives/#h_rootconsonantscarriersoflexicalconent"
rel="external" hide-print="yes">root consonants</esp:link>,
regardless of their grammatical function. The same roots may be
shared, or changed a little, across Semitic languages too.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="sickle">Large knife with a curved blade, used for harvesting grain but also as a weapon.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="silver">In Assyrian times, most silver came
from mines around the area of <esp:glossary term="Que (place)">Que</esp:glossary> in the northwest of the empire.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Society for Biblical Archaeology">British
society of Egyptologists and Assyriologists, founded in London in 1870
to discuss, publish, and promote research (not just archaeology) on
the ancient Middle East (not just the Biblical lands). In the early
20th century its membership declined dramatically as these subjects became increasingly
embedded in British universities and it was eventually wound up.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="squeeze">Impression of an inscription or
carving made by pressing layers wet paper into it, leaving the paper
to dry, and then peeling it off. The result is a mirror image of the
original. Squeezes were a useful means of accurately copying
inscriptions on immovable objects before photography became reliable
but they were also fragile and difficult to reproduce. </esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Standard Babylonian">Literary dialect of <esp:techterms term="Akkadian">Akkadian</esp:techterms> in the first millennium BC, used in Assyria as well as <esp:glossary term="Babylonia (place)">Babylonia</esp:glossary>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="State Board of Antiquities and Heritage">Iraqi government authority in charge of
managing archaeology, museum work, and related research, under the
direction of the <esp:techterms term="Ministry of Culture">Ministry of Culture</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="stela, stele">Plural stelae. Large, standing stone monument, carved with inscriptions and/or images.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="stereoview">Two slightly different photographic images, designed to be viewed together — one by the right eye, the other by the left — in order to create a sense of visual depth.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="stratified">Having
clear <esp:techterms term="stratigraphy">stratigraphy</esp:techterms>;
unstratified excavation sites have usually been disturbed before the
arrival of the archaeologists, for instance by long-ago burials or
building works, or the activities of farmers or burrowing animals.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="stratigraphy">Archaeological study of
the different layers, or strata, left by human (or animal) occupation
of a building or settlement over time. Individual stratigraphic layers
often show up as different colours, textures or densities of earth in
the excavation.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="succession">In the Assyrian context,
ensuring that the ruling king's nominated successor, his
<esp:techterms term="crown prince">crown prince</esp:techterms>,
becomes king in his turn.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="stylus">Pointed writing implement, the
size and shape of a pen, used to impress <esp:techterms
term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms>  signs on the surface of a
<esp:techterms term="tablet">tablet</esp:techterms>  or a
<esp:techterms term="writing board">writing
board</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="survey">Archaeological survey involves investigating the surface of a site, or series of sites. It may include techniques such as examining pottery and other artefacts found on the surface in order to date the site, mapping the contours of the site(s), or taking soil samples at regular intervals. </esp:termsdefinition>


<!-- T -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="tablet">Most simply, a document made of
clay, on which <esp:techterms
term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms>  writing was impressed with
a reed <esp:techterms term="stylus">stylus</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Tablet of Destinies">Magnificent
<esp:techterms term="lapis lazuli">lapis
lazuli</esp:techterms> <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablet</esp:techterms>
owned by the gods, on which they inscribed the fate of humankind. It was stolen by
the evil <esp:glossary term="Anzu (deity)">Anzu</esp:glossary> and
reclaimed by the god <esp:link
page="ninurta">Ninurta</esp:link>. Likewise, the
<esp:techterms term="seal, sealing">Seal</esp:techterms> of
Destinies was used by the gods to sign particularly important
documents such as <esp:link page="vte-intro">Esarhaddon's succession treaties</esp:link>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="Tašritu"></esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="temple steward">While the Assyrian term
<i>lahhinnu</i> is a loan from a Hurrian word of unknown meaning, it is clear
that it designates a high-ranking administrative temple
official.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="topographical map">In archaeology, a map that details the contours of a site, often in order to determine where the remains of structures mihght be lying under the surface.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="torque">Decorative metal band worn tightly around
the arm, emphasising the wearer's muscles; appears frequently on the
king and <esp:techterms term="genie">genies</esp:techterms> on
Assyrian palace
<esp:techterms term="bas-relief">bas-reliefs</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="treason">Act of betraying one's country, or
its current ruler.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="trench">In archaeology, a narrow,
rectangular hole cut into the surface of a site, layer by layer in
order to expose and record the site's <esp:techterms
term="stratigraphy">stratigraphy</esp:techterms> and any artefacts
found in that context.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="tribute">Annual payment by a <esp:techterms term="vassal">vassal</esp:techterms> state
to the Assyrian king, either handed over at the border to a
<esp:techterms term="governor">governor</esp:techterms>  or delivered
by <esp:techterms term="emissary">emissaries</esp:techterms> to the
king in person. This second option was seen as more dignified and prestigious.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="type series">In archaeology, a collection
of artefacts, especially pottery, that systematically shows a representative range
and variety of shapes found at a particular site from a particular
period in the past. This series of typical artefacts then serves as a
standard reference set to help date or categorise
material found at other sites.</esp:termsdefinition> 
	

<!-- V -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="vassal">In relation to Assyria, a
neighbouring state which was loyal to Assyria and paid regular
<esp:techterms term="tribute">tribute</esp:techterms> to ensure
Assyria's continuing protection and friendship but was still nominally
independent from it. </esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="viscid">Gluey or sticky; see also
<esp:techterms term="gelatinous">gelatinous</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="vizier">Very senior official
(<esp:techterms term="magnate">magnate</esp:techterms>) in the king's
personal retinue, who held high administrative functions within the
empire and commanded a border <esp:techterms
term="province">province</esp:techterms> of key strategic
importance. </esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="votive">Object or person dedicated to a
deity, thereby becoming the property of the temple; see also
<esp:techterms term="oblate">oblate</esp:techterms>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- W -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="water buffalo">Large cattle with huge horns
which spend a lot of time in rivers and marshes, and eat reeds and
other aquatic plants. They are very
strong and docile draft animals, and produce
highly nutritious milk. Water buffalos probably originate in India but
there have been significant populations in southern Iraq since at
least the third millennium BC.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="wedge">Basic component of <esp:techterms
term="cuneiform">cuneiform</esp:techterms> script made by pushing the
edge of a <esp:techterms term="stylus">stylus</esp:techterms> into the
surface of a clay <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablet</esp:techterms>
and lifting it up again. For more detail see the <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/knpp/cuneiformrevealed/aboutcuneiform/wedgesandsigns/#h_wedges">Cuneiform Revealed</esp:link> website.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="West Semitic">Subgroup of the
<esp:techterms term="Semitic language">Semitic
languages</esp:techterms> from Syria and the <esp:glossary term="Levant (place)">Levant</esp:glossary>; <esp:techterms
term="Akkadian">Akkadian</esp:techterms>, by contrast, is the only
Eastern member of this language family.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="winged disk">Symbol originating in
ancient <esp:glossary term="Egypt (place)">Egypt</esp:glossary>, consisting of a round centre flanked by two horizontal
wings. On Assyrian palace <esp:techterms
term="bas-relief">bas-reliefs</esp:techterms> it is always shown
close the king's head. It may represent the divine aspect of
kingship, or the sun-god <esp:glossary term="Šamaš (deity)">Šamaš</esp:glossary> or a
combination of the two.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="writing board"><esp:techterms
					      term="scribe">Scribes</esp:techterms>
often wrote on wooden boards which were covered in a thin layer of
wax. The wax could be warmed to smooth the surface and erase the
writing on it. Writing boards had the advantage of being more portable
than <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablets</esp:techterms>  and could
be hinged together to form <esp:techterms
term="polyptych">polyptychs</esp:techterms>. Fortunately for modern
scholarship, in Assyrian times the perishable writing board never completely replaced the relatively indestructible <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablet</esp:techterms>  - or we would have almost no surviving written evidence to work with.</esp:termsdefinition>

<!-- Z -->
<esp:termsdefinition term="ziggurat">Stepped tower in or near a
temple precinct and itself a place of worship as well as a major
landmark and symbol of a city's prestige. In Kalhu the ziggurat was
associated with <esp:link page="ziggurat"
bookmark="h_thezigguratandthetempleofninurta">Ninurta's
temple</esp:link>.</esp:termsdefinition>

<esp:termsdefinition term="xxxxxxxx"></esp:termsdefinition>

					</esp:techterms-list>
					
					<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/>

				<p>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/>.</p>

			</body>

		</html>

	</esp:page>

