<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
	<esp:name>Cuneiform on clay</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Writing cuneiform on clay</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>

<p class="firstpara"><esp:techterms term="cuneiform">Cuneiform</esp:techterms> is designed to be written on clay. The wedge-shaped impressions that give cuneiform its modern name are made by pressing a <esp:techterms term="stylus">stylus</esp:techterms> into the surface of a moist clay <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablet</esp:techterms>. The stylus is then lifted back up ready to make the next impression, rather than dragged across the surface as we would use a pen. Some tablets were enclosed within a clay envelope. And tablets or envelopes were sometimes stamped or sealed. There are strong connections between a language, the writing system in which it is written, the medium on which it is usually written and the technique of writing. The <esp:link page="sumerian">Sumerian</esp:link> and <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/knpp/cuneiformrevealed/akkadianlanguage/Akkadian" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Akkadian</esp:link> languages were typically written in cuneiform script on clay but was also sometimes <esp:link page="materials-others">written on other media</esp:link>.</p>

<esp:h><esp:bookmark id="shapes" title="object shapes and sizes">Object shapes and sizes</esp:bookmark></esp:h>

<esp:image file="langscripts/BM90976.jpg" description="Clay moulded into the shape of a clenched human fist, complete with fingernails. Cuneiform text is written down each of the fingers" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/langscripts/BM90976-40cm.jpg" title="View large image"/><esp:caption><b>Image 1</b>: This <esp:techterms term="clay hand">clay hand</esp:techterms> lists the titles of king <esp:link page="assurnasirpal2">Assurnasirpal II</esp:link>. Its first line says it is from "the palace", meaning the <esp:link page="northwestpalace">Northwest Palace</esp:link> <esp:ref referent="grayson1991" page="373-4, A.0.101.123"/>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=369021&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 90976</esp:link>. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/langscripts/BM90976-40cm.jpg" hide-print="yes" rel="external" title="View large image">View large image (193KB)</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image> 
	
<p>Most cuneiform inscriptions were written on clay tablets. Different shapes and sizes of tablet were used for different purposes, but most fit comfortably in the hand. The <esp:link page="vte-intro">Succession Treaties</esp:link> of <esp:glossary term="Esarhaddon (person)">Esarhaddon</esp:glossary> are written on unusually large and thick tablets. Various types of clay were used, some containing stones or shells, others with very few <esp:techterms term="inclusion">inclusions</esp:techterms>. This is similar to our use of different sizes and qualities of paper for newspapers, letters and post-it notes.</p>

<esp:image file="langscripts/bm108775-bm131129.jpg" description="Two clay foundation cylinders of Assyrian kings, inscribed with cuneiform text" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/langscripts/bm108775-bm131129-large.jpg" hide-print="yes" rel="external" title="View large image"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img120"><b>Image 2</b></esp:bookmark>: Left: a typical cylinder of <esp:glossary term="Sargon II (person)">Sargon II</esp:glossary>, with flattened faces. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=1351262&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 108775</esp:link>. This example <esp:glossary term="Dur-Šarruken (place)">Dur-Šarruken</esp:glossary> (modern Khorsabad), but Sargon deposited similar examples in Kalhu. Right: a typical cylinder of <esp:glossary term="Esarhaddon (person)">Esarhaddon</esp:glossary> from Kalhu, narrower and fully rounded. British Museum <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=1351302&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">BM 131129</esp:link> (ND1126). <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/langscripts/bm108775-bm131129-large.jpg" hide-print="yes" rel="external" title="View large image">View large image.</esp:link> Image: Jon Taylor for the Nimrud Project <esp:link page="copyright">CC-BY-SA 3.0</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Clay could also be formed into other shapes for special purposes. <esp:link page="legaldocuments" bookmark="loan dockets">Loans of barley</esp:link> were written on triangular <esp:techterms term="docket">dockets</esp:techterms>. Assyrian kings of the first millennium BC had their <esp:link page="inscriptions">inscriptions</esp:link> written on a variety of objects: tablets, cones, bricks, prisms and cylinders. The exact text of each was discussed and carefully chosen. The objects themselves were carefully chosen as well. Two popular types of object chosen to carry royal inscriptions were prisms and cylinders. The size and shape of these varies from one ruler to the next (<b>Image 2</b>). And inscriptions are found even on <esp:techterms term="clay hand">architectural fittings in the shape of hands</esp:techterms> (<b>Image 1</b>).</p>

<esp:image file="langscripts/nimrud-tablet-shapes.jpg" description="Some typical shapes for the various types of text found at Nimrud" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/langscripts/nimrud-tablet-shapes-large.jpg" hide-print="yes" rel="external" title="View large image"/><esp:caption><b>Image 3</b>: Some typical tablet shapes for the various types of text found at Nimrud. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/langscripts/nimrud-tablet-shapes-large.jpg" hide-print="yes" rel="external" title="View large image">View large image.</esp:link> Image: Jon Taylor for the Nimrud Project <esp:link page="copyright">CC-BY-SA 3.0</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Scribes also chose certain shapes and sizes for each of the different types of text from daily life. <esp:techterms term="conveyance">"Conveyances"</esp:techterms> (such as the sale of slaves or land), for example, are characterised by their <esp:techterms term="portrait format">portrait format</esp:techterms> and band of <esp:techterms term="seal, sealing">seal</esp:techterms> <esp:techterms term="impression">impressions</esp:techterms> across the upper <esp:techterms term="obverse, reverse">obverse</esp:techterms>. The more ephemeral contracts (for things such as loans) meanwhile are smaller, <esp:techterms term="landscape format">landscape format</esp:techterms> tablets, with envelopes. The envelope was sealed, the tablet not. A typical letter would be portrait format, but thinner than a conveyance and not sealed. <esp:link page="scholarlyworks">Scholarly tablets</esp:link> are often written in portrait orientation, in one or two columns. <b>Image 3</b> shows some common tablet types from Nimrud.</p>

<esp:h>Working with clay</esp:h>

<esp:image file="langscripts/nd_2627.jpg" description="Close up of clay tablet section, showing 'inclusions' of other material within the clay. Inclusions of (now decayed) plant matter appear as small holes but stones remain visible in the clay" position="float"><esp:caption><b>Image 4</b>: Many stone <esp:techterms term="inclusion">inclusions</esp:techterms> are present in the clay of this tablet from Kalhu. The tablet itself contains an 8th century BC letter about purchasing horses (translation online: <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/P393666/html" rel="external" hide-print="yes">SAA 19:168</esp:link>). British Museum <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=1604873&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">ND 2627</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Clay for making tablets was readily available from rivers. So too were reeds for making a stylus. The clay for tablets could first be processed to remove stones and plant matter. This did not always happen, however, and many tablets contain such <esp:techterms term="inclusion">inclusions</esp:techterms> (<b>Image 4</b>). Indeed, tablets from Nimrud contain inclusions much more often than those from <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary>, for example.</p>

<p><esp:techterms term="Assyriology">Assyriologist</esp:techterms> Henry Saggs tested the clays of tablets from Nimrud <esp:ref referent="saggs2001" page="2"/>. He found that tablets originally from <esp:glossary term="Babylonia (place)">Babylonia</esp:glossary> contained a higher level of <esp:techterms term="lime">lime</esp:techterms> than their Assyrian counterparts. This made them softer, and less likely to suffer cracking, but more susceptible to damage from salts coming to the surface and breaking off text as they crystallised.</p>

<esp:image file="langscripts/firing_nd4401.jpg" description="Tablet surface with visible firing holes" position="float"><esp:caption><b>Image 5</b>: <esp:link page="scholarlyworks">Scholarly tablet</esp:link> of <i>tamītu</i> prayers (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/P363477/" hide-print="yes" rel="external">CTN 4 62</esp:link>), with visible "firing holes". Despite their name, the exact function of these holes is not known. British Museum <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=1606083&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">ND 4401</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image> 

<p>Most tablets were not fired in antiquity. Left to dry in the air (preferably not in the sun, which dries them too quickly), tablets become hard enough to withstand normal handling and storage. This means that they could potentially be recycled by melting down the clay in water, although in many cases old tablets were simply discarded. Tablets intended to survive for very long periods could be fired. Such tablets sometimes contain what Assyriologists call “firing holes”, the actual function of which was probably not to assist in the firing process, however (<b>Image 5</b>).</p>

<esp:h><esp:bookmark id="tablet_making" title="tablet making">Tablet making</esp:bookmark></esp:h>

<esp:image file="langscripts/nd_2661.jpg" description="End view of clay tablet, showing visible individual layers where the sheet of clay has been rolled into a tablet shape" position="float"><esp:caption><b>Image 6</b>: End view of a tablet, showing visible individual layers where the sheet of clay has been rolled into a tablet shape. This 8th century BC tablet is inscribed with a letter to the king about mules for a postal service (translation online: <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/P393656/html" rel="external" hide-print="yes">SAA 19: 141</esp:link>). British Museum <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=1605728&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">ND 2661</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image> 

<esp:image file="langscripts/nd_2370.jpg" description="End view of tablet, showing a skin of fine clay wrapped around a core of rougher clay" position="float"><esp:caption><b>Image 7</b>: End view of a tablet, showing a skin of fine clay wrapped around a core of rougher clay. This 8th century BC tablet is a letter reporting on an <esp:glossary term="Ionia (place)">Ionian</esp:glossary> raid on a western <esp:techterms term="province">province</esp:techterms> of Assyria (translation online: <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/P393612/html" rel="external" hide-print="yes">SAA 19: 25</esp:link>). British Museum <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=1602844&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">ND 2370</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image> 

<p>Many tablets survive only in broken condition. While this obviously means that we have lost some of the text, it does sometimes allow us to see how the tablet was made. Often we can see that the <esp:techterms term="scribe">scribe</esp:techterms> had rolled a sheet of clay into the tablet shape (<b>Image 6</b>). Another technique saw a skin of fine clay wrapped around a core of rougher clay (<b>Image 7</b>).</p>

<esp:h>Sealing</esp:h>

<esp:image file="langscripts/nd_2325.jpg" description="Clay tablet with inscribed cuneiform text, with a circular seal stamped three times into the surface" position="float"><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img126"><b>Image 8</b></esp:bookmark>: Cuneiform tablet recording the sale of a slave woman named Arbela-lamur ("May I see <esp:glossary term="Arbela (place)">Arbela</esp:glossary>!"). An officer in the <esp:techterms term="crown prince">crown prince</esp:techterms>’s retinue has certified the sale by impressing his stamp seal on to the tablet. The tablet dates from the reign of king <esp:glossary term="Assurbanipal (person)">Assurbanipal</esp:glossary> <esp:ref referent="parker1954" page="42"/>, <esp:ref referent="parker1955" page="96, plate XXIV, no. 1"/>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=1549824&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">ND 2325</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image> 

<p>Seals had long been used to confirm identity or indicate authority. The <esp:link page="vte-intro">Succession Treaties of Esarhaddon</esp:link> are sealed with no fewer than <esp:link page="vte-detail" bookmark="seal impressions">three cylinder seals</esp:link>. During the <esp:techterms term="Neo-Assyrian">Neo-Assyrian</esp:techterms> period, old-fashioned cylinder seals gave way to stamp seals (<b>Image 8</b>). Instead of being rolled across the surface, a stamp seal was simply impressed into the clay. Sometimes an old cylinder seal was kept, and was used as though it were a stamp seal.</p> 

<esp:image file="langscripts/nd_211.jpg" description="Clay tablet with inscribed cuneiform text, which has been 'sealed' using the fingernails of 11 men. The fingernail impressions run in a horizontal row across the top of the tablet" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=1348689&amp;objectId=1536891&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><b>Image 9</b>: A row of fingernail ‘signatures’ runs in a horizontal row across the top of this tablet, <esp:techterms term="seal, sealing">sealing</esp:techterms> the document. It records <esp:glossary term="Bel-tarṣi-ilumma (person)">Bel-tarṣi-ilumma</esp:glossary> paying off a huge debt ("2 talents, 20 minas of bronze") for someone named Sabiri. From Room 6 of the <esp:link page="governorspalace">Governor's Palace</esp:link>, 793 BC <esp:ref referent="postgate1973" page="121"/>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=1536891&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">ND 211</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=1348689&amp;objectId=1536891&amp;partId=1" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Another method of sealing was to use a fingernail. In the tablet shown in <b>Image 9</b> men impress their fingernail “instead of their seal” to certify that the debts owed to them have been repaid. It has been suggested that some fingernail impressions were made with a special tool.</p> 

<esp:h>Enveloping</esp:h>

<esp:image file="langscripts/nd_3445.jpg" description="Photograph of inscribed clay tablet and the inscribed clay envelope that surrounded it" position="float"><esp:caption><b>Image 10</b>: Clay tablet (bottom) and its envelope (top). This loan document from 636<esp:techterms term="eponym">*</esp:techterms> BC was excavated from Room 19 of Town Wall house 57, Nimrud <esp:ref referent="wiseman1953" page="143"/>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=1605930&amp;partId=1" hide-print="yes" rel="external">ND 3445</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>There was a very long tradition in Mesopotamia of enclosing texts within protective envelopes (<b>Image 10</b>). Like a modern envelope, the Assyrian type was made from a folded sheet (although in this case made of clay rather than paper). In the case of a letter, the name of both sender and recipient were written on the envelope, together with a short greeting and a seal impression to confirm the sender’s identity. Few envelopes survive, because the act of opening them meant breaking them; the broken pieces would then be discarded. </p> 

<esp:h><esp:bookmark id="stylus" title="stylus">Stylus</esp:bookmark></esp:h>

<!--<esp:image file="langscripts/stylus.jpg" description="Carved stone relief showing a scribe holding a stylus" position="float" hide-print="yes"><esp:caption><b>Image 11</b>: Carved stone relief showing a scribe holding a stylus. ACCESSION NUMBER?<esp:link url="XXXXXXXXXX" rel="external">XXXXXX</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>-->

<p>The word for stylus is written with signs that mean “tablet reed”. Reed was a natural and very suitable material for a stylus. Traces of the fibres of the reed can sometimes be seen in the <esp:techterms term="wedge">wedges</esp:techterms> of cuneiform. Wood, bone and other materials could also be used. No original Assyrian styluses survive.</p> 

<esp:h>Storage</esp:h>

<esp:image file="langscripts/filing.jpg" description="Excavated room within the temple of the god Nabu at Nimrud" position="float"><esp:caption><b>Image 11</b>: An Assyrian filing cabinet? The archive room in <esp:link page="assurnasirpal2">Assurnasirpal II's</esp:link> <esp:link page="northwestpalace">Northwest Palace</esp:link> during excavations by the <esp:techterms term="British School of Archaeology in Iraq">British School of Archaeology in Iraq</esp:techterms> in the 1950s. Photo: <esp:link page="copyright" bookmark="BISIimages">BSAI/BISI</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Mesopotamian scribes stored their tablets in jars, bags or on shelves. Max Mallowan, who excavated in Nimrud in the 1950s, suggested that the feature in archive room ZT 4 of the <esp:link page="northwestpalace">Northwest Palace</esp:link> should be interpreted as a filing cabinet for tablets (<b>Image 11</b>).</p>  

<esp:reading referent="cartwrighttaylor2011"/>
<esp:reading referent="parker1955"/>
<esp:reading referent="radner1995"/>
<esp:reading referent="taylor2011"/>
<!--<esp:reading referent="taylor2014"/> TO UPDATE WHEN BOOK APPEARS-->
<esp:reading referent="saggs2001"/>

<p>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/>.<br/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/></p>

<esp:author first-names="Jonathan" last-name="Taylor"/>
</body></html>
</esp:page>
