<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
	<esp:name>Sumerian</esp:name>
	<esp:title>The Sumerian language</esp:title>

	<html><head></head><body>

<p class="firstpara">Sumerian is the earliest documented language in Mesopotamia, and perhaps the world. Long after it ceased to be spoken as a mother tongue, knowledge of it continued to be maintained as a prestigious part of Mesopotamian scholarship until the death of cuneiform writing some two thousand years later.</p>

<esp:image file="langscripts/BM-140852.jpg" description="Clay tablet inscribed with details of food rations, dating from c.3300-3100 BC" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=327221&amp;partId=1" title="View large image of BM 140852 on British Museum website" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><b>Image 1</b>: Clay tablet inscribed with details of food rations, dating from c.3300-3100 BC from southern Mesopotamia. Note the pictorial nature of the signs, such as the human head with bread in the lower register, typical of ration texts. The sign is used in later Sumerian to mean “eat”. The round indentations record numbers. <esp:link url="https://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/highlights/highlight_objects/me/r/record_of_food_supplies.aspx" rel="external" hide-print="yes">BM 140852</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=327221&amp;partId=1" title="View large image of BM 140852 on British Museum website" rel="external" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Sumerian emerged as a written language in what is now southern Iraq at the end of the 4th millennium BC. It therefore vies with Egyptian for the title of the oldest recorded language in the world. The word “Sumerian” derives from the <esp:techterms term="Akkadian">Akkadian</esp:techterms> word <i>šumeru</i>; the Sumerians themselves referred to their language simply as eme-gi<sub>7</sub> (“native tongue”). Sumerian was written on clay <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablets</esp:techterms> and other durable materials such as stone using the <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/knpp/cuneiformrevealed" rel="external" hide-print="yes">cuneiform script</esp:link>. Many of the earliest signs were pictorial in nature (<b>Image 1</b>) but they gradually developed more stylised and linear forms (<b>Image 2</b>). The script itself functioned as a mixture of logograms, which represent whole words, and phonetic signs, which represent vowels and syllables. Impressed signs were also used to record numbers <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/dccmt/metrology/" rel="external" hide-print="yes">in a variety of different arithmetical bases</esp:link>.</p>

<esp:h>“A scribe who does not know Sumerian, what (kind of) a scribe is he?”</esp:h>

<p>Eventually, the cuneiform script which had been developed for Sumerian was adapted for <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/knpp/cuneiformrevealed/akkadianlanguage" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Akkadian</esp:link>, a <esp:techterms term="Semitic language">Semitic language</esp:techterms> also spoken in Mesopotamia but linguistically unrelated to Sumerian. The two languages were used side by side until Sumerian died out as a mother tongue, sometime around 2000 BC (the exact date remains the subject of much debate). However, this did not spell the end of Sumerian. Its influence on Akkadian remained visible in Sumerian loanwords and certain grammatical features as well as in the logograms (or “Sumerograms”) which had originated as Sumerian cuneiform signs. This was especially true in the <esp:techterms term="Neo-Assyrian">Neo-Assyrian</esp:techterms> period, when the use of logograms as opposed to syllabic writings became a particularly popular way of showcasing one's learnedness and appreciation of  cuneiform's complexity.</p>

<esp:image file="langscripts/bm-15826.jpg" description="Clay tablet inscribed in Sumerian, c.2500 BC, showing a more linear form of the cuneiform script" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=326405&amp;partId=1" title="View large image of BM 15826 on British Museum website" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><b>Image 2</b>: Clay tablet inscribed in Sumerian, c.2500 BC, showing a more linear form of the cuneiform script. The inscription gives an account of <esp:techterms term="silver">silver</esp:techterms> and other commodities and is probably from the Sumerian city of <esp:glossary term="Šuruppag (place)">Šuruppag</esp:glossary>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=326405&amp;partId=1" title="View catalogue entry for BM 15826 on British Museum website" hide-print="yes">BM 15826</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=326405&amp;partId=1" title="View large image of BM 15826 on British Museum website" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Even more importantly, such was the perceived importance and prestige of Sumerian that it continued to be maintained as a language of cult and scholarship, much like Latin in medieval Europe. An old Sumerian proverb asks, “A <esp:techterms term="scribe">scribe</esp:techterms> who does not know Sumerian, what (kind of) a scribe is he?” (<esp:link url="http://etcsl.orinst.ox.ac.uk/cgi-bin/etcsl.cgi?text=t.6.1.02&amp;display=Crit&amp;charenc=gcirc&amp;lineid=t6102.p47" rel="external" hide-print="yes">ETCSL 6.1.02 80</esp:link>), and this continued to hold true in first millennium Assyria. Scribal training remained bilingual, but scribes who grew up speaking the Assyrian dialect of Akkadian now had to acquire Sumerian as a second language. To do so, they relied on many of the same sorts of resources that we still use in language learning today, from <esp:techterms term="lexical list">lexical lists</esp:techterms> and grammars to bilingual texts.</p>

<p>In fact, we owe our ability to understand Sumerian to these ancient learning tools, as they have provided <esp:techterms term="Assyriology">Assyriologists</esp:techterms> with an invaluable means of deciphering the language through the much better understood Akkadian. Without these texts, our ability to appreciate the rich Sumerian-language culture would be greatly diminished, although the language itself continues to present significant challenges in terms of both grammar and vocabulary.</p>

<esp:h>Keeping Sumerian alive in the first millennium BC</esp:h>

<esp:image file="langscripts/bm-rm367.jpg" description="Fragment of Tablet III of the lexical list ur5-ra = hubullu" position="float"><esp:link url="https://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=297061&amp;partId=1" title="View large image of Rm.367 on British Museum website" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><b>Image 3</b>: Fragment of Tablet III of the <esp:techterms term="lexical list">lexical list</esp:techterms> ur<sub>5</sub>-ra = <i>hubullu</i> (so called after its opening line which gives the Sumerian and Akkadian terms for “interest-bearing loan”) from the library of king <esp:glossary term="Assurbanipal (person)">Assurbanipal</esp:glossary>. The series comprises twenty-four tablets organised around a common theme; Tablet III lists trees and woods. The document is arranged in two columns, the first of which gives the Sumerian term while the second provides the Akkadian equivalent. <esp:link url="https://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=297061&amp;partId=1" title="View catalogue entry for Rm.367 on British Museum website" hide-print="yes">Rm.367</esp:link>. <esp:link url="https://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=297061&amp;partId=1" title="View large image of Rm.367 on British Museum website" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>By the first millennium BC, compositions only in Sumerian had become fairly rare, probably reflecting the crucial role which Akkadian played in providing access to Sumerian. Such monolingual texts tend to record <esp:techterms term="incantation">incantations</esp:techterms> used in religious <esp:techterms term="rite, ritual">rituals</esp:techterms>. Much more common were bilingual compositions featuring both languages, whether in separate columns or with the Akkadian translation inserted into the body of the Sumerian text to provide a line-by-line translation (see <b>Image 3</b>).</p>

<p>Most of the Sumerian texts from the Neo-Assyrian period come from the cities of <esp:glossary term="Assur (place)">Assur</esp:glossary>, the religious capital of Assyria, and from <esp:glossary term="Nineveh (place)">Nineveh</esp:glossary>, the site of the <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/knpp/essentials/assurbanipalslibrary" rel="external" hide-print="yes">famous library</esp:link> of king <esp:glossary term="Assurbanipal (person)">Assurbanipal</esp:glossary>. Excavations in the city of Kalhu have also uncovered numerous bilingual tablets which were once housed in <esp:link page="ezida">Ezida</esp:link>, the city's temple to the god <esp:link page="nabu">Nabu</esp:link>. Bilingual tablets including literary compositions and cultic texts have also been found in the tiny town of <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/cams/gkab/contexts/huzirina/" hide-print="yes" rel="external">Huzirina</esp:link> in <esp:glossary term="Anatolia (place)">Anatolia</esp:glossary>, far away from the Assyrian heartland, demonstrating the wide spread of Mesopotamian scribal culture.</p>

<p>In Kalhu itself, Sumerian featured in the <esp:link page="scholarlyworks">scholarly works</esp:link> kept in <esp:link page="ezida">Nabu's temple</esp:link>.The included Sumerian and bilingual <esp:link page="scholarlyworks" bookmark="h_wardingoffevil">prayers and incantations</esp:link>, <esp:link page="scholarlyworks" bookmark="h_invokingdivinesupport">cultic hymns</esp:link>, and <esp:link page="scholarlyworks" bookmark="h_constructingtextualmeaning">lexical lists</esp:link>, as well as literary compositions <esp:link page="ninurta" bookmark="h_mythicalheroconquererofchaosninurtandthetabletofdestinies">about the hero god Ninurta</esp:link>.</p>
<!-- Replace with paragraph on Sumerian at Kalhu


<p>The collection which once formed part of Assurbanipal's library contained a wealth of tablets gathered or copied by scribes and agents of the king, and included many fine examples of texts from the Sumero-Babylonian scribal tradition. Many of these tablets formed part of the working libraries of the king's <esp:link page="professions">learned advisors</esp:link>. For instance, Sumerian and bilingual prayers, cultic hymns and songs represented the lore of the <esp:techterms term="lamenter">lamentation priest</esp:techterms> (<i>kalû</i>), while incantations and rituals formed part of the scholarly repertoire of the <esp:techterms term="exorcist">exorcist</esp:techterms> (<i>āšipu</i>).</p> -->

<esp:h>Beyond cuneiform: Sumerian and the Hellenistic world</esp:h>

<esp:image file="langscripts/bm-34816.jpg" description="The reverse of a tablet from the so-called Graeco-Babyloniaca" position="float"><esp:link url="https://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=327185&amp;partId=1" title="View large image of BM 34816 on British Museum website" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><b>Image 4</b>: The <esp:techterms term="obverse, reverse">reverse</esp:techterms> of a tablet from the so-called Graeco-Babyloniaca, showing a rendering into the Greek alphabet of an incantation against evil spirits which is written in Sumerian and Akkadian cuneiform on the tablet's obverse; probably from Babylon, dating from the last few centuries BC. <esp:link url="https://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=327185&amp;partId=1" title="View catalogue entry for BM 34816 on British Museum website" hide-print="yes">BM 34816</esp:link>. <esp:link url="https://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=327185&amp;partId=1" title="View large image of BM 34816 on British Museum website" hide-print="yes">View large image on British Museum website.</esp:link>. © The Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Knowledge of Akkadian and Sumerian survived the demise of Assyria at the end of the 7th century BC, as well as that of Assyria's successor, the <esp:techterms term="Neo-Babylonian">Neo-Babylonian</esp:techterms> empire. Even after the Mesopotamian lands were absorbed into empires ruled by foreign-born kings, the Sumero-Babylonian scribal tradition lived on. A group of remarkable documents, known as the Graeco-Babyloniaca and dating mainly between the 1st centuries BC and AD, shows evidence of the transmission of Sumerian and Akkadian to Greek-speaking trainee scribes (or possibly attempts to write those languages using the alphabetic rather than cuneiform script). Sumerian and Akkadian text was written out in cuneiform on one side and transliterated into Greek characters on the other (see <b>Image 4</b>). The result is a fascinating insight into the longevity and continued appeal of Mesopotamian knowledge.</p> 

<esp:reading referent="black2007"/>
<esp:reading referent="fincke2003-2004"/>
<esp:reading referent="geller1997"/>
<esp:reading referent="michalowski2004"/>
<esp:reading referent="westenholz2007"/>

<p>For an overview of Sumerian grammar, see the <esp:link url="http://etcsl.orinst.ox.ac.uk/edition2/language.php" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Electronic Text Corpus of Sumerian Literature</esp:link>.</p>

<p>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/><br/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/></p>
<esp:author first-names="Silvie" last-name="Zamazalová"/>

</body></html>
</esp:page>
