<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>
	<esp:name>Iraq Museum displays</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Displaying and redisplaying Nimrud at the Iraq Museum</esp:title>

	<html><head>
</head><body>

<p class="firstpara">On this page, Dr Lamia al-Gailani discusses how Nimrud artefacts have been displayed in the <esp:techterms term="Iraq Museum">Iraq Museum</esp:techterms> in <esp:glossary term="Baghdad (place)">Baghdad</esp:glossary> over the past century.  Dr al-Gailani has worked with the Iraq Museum for many decades and has recently been carrying out archival work on the Museum's history. Here she presents some historical photographs from the Museum's rich archival collections.</p> 

<p>The first premises for the Baghdad Archaeological Museum were acquired in 1926, with the assistance of British archaeologist <esp:glossary term="Bell, Gertrude (person)">Gertrude Bell</esp:glossary>. This former law training school in Al-Mamoun Street <!-- Image? Pictured around 1925 --> was intended to be a temporary home until a purpose-built space could be constructed, but the museum had to wait 40 years for this to be realised. A new museum building was constructed in the 1960s and still houses the Iraq Museum today (<b>Image 1</b>).</p>

<esp:image file="im/assyrian_gate_iraq_museum.jpg" description="Replica of an Assyrian city gate from the city of Khorsabad, Iraq Museum's Children's Museum" position="inline"><esp:link url="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/b/bc/National_Museum_Iraq.jpg" title="Large image of replica Assyrian city gate, Iraq Museum" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img179"><b>Image 1</b></esp:bookmark>: Replica of an Assyrian city gate from the city of <esp:glossary term="Khorsabad (place)">Khorsabad</esp:glossary>, part of the Iraq Museum. The gate became part of the Children's Museum in 1982. The brick-filled hole in the gate's centre is repaired damage, <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/about_us/museum_activity/middle_east/iraq_project/2003_invasion_and_aftermath.aspx" rel="external" hide-print="yes">caused by a shell</esp:link> during fighting in <esp:techterms term="Iraq War">2003</esp:techterms>. Image: <esp:link url="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:National_Museum_Iraq.jpg" title="Large image of replica Assyrian city gate, Iraq Museum" hide-print="yes">Public domain</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/b/bc/National_Museum_Iraq.jpg" title="Large image of replica Assyrian city gate, Iraq Museum" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link> (707 KB).</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>There is an impressive amount of material in the Iraq Museum's archives that has been collected and accumulated over the decades. The following images are not intended to give a complete chronological history of the museum, but rather some snapshots, because I am working with what material I can find. A lot of things are still chaotic at the Museum and the archives are a hotchpotch at the moment. For example, there are very good <esp:techterms term="microfilm">microfilms</esp:techterms> for the Islamic manuscripts made the 1990s, although they now don’t have a microfilm machine, so people can’t see it. Some other parts of the archives haven't been worked on - a lot is still uncatalogued or only partially catalogued.</p>

<p>If the records were in date order, it would be easier to go through the material for the 1920s and 30s, but it’s not organised according to date. There’s now a very dedicated head of department, and people are working on it, but there are language issues when dealing with a lot of the early material. Most of the people who work with the archives only know Arabic, so it is very difficult to categorise documents in languages such as English or German. So the first step in my work is going through material and scanning, without much detailed reading. Later I hope I’ll be able to sit and read in more detail.</p>

<esp:h>The old museum</esp:h>
<p>Most of the the objects from Nimrud at the Iraq Museum come from <esp:link page="nd1950">1950s excavations</esp:link> or later, but a few arrived as early as the 1920s. We can see the way they were exhibited by looking at early photographs.</p>

<esp:image file="im/IMG_0004.jpg" description="Assembled crowd seated in the museum, with two colossal statues standing in the background. King Faisal stands next to High Commissioner Sir Henry Dobbs" position="inline"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/im/IMG_0004-large.jpg" title="Large image of assembled crowd with King Faisal and Nimrud statues in the background" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img180"><b>Image 2</b></esp:bookmark>: King <esp:glossary term="Faisal I (person)">Faisal I</esp:glossary> unveiling a bust of Gertrude Bell at the Iraq Museum. Colossal statues of guards from Nimrud tower over the assembled crowd. Image: Iraq Museum. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/im/IMG_0004-large.jpg" title="Large image of assembled crowd with King Faisal and Nimrud statues in the background" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link> (669 KB).</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>The first objects from Nimrud that arrived at the Museum are two colossal statues of guards from <esp:link page="ezida">Nabu's temple</esp:link>, which were found by <esp:glossary term="Rassam, Hormuzd (person)">Rassam</esp:glossary>, I think, but were left at Nimrud. They were brought to the Museum at the end of 1926, transported by the <esp:techterms term="Iraq Petroleum Company">Iraq Petroleum Company</esp:techterms>. It’s a tradition that the oil company brings everything that is too heavy. This was after Gertrude Bell's time, but she must have worked to get them. The statues are pictured in the background of <b>Image 2</b>, which shows king <esp:glossary term="Faisal I (person)">Faisal I</esp:glossary> unveiling a bust of Gertrude Bell at the museum. King Faisal is talking to the High Commissioner <esp:glossary term="Dobbs, Sir Henry Robert Conway (person)">Sir Henry Dobbs</esp:glossary>, and behind him <!--'at the corner nearer to this'--> is the Minister of Education, <esp:glossary term="Chelebi, Abdul Hussein (person)">Abdul Hussein Chelebi</esp:glossary>, who is the grandfather of a well-known politician today. The objects were not intended to be the main subject here, but are luckily captured on film due to their large size.</p>

<esp:image file="im/IMG_0043.jpg" description="The Shah of Iran visiting the Iraq Museum, walking past walking past one of the winged bulls from Nimrud" position="inline"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/im/IMG_0004-large.jpg" title="Large image of the Shah of Iran visiting the Iraq Museum" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img181"><b>Image 3</b></esp:bookmark>: The <esp:link url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mohammad_Reza_Pahlavi" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Shah of Iran</esp:link>, visiting the Museum when he was still crown prince. Walking next to him, past one of the winged bulls from Nimrud, is the <esp:techterms term="Director-General of Antiquities">Director-General of Antiquities</esp:techterms>, <esp:glossary term="al-Husri, Sati' (person)">Sati' al-Husri</esp:glossary>. Behind him is archaeologist <esp:glossary term="Lloyd, Seton (person)">Seton Lloyd</esp:glossary>, then President of the British School of Archaeology in Iraq. Image: Iraq Museum. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/im/IMG_0004-large.jpg" title="Large image of the Shah of Iran visiting the Iraq Museum" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link> (436 KB).</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Nimrud objects also feature in <b>Image 3</b>, taken in the 1930s during a visit by the <esp:link url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mohammad_Reza_Pahlavi" rel="external" hide-print="yes">Shah of Iran</esp:link> when he was still <esp:techterms term="crown prince">crown prince</esp:techterms>. Here the visitors are walking past a <esp:techterms term="colossal bull">winged bull</esp:techterms> from the <esp:link page="northwestpalace">Northwest Palace</esp:link>, so we can see that the bull was definitely in the museum by the 1930s. It is one of two winged bulls from Nimrud that were in the courtyard at the museum's entrance.</p>

<esp:image file="im/IMG_0003-detail.jpg" description="Group of men sitting in one of the museum galleries, surrounded by stone reliefs" position="inline"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/im/IMG_0003-large.jpg" title="Large image of a group of men sitting in one of the museum galleries, surrounded by stone reliefs" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img182"><b>Image 4</b></esp:bookmark>: A group of men sitting in one of the Iraq Museum's galleries, surrounded by stone <esp:techterms term="bas-relief">bas-reliefs</esp:techterms>. Image: Iraq Museum. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/im/IMG_0003-large.jpg" title="Large image of a group of men sitting in one of the museum galleries, surrounded by stone reliefs" hide-print="yes">View full image</esp:link> (223 KB).</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p><b>Image 4</b> shows a group of men sitting in the Assyrian room. It's difficult to know exactly what event is taking place here, but I think it was a medical conference. Incidental records like this show us how objects were exhibited, even though they are not purposely-taken photos of displays.</p>

<esp:image file="im/IM-4.jpg" description="Photo of the Assyrian room at the Iraq Museum" position="inline"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/im/IM-4-large.jpg" title="Large version of the Assyrian room at the Iraq Museum" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img183"><b>Image 5</b></esp:bookmark>: The Assyrian room at the Iraq Museum. Image: Iraq Museum. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/im/IM-4-large.jpg" title="Large image of the Assyrian room at the Iraq Museum" hide-print="yes">View full image</esp:link> (77 KB).</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Early displays contained a mixture of objects from Nimrud and from <esp:glossary term="Khorsabad (place)">Khorsabad</esp:glossary>. <b>Image 5</b> shows the Assyrian room itself, mostly containing Khorsabad material. This is the earliest picture of it, with a model of the city in the centre.</p>

<esp:image file="im/IMG_0016-detail.jpg" description="King Faisal II with Dr Naji al-Aseel, Director of Antiquities, standing in front of a display case containing a carved ivory representation of a woman's face" position="inline"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/im/IMG_0016-large.jpg" title="Large version of King Faisal II with Dr. Naji al-Aseel, Director of Antiquities, standing in front of a display case containing an ivory carving of a woman's face" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img184"><b>Image 6</b></esp:bookmark>: <esp:glossary term="al-Aseel, Naji (person)">Dr Naji al-Aseel</esp:glossary>, Director-General of Antiquities, and king <esp:glossary term="Faisal II (person)"> Faisal II</esp:glossary> in front of the 'Mona Lisa of Nimrud', a finely carved ivory female head found <esp:link page="maadog" bookmark="h_founddownapalacewell">along with other objects</esp:link> down a well in the Northwest Palace. Image: Iraq Museum. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/im/IMG_0016-large.jpg" title="Large image of King Faisal II with Dr. Naji al-Aseel, Director of Antiquities, standing in front of a display case containing an ivory carving of a woman's face" hide-print="yes">View full image</esp:link> (77 KB).</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>I looked for pictures for the smaller finds from Nimrud but couldn't find any. Unfortunately, I think people were not interested. Either they didn’t have cameras at the time, or they didn’t waste film on just photographing cases. A rare exception is the iconic object shown in <b>Image 6</b>. Here king <esp:glossary term="Faisal II (person)">Faisal II</esp:glossary> is standing in front of a special case in the old museum building, containing a finely carved <esp:techterms term="ivory">ivory</esp:techterms> female head. The head was discovered down a well in Room NN of the <esp:link page="northwestpalace">Northwest Palace</esp:link>. <esp:glossary term="al-Aseel, Naji (person)"> Dr Naji al-Aseel</esp:glossary>, Director-General of Antiquities, nicknamed the piece the ‘<esp:link page="ivories" bookmark="h_agathaandtheivories">Mona Lisa of Nimrud</esp:link>' because of its fine craftsmanship. The 'Mona Lisa' became one of the site's most famous discoveries, appearing on the front page of the British periodical <esp:techterms term="Illustrated London News"><i>The Illustrated London News</i></esp:techterms> in August 1952 <esp:ref referent="mallowan1966" page="260"/><esp:ref referent="iln1952-08-16" page="1"/>.</p>

<esp:h>The new museum</esp:h>

<esp:image file="im/SDC10978-detail.jpg" description="Colour photograph of the outside of the Iraq Museum, showing a stone statue from Nimrud, of a standing god, on a plinth in front of the building" position="inline"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/im/SDC10978-large.jpg" title="Large image of the outside of the Iraq Museum" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img185"><b>Image 7</b></esp:bookmark>: A stone statue from <esp:link page="ezida">Nabu's temple</esp:link> at Nimrud, outside the Iraq Museum. Image: Iraq Museum. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/im/SDC10978-large.jpg" title="Large image of the outside of the Iraq Museum" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link> (304 KB).</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>When the new Iraq Museum building was finished in 1966, a stone statue of a guardian - one of two statues from the entrance of <esp:link page="ezida">Nabu's shrine</esp:link> in his temple at Nimrud - was placed outside (<b>Image 7</b>). The plan for the new museum building was by a German architect called <esp:glossary term="March, Werner (person)">Werner March</esp:glossary> and he tried to make it look like <esp:link url="http://www.islamic-architecture.info/WA-IQ/WA-IQ-018.htm" rel="external" hide-print="yes">a traditional Iraqi house</esp:link>. I personally think he succeeded in doing that.</p>



<esp:image file="im/IM-3.jpg" description="Photograph of Assyrian gallery at the Iraq Museum, with stone relief panels lining the walls and free-standing stone statues in the centre" position="inline"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/im/IM-3-large.jpg" title="Large version of Assyrian gallery"  hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img186"><b>Image 8</b></esp:bookmark>: Displays of material from Khorsabad and Nimrud at the Iraq Museum. Image: Iraq Museum. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/im/IM-3-large.jpg" title="Large image of Assyrian gallery" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link> (82 KB).</esp:caption></esp:image>


<p><b>Image 8</b> is one of the early photographs in the new museum, after 1966, with the Nimrud material visible at the back. The throne base of <esp:glossary term="Shalmaneser III (person)">Shalmaneser III</esp:glossary> is partly visible at the far end of the room. </p>

<p>If you were to look at the winged bulls up close, you would see parallel incisions on them. This is damage that was done in the 1990s when the <esp:techterms term="Ministry of Culture">Ministry of Culture</esp:techterms> wanted to have a replica of these statues made to put inside the Ministry building. The incisions happened when they were making a mould of the object, and it’s apparently been very difficult to remedy them.</p>

<esp:image file="im/IM-2008.jpg" description="Photograph of Iraq Museum Assyrian displays" position="inline"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/im/IM-2008-large.jpg" title="Large version of Assyrian displays in 2008"  hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img187"><b>Image 9</b></esp:bookmark>:  Assyrian displays at the Iraq Museum in 2008. The 4-metre high <esp:link page="shalmaneser3" bookmark="img61">panel of glazed bricks</esp:link> on the rear wall comes from king <esp:link page="shalmaneser3">Shalmaneser III</esp:link>'s palace at Nimrud, now known as <esp:link page="fortshalmaneser">Fort Shalmaneser</esp:link> (IM 72136). Image: Lamia Al-Gailani Werr. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/im/IM-2008-large.jpg" title="Large image of Assyrian displays in 2008" hide-print="yes">View large image</esp:link> (457 KB).</esp:caption></esp:image>


<p><b>Image 9</b> shows what the galleries looked like in 2008. Nimrud material has been separated from the Khorsabad material and for the first time, they have produced information panels with text in both English and Arabic. The writing is rather small and you have to be very close to read it, but having panels is a big improvement.</p>


<!--IMAGE I’m just showing the Nimrud one—a panel. And that’s what it is, more or less, today. It was once nicer when you had it all open. It’s more impressive than having this, sort of… wall behind, and hid…  the Nimrud material. The other thing is, the Nimrud bulls are—before that, during that time, the next room, the next very last room used to be the Hatra material and material from the Parthian period. That has been removed to another because the museum got, was expanded, so the Hatra statues and so on were taken to another one. And this one was supposed to be for Assyrian material, and they put, at the time… The smaller material was exhibited, but not very good, so it looks like they decided to do something else. But the Italians decided, until they do that, they did a picture gallery of Assyrian sculpture from Nineveh and Nimrud. And these statues—the head underneath is newly—I mean, newly discovered but 1990—it’s not discovered, it was cut by looters from Khorsabad in the 90s, and they couldn’t carry it because the head of a bull, it’s about, I don’t know, a tonne in weight. And they couldn’t, so they really cut it. You can see, at the top, they cut it into six pieces. They were found, and… um, the antiquity laws had to be amended because, apparently four of the looters were found, and they were executed at the time. Um, now they are amending it again, and I don’t know… there’s a lot of… debate about this, death sentence for the looters. It’s a bit… you know. I mean, my comment, because I was asked, ‘what do you think?’ I said, you don’t… you don’t execute somebody because he stole the head of Hammurabi. Honestly. {laughs} Certainly right. So, I don’t know. It will discussed sometime very soon, in parliament.


But these two bulls, are now being… have been removed, from this room to the next room, where I showed the picture gallery. Now it’s being prepared for more Assyrian material, and you could see… like when they brought them to the British Museum, these ones are being also removed. And they are being put in a new location. Not much difference from what… Layard did. [slide?] Just moving them. [slide?] Just moving them. And they are being put. All these sort of, what do you call it, the wires and so on, on top. It’s going to stay more or less like that. Its going to give the idea of a door, but they are not going to make a door really. This is the idea. And on top—all these sort of panels on top of it—it’s to give the idea of a ceiling, but it’s open because on top of, on this first floor, there is another gallery and they don’t want to close it.
IMAGE There is, sort of the idea. You only, to give the feeling of an… an arched gate.


While the smaller finds are being done into little cases all around, wall cases most of them. IMAGE That’s another one. This is when I was there a few weeks ago, it was like that. Otherwise the cases were like this one. This is the gold material, which was put out in an exhibition in July 2003, because people started saying that they were stolen, saying they were looted or that Saddam has taken them, and so on. And so by the end the American authorities decided that the best thing was put them out for exhibition. The gold, it was wonderful to see again—for three hours only, publicly, and then it went back to the bank.

New cases also were brought by the cultural fund from the American embassy.
IMAGE These were the cases when I saw them, over a year ago. Because again, they were, the museum tried in 2009—to open the museum, and these cases were used for the ivories later on. But then the ivories—or what left of the ivories—the ivories went back into storage, and… I don’t know what’s going to happen now. I think these are the… the new cases I showed you will be for the ivories and small finds. This is how they were exhibiting the tablets and the cuneiform objects from Nimrud. Like that.

IMAGE This is the back—John, you showed it. You showed that one—this one. I think this is the one that was stolen. Found in Jordan, but in quite a bad state.
IMAGE There it is again. Yeah. And so they were…the conservators started working on it. Most of the ivories in the museum that were not stolen - quite a lot of them, as John said - some of them went to about 30 pieces.
[slide?] This one is much more than 30 pieces. There is the conservator sitting.I think one of them is telling them what to do.
IMAGE And this is one of BISI’s scholars, [Faisa?] here, working on conserving tablets from Nimrud. She sent me the photograph.
IMAGE A new storage building has been added to the old one, so the new one is the lighter brick, and with it, quite a number of new panels and new shelves for the material. One of them is this room, with all the shelves for the antiquities. And for the ivory, small objects and tablets, these are the cases and cabinets that were brought from Germany.

IMAGE And last I want to show the ledgers where the Nimrud material was recorded - the catalogues. And one page from page 1, where everybody signed that they’ve done the division. And so you’ve got the names of Jeffrey Orchard, David Oates, Taha Baqir, Fuad Safar, and Selim al-Jelili. And that’s it.-->


<p><i>This page is based on Dr al-Gailani's talk given at the</i> <esp:link page="moundmuseum">Nimrud: Mound to Museum</esp:link> <i>study day in April 2013.</i></p>

<p><small>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/>.<br/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/></small></p>

<esp:author first-names="Lamia" last-name="al-Gailani Werr"/>

</body></html>
</esp:page>
