<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<esp:page
	xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
>

	<esp:name>Nabu</esp:name>
	<esp:title>Nabu, god of wisdom</esp:title>

	<html><head>
</head><body>
	
<p class="firstpara">Nabu, god of wisdom, was originally a Babylonian deity. However, over the course of the 1st millennium BC he became increasingly important in Assyria too. At first he was venerated primarily by literate bureaucrats and <esp:techterms term="scholar">scholars</esp:techterms>, but by the end of the 8th century BC he had also become a central member of the Assyrian royal cult. He had  at Kalhu, Nineveh, and (briefly) at Dur-Šarruken and Assur.</p>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/nabu-temple-isometric-detail.png" description="Isometric plan of Nabu's temple at Kalhu" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/nabu-temple-isometric-large.png" title="View large image of isometric plan of Nabu's temple at Kalhu" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img231"><b>Image 1.</b> Detail from an isometric plan of the Ezida temple in Kalhu, showing the tablet room in close proximity to the god's sanctuary <esp:ref referent="mallowan1966" page="233, Figure 195"/></esp:bookmark>. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/nabu-temple-isometric-large.png" title="View large image of isometric plan of Nabu's temple at Kalhu" hide-print="yes">View large image (251 KB)</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>


<esp:h>Babylonian origins</esp:h>

<p>As the <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/amgg/listofdeities/nabu/" rel="external" title="Nabu on AMGG" hide-print="yes">Ancient Mesopotamian Gods and Goddesses website explains</esp:link>, the earliest reference to Nabu is in the ancient Syrian city of Ebla in the 24th century BC. In early 2nd millennium Babylonia, Nabu was portrayed as a <esp:techterms term="scribe">scribe</esp:techterms> of the great god <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/amgg/listofdeities/marduk" hide-print="yes" rel="external">Marduk</esp:link>. But he did not have his own temple and did not feature at all in Old Babylonian royal inscriptions.</p> 

<p>By about 1100 BC Nabu had developed his first-millennium characteristics as lord of wisdom, first-born son of the supreme Babylonian deity Marduk, and lord of Ezida - the "true house" temple in <esp:glossary term="Borsippa (place)">Borsippa</esp:glossary>. At around this time he also become particularly important to the Babylonian royal family <esp:ref referent="pomponio1998-2001" page="17–19"/>.</p>

<esp:h>Nabu in Assur</esp:h>

<p>The earliest concrete evidence for Nabu’s involvement in Assyrian scholarship come from the reign of <esp:glossary term="Tiglath-pileser I (person)">Tiglath-pileser I</esp:glossary>. A scribe named <esp:glossary term="Aššur-šumi-aṣbat (person)">Aššur-šumi-aṣbat</esp:glossary> working in the royal palace at <esp:glossary term="Assur (place)">Assur</esp:glossary> had this prayer inscribed on his personal cylinder seal:</p>

<blockquote><p>At the command of Nabu, exalted son of <esp:glossary term="Ekur (place)">Ekur</esp:glossary> (or: of the temple), <br/>
for the days I am alive, let me obtain justice, <br/>
let me uphold truth and rightness.<br/>
As soon as I enter the palace each time,<br/> 
may my steps go well.<br/>
Seal of the scribe Aššur-šumi-aṣbat, <br/>
son of the royal scribe Ribatu <esp:ref referent="deller1982"/>. </p></blockquote>

<p>Here Aššur-šumi-aṣbat invokes Nabu’s guidance in serving the palace to the best of his ability, by behaving with appropriate decorum ("may my steps go well") as well as by acting wisely and fairly ("let me obtain justice, let me uphold truth and rightness").</p>

<p>Similarly, the scribe <esp:glossary term="Aššur-išmanni (person)">Aššur-išmanni</esp:glossary>, who also served as one of Tiglath-pileser I’s <esp:techterms term="eponym">eponym</esp:techterms> officials, wrote a dedication to <esp:glossary term="Tašmetu (deity)">Tašmetu</esp:glossary>, Nabu’s divine spouse <esp:ref referent="grayson1991" page="83-84, A.0.87.2001"/>. However, Tiglath-pileser’s own inscriptions do not mention Nabu at all <esp:ref referent="grayson1991" page="7-71, A.0.87.1-30"/>. This suggests that at this time Nabu did not feature in royal cult but was worshipped in a personal capacity by senior literate state officials.</p>

<esp:h>Trust in Nabu! The magnates of Kalhu</esp:h>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/nabu-attendant-im.jpg" description="Stone statue of bearded human figure with hands clasped together" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/nabu-attendant-im-large.jpg" title="View large image of stone attendant statue" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img222"><b>Image 2.</b> Stone statue of a bearded attendant, one of a pair that stood at the entrance to Nabu's temple. The <esp:link page="ezida" bookmark="img10">other attendant statue</esp:link> is now in the British Museum.</esp:bookmark> <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/nabu-attendant-im-large.jpg" title="View large image of stone attendant statue" hide-print="yes">View large image (160 KB)</esp:link>. Photo: Eleanor Robson.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>This trend continued at Kalhu (<esp:link bookmark="img221"><b>Image 1</b></esp:link>). When <esp:link page="assurnasirpal2">Assurnasirpal II</esp:link> made the city his capital in the early 9th century BC, a temple to Nabu was a very late addition to the <esp:techterms term="citadel">citadel</esp:techterms>, and did not feature <esp:link page="inscriptions">royal inscriptions</esp:link>. In fact, a king is named in just two places in the temple itself. Twin statues of divine attendants, 1.8m high, were placed to look from the gateway of Nabu’s antecella into the courtyard below—and into the <esp:techterms term="tablet">tablet</esp:techterms> store opposite (<esp:link bookmark="img222"><b>Image 2</b></esp:link>). They are dedicated to Nabu for the life of king <esp:glossary term="Adad-nerari III (person)">Adad-nerari III</esp:glossary> (r. 810-783 BC) and send a strong message of a personal relationship between the god and a human being:</p>

<blockquote><p>To Nabu, heroic (and) exalted, son of <esp:glossary term="Esaggila (place)">Esaggila</esp:glossary>, wise (and) splendid, mighty prince, heir of Nudimmud, whose command is supreme, skilled in the arts, trustee of all heaven and underworld, expert in everything, wise, the holder of the tablet <esp:techterms term="stylus">stylus</esp:techterms>, learned in the scribal art, merciful (and) judicious, who has the power to depopulate (and) repopulate (a country), beloved of the god Ellil, lord of lords, whose might has no rival, without whom there can be no order in heaven, the merciful (and) compassionate whose benevolence is good, dweller in Ezida, which is within Kalhu, the great lord, his lord:</p>

<p>For the life of Adad-nerari, king of Assyria, his lord, and (for) the life of Sammu-ramat, the palace woman, his mistress: Bel-tarṣi-ilumma, <esp:techterms term="governor">governor</esp:techterms> of Kalhu (and) the lands of <esp:glossary term="Hamedu (place)">Hamedu</esp:glossary>, <esp:glossary term="Sirgana (place)">Sirgana</esp:glossary>, <esp:glossary term="Temenu (place)">Temenu</esp:glossary>, (and) <esp:glossary term="Yaluna (place)">Yaluna</esp:glossary>, has had (this statue) made and dedicated (it) for his life, that his days might be long, his years many, (for) the well-being of his household and people, (and) that he might not become ill.</p>
<p>Whoever you are, after (me), trust in Nabu! Do not trust in another god! [Translation after <esp:ref referent="grayson1996" page="227, A.0.104.2002"/>]</p></blockquote>

<p>The statues' commissioner, <esp:glossary term="Bel-tarṣi-ilumma (person)">Bel-tarṣi-ilumma</esp:glossary>, was <esp:glossary term="Adad-nerari III (person)">Adad-nerari’s</esp:glossary> <esp:techterms term="eponym">eponym</esp:techterms> official in 797 BC <esp:ref referent="millard1994" page="57"/> and a particular devotee of Nabu. His personal <esp:techterms term="seal, sealing">seal</esp:techterms> was found on sealings and a tablet in his <esp:link page="governorspalace">Governor’s Palace</esp:link>, right next door to the Ezida <esp:ref referent="postgatereade1976-1980" page="316"/>. The seal's inscription ends:</p>

 <blockquote><p>I have trusted in you, let me not be put to shame, O Nabu! <esp:ref referent="grayson1996" page="228, A.0.104.2003:6-7"/></p></blockquote>
 
<p>Bel-tarṣi-ilumma was not the only senior court official with a particular affinity for the god of wisdom. <esp:glossary term="Nergal-ilaʾi (person)">Nergal-ilaʾi</esp:glossary>, Adad-nerari’s <i>turtānu</i> ("commander-in-chief"), inscribed a 5kg stone weight in the shape of a duck, which was found in the goddess <esp:glossary term="Tašmetu (deity)">Tašmetu</esp:glossary>’s shrine. Lower down the ranks, the scribe <esp:glossary term="Nabu-šallim-ahhe (person)">Nabu-šallim-ahhe</esp:glossary> dedicated a mace-head "to Nabu, his lord, for his life". It was discovered just outside the so-called "<esp:link page="ezida" bookmark="heyday">Fish Gate</esp:link>" <esp:ref referent="mallowan1966" page="257, 269 (vol. I)"/>.</p>

<p>In the light of all this evidence, it seems that in the 9th century BC Nabu was not a prominent figure in the divine pantheon of Kalhu. The temple did not attract much, if any, royal patronage, but was perhaps rather an entrepreneurial initiative by literate senior officials such as Kalhu's governor Bel-tarṣi-ilumma. The project must have been carried out with the king’s blessing, almost certainly, for it entailed large-scale demolition and rebuilding on the royal citadel. But - as we have seen - all the inscriptional and geographical evidence points to personal piety rather than official cult.  </p>

<esp:h>Royal involvement: Sargon II and Dur-Šarruken</esp:h>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/detail-Nabu-temple-Dur-Sharruken-drawing-Loud-Altman-1938-p12.jpg" description="Drawing of restoration of Nabu's temple at Khorsabad" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/Nabu-temple-Dur-Sharruken-drawing-Loud-Altman-1938-p12.jpg" title="View large image of restoration of Nabu's temple" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img221"><b>Image 3.</b> Artist's impression from 1938 of Nabu's temple in Dur-Šarruken, viewed from the royal palace</esp:bookmark>  <esp:ref referent="loudaltman1938" page="12"/>. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/Nabu-temple-Dur-Sharruken-drawing-Loud-Altman-1938-p12.jpg" title="View large image of restoration of Nabu's temple" hide-print="yes">View large image (559 KB)</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>While both Assurnasirpal II and Adad-nerari III supported their <esp:techterms term="magnate">magnates’</esp:techterms> trust in Nabu, they kept the cult at arm’s length. It was only under <esp:glossary term="Sargon II (person)">Sargon II</esp:glossary> that Nabu and his scholars became fully integrated into the highest echelons of court life. Even that was not an instant transformation.</p>

<p><esp:bookmark id="musasir" title="Sargon's capture of Musasir">The turning point was the capture of the northern city of <esp:glossary term="Muṣaṣir (place)">Muṣaṣir</esp:glossary> in 714 BC</esp:bookmark>. Assyrian <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/aebp/essentials/countries/urartu" hide-print="yes" rel="external">plundering of the god Haldi's ancient and wealthy temple</esp:link> not only secured Sargon’s military reputation but also brought in substantial wealth, doubly confirming his right to rule. The famous <i>Letter to Aššur</i>, a report of his 8th military campaign, opens with acknowledgement of "the great support of Aššur, <esp:glossary term="Šamaš (deity)">Šamaš</esp:glossary>, Nabu (and) Marduk" <esp:ref referent="thureaudangin1912" page="5:i 13"/> and consistently treats Nabu - always paired with his father Marduk - as a key factor in its success. Famously, it also contains the earliest extant reference to omens determining the course of an Assyrian military campaign:</p>

<blockquote><p>At the exalted command of Nabu and Marduk (i.e. Mercury and Jupiter), who took a course through the positions of the stars (which signified) a good <esp:techterms term="omen">omen</esp:techterms> for the taking up of my weapons, and favourable signs which mean the gaining of power, <esp:glossary term="Sin (deity)">Sin</esp:glossary>, lord of the crown, remained eclipsed for a watch, (a portent) for the ruination of the Guti. At the invaluable consent of the hero Šamaš, who caused the liver to be inscribed with reiable omens that he would walk at my side … I took the road to Muṣaṣir, a difficult path <esp:ref referent="oppenheim1960" page="136-138"/>.</p></blockquote>

<p>Here, observed planetary and lunar omens are confirmed through the taking of <esp:techterms term="extispicy">extispicies</esp:techterms>, as also in 7th century court practice. Clearly, then, the scholars had proved their worth - and the value of their gods—to Assyrian kingship. This was spectacular, decisive proof of scholarship’s value in predicting and determining the outcome of battle by maintaining  clear lines of communication with the gods.</p>

<p>From this point onwards, Nabu occurs routinely, if not inevitably, in Sargon's royal inscriptions as far afield as <esp:glossary term="Cyprus (place)">Cyprus</esp:glossary> and northwest Iran.</p>

<p>Sargon’s victory at Muṣaṣir proved a turning point, for the rich spoils enabled him to complete the construction of a new capital city, <esp:glossary term="Dur-Šarruken (place)">Dur-Šarruken</esp:glossary> (modern <esp:glossary term="Khorsabad (place)">Khorsabad</esp:glossary>), some 50 kilometres upriver from Kalhu, which had already begun in 717 BC. Unconstrained by existing building, Sargon’s planners were free to create the royal citadel in Dur-Šarruken exactly as the king wanted. That new vision put Nabu at its very heart. In one of the earliest Dur-Šarruken inscriptions, written in 713 (or soon after) on clay cylinders deposited all over the citadel, Sargon claims to have commissioned the bricks for the palace "on the day of an <i>eššēšu</i>-festival for <esp:glossary term="Bel (deity)">Bel’s</esp:glossary> son, the exceedingly wise Nabu, scribe of everything, who gives orders to all the gods".</p>  

<p>Sargon built an enormous temple for Nabu right next door to the palace (<esp:link bookmark="img221"><b>Image 3</b></esp:link>), linked by a private bridge <esp:ref referent="loudaltman1938" page="56-65"/>. It was was bigger and better than the one at Kalhu, though clearly heavily influenced by it. And while, as we have seen, the Kalhu Ezida lacked royal inscriptions, the major thresholds of its successor at Dur-Šarruken were inscribed with a prayer, proclaiming Sargon’s piety towards Nabu:</p>

<blockquote><p>O Nabu, scribe of the universe, controller of harmony: (as for) Sargon, king of the world, king of Assyria, city governor of Babylon, king of Sumer and Akkad, builder of your shrine—look steadily with firm heart and direct your just face towards him, provide him with many days of bodily good health and fix years of wellbeing as his fate.</p>

<p>May his reign be as long as heaven and earth; may he perform the shepherdship of all the lands; may his foundations be as firmly established as this building (site) and platform! [Translation after <esp:ref referent="fuchs1994" page="370, no. 3.2.5"/>]</p></blockquote>

<!-- <p>Sargon died inauspiciously in battle in the summer of 705 BC, and - even more inauspiciously - his body was never found. His son and heir <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/knpp/essentials/sennacherib" hide-print="yes" rel="external">Sennacherib</esp:link> ordered the court to move to <esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/knpp/essentials/nineveh" hide-print="yes" rel="external">Nineveh</esp:link> for a fresh beginning. Sennacherib was quick to distance himself from many of his father’s policies and attitudes, not only his abandoned capital city Dur-Šarruken. Marduk disappeared completely from Sennacherib’s royal inscriptions and Nabu was greatly demoted ADD as ref. (Landsberger, Parpola and Tadmor 1989: 26; Pomponio 1998–2001: 19). Sennacherib commissioned no building work on any of Nabu’s temples and never mentioned him in any of his copious royal inscriptions, except in occasional collective invocations to all the great gods for their blessings or curses (Pomponio 1978: 78–9).</p> -->

<esp:h>Nabu at Nineveh</esp:h>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/BM-K2529-rev.jpg" description="Reverse side of cuneiform tablet inscribed with finely written text" position="float"><esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=1324486&amp;objectId=311065&amp;partId=1" title="View large image on British Museum website" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img220"><b>Image 4.</b> A catalogue of laments, excavated from the ruins of Nabu's temple in Nineveh, dedicated to Nabu and Tašmetu by "prince Assurbanipal for the preservation of his life"</esp:bookmark>, <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=311065&amp;partId=1&amp;searchText=K.2529&amp;page=1" title="View large image" hide-print="yes">K. 2529</esp:link>. <esp:link url="http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details/collection_image_gallery.aspx?assetId=1324486&amp;objectId=311065&amp;partId=1" title="View large image" hide-print="yes">View large image on the British Museum's website</esp:link>. © Trustees of the British Museum.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Nineveh had been an important Assyrian city for many centuries. Nabu had a temple on the citadel from at least the early 8th century. The standard Assyrian <esp:techterms term="eponym">eponym list</esp:techterms>, which rarely mentions particular events, tersely notes: "foundations of Nabu’s temple in Nineveh laid" in 788 BC (Adad-nerari's 23rd regnal year) and "Nabu entered the new temple" in 787 (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saas2/Q004243" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAAS 2: 2</esp:link>). Unfortunately we know almost nothing else about this temple until the reign of <esp:link page="assurbanipal">Assurbanipal</esp:link>.</p>

<p>As a boy Assurbanipal had trained for the priesthood because he was not a direct heir to the Assyrian throne <esp:ref referent="novotnysingletary2009"/>. However, when his father nominated him as <esp:techterms term="crown prince">crown prince</esp:techterms> in 672, he cannily made the most of this unorthodox preparation for the role, and headed off possible worries about his suitability, by stressing his identification with the scholarly Nabu, "crown prince of the gods" as Marduk’s heir (<esp:link bookmark="img220"><b>Image 4</b></esp:link>).</p> 

<p>Assurbanipal’s scholarly ambitions and personal devotion to Nabu are very well known <esp:ref referent="livingstone2007"/>, <esp:ref referent="frahm2011"/>. They are manifested in prayers and dialogues with the god (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa03/P336226,P313430" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAA 3: 6, 13</esp:link>), the <esp:techterms term="colophon">colophons</esp:techterms> on his extensive personal collection of scholarly tablets which comprise "almost every tablet of importance in the <esp:techterms term="Kuyunjik collection">Kouyunjik Collection</esp:techterms>" <esp:ref referent="lieberman1990"/>, as well as  numerous official inscriptions and the repair programmes for Nabu’s temples in Kalhu and Nineveh <esp:ref referent="pomponio1998-2001" page="20"/>.</p>

<p>In 652 BC, Assurbanipal's "favourite brother" <esp:glossary term="Šamaš-šumu-ukin (person)">Šamaš-šumu-ukin</esp:glossary> turned traitor and allied with his <esp:glossary term="Elam (place)">Elamite</esp:glossary> neighbours to wage a war for Babylonian independence. In keeping with his lack of military training, Assurbanipal did not lead the army in the field but stayed in Nineveh. He used his scholarly abilities to ensure divine support for Assyria through reading <esp:techterms term="celestial">celestial</esp:techterms> <esp:techterms term="omen">omens</esp:techterms> and inducing <esp:techterms term="prophet(ess)">prophetic messages</esp:techterms> from <esp:glossary term="Ištar (deity)">Ištar</esp:glossary>. After the victory, as a gesture of thanks to his divine counterpart Assurbanipal enlarged and repaved the main courtyard of Ezida in Nineveh, attributing the ultimate success of his military strategy to "the placing of (Nabu’s) order and the giving of his weighty command". Assurbanipal’s learned, non-combatant approach to kingship looked to be amply justified.</p>

<esp:h>Nabu at the end</esp:h>

<esp:image file="ancientcity/VAT-9948-Falkner-AfO-16-TafelXV.png" description="Line drawing of cuneiform tablet. The tablet's text describes offerings to Nabu and Tašmetu" position="float"><esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/VAT-9948-Falkner-AfO-16-TafelXV-large.png" title="View large image of cuneiform tablet describing offerings to Nabu and Tašmetu" hide-print="yes"/><esp:caption><esp:bookmark id="img232">Tablet recording offerings by Sin-šarru-iškun. He dedicated two gold washing bowls to Nabu and a silver serving spoon to Tašmetu</esp:bookmark>. <esp:ref referent="falkner1952-3" page="plate XV (transcription on page 306)"/> Source: Margarete Falkner, "Neue Inschriften aus der Zeit Sin-šarru-iškuns", AfO 16 (1952-1953), p. 305-310. © Archiv für Orientforschung (AfO), Institut für Orientalistik, Universität Wien. <esp:link url="/nimrud/images/ancientcity/VAT-9948-Falkner-AfO-16-TafelXV-large.png" title="View large image of cuneiform tablet describing offerings to Nabu and Tašmetu" hide-print="yes">View large image (199 KB)</esp:link>.</esp:caption></esp:image>

<p>Over the course of the 640s Assyrian court scholarship fell into a dramatic decline. Cultic activity - if not scholarship - continued at the various Assyrian temples of Nabu. As late as 618<esp:techterms term="eponym">*</esp:techterms> BC palace personnel were still making small but high-value <esp:techterms term="votive">votive</esp:techterms> offerings to Nabu in the Nineveh Ezida (<esp:link url="http://oracc.org/saao/saa07/P336209" hide-print="yes" rel="external">SAA 7: 81</esp:link>). At Kalhu too, the Ezida continued to function perhaps right until the end of empire. </p>

<p>The final big gesture of Assyrian royal reverence for Nabu was made by, or for, <esp:glossary term="Sin-šarru-iškun (person)">Sin-šarru-iškun</esp:glossary> (r. c.627–612 BC), the last king of Assyria. During the very first year of his reign, when he must still have been a child, a completely new temple to Nabu and Tašmetu was constructed in the heart of <esp:glossary term="Assur (place)">Assur</esp:glossary>, the ancestral city.</p>

<p>Sin-šarru-iškun's inscriptions say that Nabu's original temple in Assur had "turned into waste-land, became (nothing but) ground" and so Nabu and Tašmetu had taken up residence in Ištar's temple. In fact, there is no independent evidence for an earlier building, and it is likely that the divine pair had had shrines in Ištar's temple all along.</p>

<p>Whatever the truth of the matter, Sin-šarru-iškun now gave them their own cult centre, based on earlier models, with twin shrines and antechambers for the divine couple and a throne room for himself. He also dedicated two gold washing bowls to Nabu and a <esp:techterms term="silver">silver</esp:techterms> serving spoon to Tašmetu.</p> 

<p>However, there is no architectural or inscriptional evidence that the temple ever served as a scholarly centre and Sin-šarru-iškun characterises Nabu as an "honest judge who speaks truth and justice" rather than as a learned scribe. Just as scholars had disappeared from Assyrian court circles, so had the image of Nabu as the divine patron of scholarship.</p>

<!-- further reading-->
<esp:reading referent="pomponio1978"/>
<esp:reading referent="pomponio1998-2001"/>

<esp:author first-names="Eleanor" last-name="Robson"/>
<esp:email address="nimrud@oracc.org"/>
<p><small>Content last modified: <esp:content-last-modified/>.</small></p>
	</body></html>

</esp:page>
